<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>DramaMusicCeremony_Civic</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

			<div>
				<head>Drama, Music, and Ceremonial Customs</head>
				<p>Ceremonial occasions involving music and often other performance activities abounded in
				medieval and early Tudor London: from religious processions, on set feast–days, in which the
				city officers and the Mcompanies took part (which are not the concern of REED), to the secular
				processions of the mayor&apos;s oath–taking and sheriffs presentation annually, to and from
				Westminster, to the formal entries – at a variety of musical and visualedisplay levels– of
				royalty and other important personages into the city. In at least the late fourteenth and
				early fifteenth centuries a multi–day biblical play– the London equivalent of the Cornish
				Ordinalia and of the biblical play cycles of centres such as Tork– was performed just outside
				the city walls at Clerkenwell/Skinners Well. Street celebrations of occasions such as a roya
				birth, a military victory abroad, or the conclusion of a peace treaty, might also be ordered
				by the civic authorities (usually in response to a directive from the Crown). More informal
				occasions of street revelry might involve hockings, mayings, and officially or unofficially
				sanctioned –or sometimes prohibited – misrule and other festivities in the Christmas or
				May seasons. At midsummer every year came two nights of festive celebration, including
				from at least the late fourteenth century, a visually impressive and (from some time in the
				fifteenth century) increasingly theatrical marching watch: the Midsummer Watch. The
				companies had their annual, biennial, or triennial feast times, mixing religious and secular
				observances, such as dirges, masses, election of company officers, and dinners with enter*
				tainments of various kinds, and other special occasions could also involve performances.
				The city might send entertainments to the court, or itself entertain royalty, nobility, foreign
				ambassadors, and the like, at magnificent dinners and on occasions such as the Midsummer
				Watch. Almost all of these occasions would have involved music, especially trumpeters for
				processions, although manuscript records often do not note it. Some involved constructed
				wood–and–canvas pageants, with or without performers, either carried through the streets by
				porters (as in the Midsummer Watch) or placed on fixed stages along a processional route
				(as in royal entries). Some involved mummings, plays, acrobats, juggling, and other forms
				of entertainment, such as tumbling and animal acts.</p>
			</div>
				<div>
				<head>Formal Entries</head>
				<p>Information on entries into London, from the basic to the highly elaborate, comes in large
				part from sources such as chronicle histories, supplemented to varying extents, from the late
				fourteenth century on, by the civic records. London&apos;s proximity to Westminster, as already
				noted, resulted in the city being frequently called upon to provide– below the level of corona*
				tion and other such major ceremonial entries into and through the city– welcomes, escortings
				lodgings, feasts, gifts, and the like, to important visitors to the court such as ambassadors,
				papal emissaries and minor royalty. The city also often met and escorted the monarch or his[her
				consort, by land or by water, on standard comings and goings to and from Westminster. These
				activities in large part do not appear in this collection, because sources do not often mention
				music or theatrical activity in relation to them, although music was doubtless often involved€
				but in a few cases, especially in the sixteenth century, music is recorded. The most important
				and expensive occasions are normally recorded in the sources with reference to music and
				pageantry, and so appear in this collection&apos;s records, Appendix I, or both. These occasions
				were the formal entries provided only for especially important visitors to the court, such as
				the emperor Charles V in 1522, and for English monarchs themselves, and their consorts,
				usually only on the occasion of their coronations. Some historical background on coronation
				entry requirements has already been provided above (p xv). Before the late fourteenth century,
				our information on coronation and similarly elaborate royal entries comes largely from the
				chronicles, and not at all from the civic records: from 1377 on, we have a varying mix of
				civic records and other sources. By the late fourteenth century it is possible to talk about a
				standard format, which probably existed much earlier, for major formal entries, although
				not all of such entries conformed to all aspects of the pattern, and in some cases we have
				insufficient entry information to know.</p>

<p>
	The standard coronation or other such major entry, by at least the late fourteenth centu*
				ry, seems normally to have involved the individual concerned– English monarch, royal
				consort, visiting foreign monarch– being met just outside the city (most often to the south,
				at Blackheath) by the mayor and other city officers on horseback, accompanied by a large
				number of citizens, all in formal liveries, and by musicians (doubtless especially trumpeters)
				After official greetings, the individual and his[her entourage would be escorted by the civic
				party into and through London. The streets would be decorated with banners and rich
				cloths hung from windows and doors: the streets would be gravelled (and the Bridge sanded
				or gravelled) for the passage of the horses. Along the processional route, stationary pageants
				consisting of constructed set pieces, role–playing performers, or both, and featuring saints,
				angels, castles, personified virtues, genealogical trees, and the like– would normally be
				displayed at customary locations. Mechanical devices would often be incorporated into
				one or more of the pageants: and one or more water conduits would usually (especially
				for coronation entries) run with wine. Individual pageants could be designed with special
				reference to the honoured entrant: St Margaret, for example, in one pageant welcoming
				Margaret of Anjou in 1445, and biblical mothers (such as St Anne), with children, in a
				pageant for the pregnant Anne Boleyn at her 1533 coronation entry. The ordered series
				of pageants could be designed according to a particular relevant theme: for example, as
				Gordon kipling has argued, that of the elegiac dream vision of ascent to glory, for the
				1501 entry of Ratherine of Aragon coming to marry the heir to the English throne, Prince
				Arthur.5 From at least the late fifteenth century, and probably earlier, the companies in
				their liveries would line the streets for a major entry, using standings (also called rails,
				scaffolds, frames, or sometimes stages): these, provided by the companies themselves, were
				wooden constructions temporarily set up along the sides of the streets and consisting of
				rails along the front of low platforms. The companies in their liveries functioned both as
				an official part of entry display and as a means of crowd control, since other spectators
				of the entry would be behind them. The rails also served as protection from the passing
				horses for those in the front line.S Each company was assigned to a particular stretch of
				the entry route: and ecclesiastics would also have their arranged positions, at the locations
				of their churches or religious houses where these were on the route.</p>
					<p>
				The traditional land route for major entries, from at least the fourteenth century and
				probably long before, was from Southwark across London Bridge and then, for non–coronation
				entrants, up Bridge Street and (New) Fish Street to Gracechurch Street and to Cornhill
				then west along Cornhill, Poultry, and Cheapside to St Paul&apos;s, and beyond St Paul&apos;s through
				Ludgate and along Fleet Street, past Temple Bar to Westminster (unless the entrant was to
				stay at the Bishop&apos;s Palace at St Paul&apos;s, or elsewhere between St Paul&apos;s and Westminster).
				Non–coronation entries took place entirely on one day. Coronation entries, from at least
				the end of the fourteenth century, were two–day affairs, as the monarch was required (as
				noted above, p xv), from at least 1377 and probably earlier, to process, on the day before
				the coronation, from the Tower of London (royal territory although within the city walls)
				through the city to Westminster. The monarch&apos;s procession to the Tower (usually, before
				1483, across the Bridge) on a preceding day (usually, until 1485, the day before) had thus
				probably also become a part of the formal entry from very early on.s From at least the mid–
				fifteenth century, royal consorts coming to be crowned at Westminster were also required
				to follow the two–day process, and sources show a two–day format for their entries from at
				least 130677. The specifics of the coronation land–entry route for the first day, from the
				Bridge to the Tower, are not usually provided in entry descriptions: but in 1420 Henry vi
				went via Fenchurch Street, that is, by a circuitous route up Bridge Street and (New) Fish
				Street to Gracechurch Street (northwest of the Tower), then east along Fenchurch Street
				to Mark Lane, and back south down Mark Lane to Tower Street and the Tower. In 1485
				Henry viI and in 1500 Henry vi1 are said to have gone to the Tower via Grace Church,
				which suggests that the same route was followed (Bridge Street, Fish Street, Gracechurch
				Street, and so forth) as that taken by Henry vi in 1420.10 Perhaps this was the traditional
				route– not direct, but a ceremonial loop, along comparatively wide streets. On a second
				day (from 1485 not usually the next day) the entrant proceeded from the Tower back to
				Gracechurch Street via Tower Street, Mark Lane, and Fenchurch Street, and then along
				the established route, from Gracechurch Street to Cheapside, St Paul&apos;s, and eventually
				Westminster. The coronation took place the next day. From 1483 a water procession to the
				Tower, with elaborate water pageants in at least both 1487 and 1533, began to replace the
				preTower coronation land procession across the Bridge. From 1483 to 1558, only two of eight
				coronation entrants, Henry vil in 1485 and Henry vIl in 1500, made a land procession
				across the Bridge to the Tower.12</p>
					<p>
				Constructed land pageants for major entries, coronation and non–coronation, go back at
				least as far as 1357, and probably at least to the thirteenth century. The city&apos;s own manuscript
				records of such pageants, together with the pageant records of the companies, do not go back
				further than 1377: but chroniclers earlier use words such as prodigialibus adinventionibus
				to describe city entry display, and Appendix I includes a number of pre–1377 entries, which
				may have included (and in 1357 definitely included) one or more constructed or performed
				pageants.8 The castle– perhaps from 1200, 1308, and[or 1357 and definitely from 1377–is SC
				far the earliest identified type of stationary constructed pageant, although the entry activity
				up to 1415, of scattering real or mock gold and[or silver coins or leaves, can be found as
				early as 1274, and from at least 1377 is associated with a castle./ The castle was apparently a
				staple of constructed pageantry: at first always in Cheapside, with the coins or leaves scatterec
				by maidens. Castles emblematically could represent, separately or in combinations, a variety
				of physical and spiritual entities: for example, a city, a political state, heaven, hell, the Nev
				]erusalem, the virgin body.</p>
					<p>
				Constructed pageants for major entries were normally located along the traditiona
				processional route at customary points where street width permitted and [or where existing
				structures along or in the streets (such as water conduits) could serve as a foundation or
				backdrop for them: and the number of pageants in a major entry grew over time, perhaps not
				only because of the natural pressures for each celebration not simply to equal but to surpass
				preceding celebrations but also in part because of the increasing number of advantageous
				structural locations for pageants. The Great Conduit in Cheapside, for example, had beer
				built by c 1245 and was in use in 1200 (for the entry of Margaret of France) at least as an
				entry wine outlet and perhaps as a pageant location.S The Little Conduit, at the western
				end of Cheapside, was begun in 1380 (and rebuilt or completed in 1440–1), and pageants
				start to be recorded there at least by 1415.1 The conduit in Gracechurch Street was begun
				in 1401, and pageants were sometimes located there in the sixteenth century.s A good
				number of other pageant locations are recorded, in recurring references, over various
				different time periods: Fenchurch Street, Leadenhall (at the intersection of Gracechurch
				Street and Cornhill), the Cornhill conduit, the Stocks, the Standard and the Cross (both in
				Cheapside), St Paul&apos;s, Ludgate, the Fleet Street conduit, Temple Bar.1/ There was always
				at least one pageant in Cheapside– by the fifteenth century usually more than one – and
				although the specific location of early pageants there is not clear, the Cross was especially
				important in the fifteenth century.2 Particular locations in some periods regularly featured
				the same kind of pageant: for example, the castle in Cheapside in perhaps consecutive
				entries from at least 1377 to 1432.2 On London Bridge, with houses and shops lining
				the roadway on both sides, three locations have been identified as suitable for constructed
				pageant displays and singing choirs: at the foot of the Bridge at its south end, in Southwark:
				at the Stonegate (a defensive gatehouse, with towers, on the second pier from the south
				end): and at the Drawbridge gate (a gatehouse with towers, a drawbridge, and a portcullis
				on the seventh pier from the south end).2€ These locations provided both some open space,
				unavailable otherwise on the narrow roadway, and towers and facades not only convenient
				for the positioning of costumed figures and the hanging of decorative cloths and banners, but
				also providing useful support and background for constructed figures and stages.€ From at
				least 1413 to 1554 one or more giants – gatekeepers in folklore৳s– were traditional parts of
				Bridge display for male entrants€€৳ and angels and[or maidens (sometimes specified as in a
				tower) were featured between at least 1415 and 1465.2 Otherwise Bridge pageants seem to
				have varied by entry, suited each time to the particular entrant and occasion. Peace and Plenty:
				for example, and Noahs ark greeted Margaret of Anjou in 1445, since her marriage to Henry vi
				had been arranged to confirm peace between England and France.2 The presence on the
				Bridge of a chapel of St Thomas, with singing priests and clerks, and of St Magnus the Martyr
				Church near the Bridge&apos;s north end, doubtless meant that the Bridge did not lack for readily
				available musical resources for entries (although it could reach farther for them as well). The
				Bridge House accounts record payment, for example, to the child choristers of St Magnus the
				Martyr for their part in the 1465 entry of Elizabeth Woodville.2</p>
				<p>The Bridges liminal status for entrants into London has been emphasized by several recent
				historians, along with its key position as the location of the first pageant(s) in a major entry,
				able to set the tone and theme for the whole.2 The break of one day or more, however, for
				coronation entries, between Bridge pageantry and other city pageantry, would have required
				any thematic connection between Bridge pageants and the city&apos;s pageants to have been
				designed with the break in mind. Also, from 1483, as previously noted, the Thames itself
				began to replace the Bridge in coronation entries, with water pageantry replacing Bridge
				pageantry, although land pageants were featured as usual in the pre–coronation procession
				from the Tower to Westminster. (Non–coronation welcomings, escortings, and the like
				could also involve the Thames. Henry vii, for example, in 1486, was welcomed by the city
				on the water, with celebratory gunfire or other pyrotechnical display, when he returned
				to Westminster from a progress in the North. Anne of Cleves in 1535/40 was met by
				Londoners at Blackheath and then escorted by land to Greenwich, where London put on a
				water show for her. A month later, Londoners escorted her by water from Greenwich to
				Westminster: she made no actual formal entry into the city.so)</p>
					<p>
				Not all major royal entries necessarily followed all aspects of the pattern described above.
				The decoration of the streets with rich hangings, for example, is not always referred to
				though it was almost certainly a standard major–entry feature, and perhaps some coronation
				entries did not have pageants, although we may simply have insufficient information on
				these entries. Chronicles and other non–civic manuscripts are usually our major sources of
				information on entry pageants, and chroniclers followed their own interests in what they
				wrote about, and also their own political agendas, even where royalty was concerned. No
				chronicler, for example, tells us about the Cheapside pageant for Anne of Bohemias 1382
				royal entry: we learn about it only from an early Goldsmiths manuscript.3 Chroniclers also
				can merely generalize, or use ambiguous wording (although the records too can sometimes be
				frustratingly minimal or unclear). Constructed pageants seem to have been regularly provided
				however, from at least 1421, for the coronation entries of queen consorts when crowned
				separately from their husbands: and since Anne of Bohemia in 1382 was welcomed with an
				entry pageant although she was not yet married to Richard II (her marriage and then corona*
				tion came shortly after her entry), it is certainly possible that one or more pageants were alsC
				provided for queen consorts Isabella of France in 1306/7 and ]oan of Navarre in 140273.3
				For ruling monarchs, the picture is less clear than for consorts. Coronation–entry pageants
				were provided possibly for Edward I (1308) and Henry 1v (1300), and definitely for Richard II
				(1377), Henry V (14133 though we know only of singers and one or more giants, at the Bridge),
				and Henry vi (1420), and again in the sixteenth century for Edward vi, Mary, and Elizabeth 1:
				but for Edward IIl (1327), Edward 1v (1460), Richard I (1483), Henry vi1 (1485), and (with
				one possible exception) Henry vii1 (1500), we have no evidence of coronation–entry pageants
				The lack of information for Edward III, Edward Iv, Richard IIl, and Henry vii, and lack of
				clarity for Henry Iv, could be ascribed to factors such as the chroniclers greater interest in–
				or caution because of– the political circumstances of these monarchs accessions: and the
				political circumstances could also explain any actual absence of pageants. Henry VIII, however,
				was a legitimate heir in an orderly succession process. Unless the chronicle references to
				virgins in white at the goldsmiths stalls in Cheapside (at Old Change), at Henry vi11s 1500
				coronation entry from the Tower to Westminster, are to a pageant of some kind, Henry vIIl is
				not recorded as having had coronation–entry pageants. Perhaps a pageant norm had lapsed
				over the preceding eighty years: or perhaps pageants after all were not a coronation–entry
				norm for ruling monarchs until the mid–sixteenth century. 2</p>
					<p>
				Normally, a monarch seems to have been given a pageantic entry only once during his[her
				reign, immediately preceding his/her coronation. In the late fourteenth and early fifteentk
				centuries, however, on three occasions a ruling monarch who had already received a corona
				tion entry with one or more pageants was given an additional pageantic entry because of
				unusual circumstances: Richard II in 1302 (a gift from the city after a major quarrel with
				the king): Henry V in 1415 (a celebration of his military victory at Agincourt): and Henry vi
				in 1432 (a welcoming of him from his coronation in France). Also, although pageants seem
				normally to have been reserved for ruling monarchs (native or foreign) and the consorts of
				English rulers, in 1426, for the entry from France of the duke of Bedford, Lord Protectori
				with his duchess, pageantry was provided on London Bridge. Perhaps only the Bridge provided
				pageantry (including music) on this occasion, or perhaps the city did as well but Bedford&apos;s
				arrival simply did not interest fifteenth–century chroniclers.৳ Either the occasion was unusual
				or there were other such individuals, over the centuries, who were similarly honoured
				but for whose entries the records – along with any mention in chronicle histories– have
				not survived.</p>
					<p>
				Usually the Crown directed the city on the level of entry to be orchestrated for any given
				entrant, and the city made and paid for arrangements accordingly8 For a coronation entry
				or other major display entry, regularly from 1483 (and at least occasionally before then) a
				special financial assessment, or tax, would be approved by the city&apos;s common council to
				cover all or part of the citys costs for gifts, entry preparations, or both. From 1483 this ta৲
				was regularly in the form of one or more fifteenths – a fifteenth being a fixed amount of
				money, little changed since the early fourteenth century, levied on the citys wards rather
				than directly on individuals. This form of tax was used for many funding purposes by the
				city (not only for activities such as major entries), and gave the wards the discretion to spare
				the poor from payment. The companies with halls seem normally to have paid fifteenths
				usually a fixed sum, per fifteenth, for each company, also largely unchanged over the years*
				in the wards where their halls were located. Sometimes this money was called a benevolence:
				that is, supposedly a voluntary contribution. The coronation tax in 1483, 1485, and 1500
				was one fifteenth: for coronations and other major entries in all of 15Ol, 1522, and on to
				1554, it was one–and–a₯half fifteenths: and for the coronation of Elizabeth 1 (1550), the tax
				was two fifteenths. Sometimes the fifteenths were specified to be for more than entry costs
				and gifts: in 1547, for example, for the costs of the funeral of Henry viIl as well as for the
				coronation of Edward vi, and in 1522, for bowmen for the kings service as well as for the
				entry of the emperor Charles v.2s Special collectors would be appointed to receive the tax
				money, and sometimes the citizens reluctance to pay was considerable, as in 1533 for th
				coronation entry of the unpopular Anne Boleyn. Not only London citizens were taxed
				From at least 1522 on, the records show that all residents in London, non–citizens as well as
				citizens, were required to pay৳ and in 1522, 1533, 1553, and 1554, London residents from
				various foreign states, such as Venetians and Florentines, were specifically obliged either to
				contribute to the one–and–a₯half fifteenths or to contribute their own constructed pageants
				to the entries.1</p>
					<p>
				There were important entries into London, other than the major ones already discussed
				which followed a different pattern. Accession entries– being the immediate movement of a
				new monarch to take possession of the Tower upon accession to the throne – also occurred,
				and varied somewhat in the initial route they followed: but at least those in the 155os fell
				into what appears to have been, by then, an expected ceremonial pattern once the monarch
				had entered through one of the city&apos;s gates. The entry point seems in part to have depended,
				as a practical consideration, on where the new monarch was located at the time of acces
				sion. Elizabeth I, for example, was at Hatfield, to the north of London, and when she
				reached London, she first stayed at the Charterhouse (outside the walls to the northwest)
				and so entered from the northwest, through Cripplegate.  Her predecessor Mary had to
				manoeuvre militarily for the throne, outside London, because of the proclamation of the
				Lady [ane Grey as queen upon the death of Edward vi: her headquarters were to the northeast:
				and when an accession entry to the Tower finally became possible for her, Mary entered from
				east of the city, through Aldgate. Both Elizabeth and Mary, however, then made their way
				to Leadenhall and followed the same basic route: from Leadenhall down Gracechurch Street to
				Fenchurch Street, then east along Fenchurch Street and down Mark Lane to the Tower, and fo*
				Mary, this entailed going out of her way, from Aldgate west along Aldgate Street to Leadenhall
				before moving south and then east again to the Tower. The route from Leadenhall to the
				Tower was not only practical (given street widths), but likely also ceremonially customary:
				from the intersection of Gracechurch Street and Fenchurch Street, it was the same route
				followed (as described above, p xxiv) by all of Henry vi, Henry vil, and Henry viII on the
				first day of their two–day coronation entries. In 1547, however, Edward vi, although north
				of the city at his accession, perhaps for security reasons entered through Aldgate and turned
				directly south, along by the city wall and past the Crutched Friars to the Tower.€ Accession
				entries – about which we have very little information before the sixteenth century – appear
				usually to have involved cheering crowds, speeches, and music, but no pageants until 1603
				[when one was prepared, but then not presented after all). Pageants would have been precluded
				by the unpredictability and speed of accessions, and also sometimes by their difficult or
				unusual political circumstances. Where accession entries appear in The Records, Appendix I,
				or both, it is because music is recorded.</p>
				<p>Other kinds of welcoming or escorting occasions in London, below the level of the major
				entries, might involve, on land, one or more of the decoration of the streets, the companie:
				lining the streets, and music. The routes could vary. The king, for example, might require
				only a welcoming escort when he returned to the city from a journey within England or
				abroad: or more elaboration might be required even on a minor occasion, such as a riding
				from Westminster to a palace south of the Thames. Different levels of activity and display
				were also involved in welcomings and escortings by water.</p>
					<p>
				The city could prepare quickly for a non–pageantic entry or other escort requirement,
				needing only to order the companies to provide riders (company members, either on horse–
				back or on barges on the water), in full livery, to meet the entrant, and, if required for a
				land entry, company members to line the streets. Also the occupants of buildings along the
				land–entry route needed little time to hang from their windows any required decorative
				rich cloths and banners: and barges could be quickly decorated for a water escort. Choristers
				and instrumental musicians from city churches could also be called into service rapidly, as
				could the city waits (the city&apos;s own paid musicians) and, at least from e 1500, the members
				of the Minstrels Company.S In 1549, for example, when the city had only some forty–eight
				hours to provide a musical welcome for Edward vi riding through the city from the Bridge
				to Westminster, orders went out for the gravelling of the streets, for citizens to hang out cloths,
				for the companies of Parish Clerks and of Minstrels to provide singers and musicians, and
				for the waits to play. The children of Paul&apos;s (presumably the cathedral choristers) were also
				required to turn out.1/ Pageants, however, took some time to prepare, although once made
				they could be stored between occasions and then mended or otherwise renovated when
				required again.18 One reason for the elaborateness of the pageants prepared for the entry of
				Xatherine of Aragon, arriving in 1501 to marry the heir to England&apos;s throne, Prince Arthur,
				was that some two years had passed between the conclusion of the marriage negotiations and
				katherines arrival in England. The city&apos;s first record of its preparations is dated I) Novembei
				1400: and the entry finally took place on 12 November 1501. When necessary, however,
				pageants could be prepared quickly, as in 1547 when the city had only three weeks from the
				accession of Edward vi to his coronation entry. In 1533 the coronation entry of Anne Boleyn,
				by both water and land, had to be provided in less than two weeks. Elaborate entries, whether
				prepared slowly or speedily, called upon the expertise not only of designers, craftsmen, and
				producers but also of scholars and writers. Names of the latter occurring in the sixteenth–
				century records of royal entries include, for example, those of grammarian William Lily (in
				1522), playwright/printer[producer [ohn Rastell (in 1522), scholars and writers Nicholas Udall
				and [ohn Leland (in 1533), and playwright and court entertainer ]ohn Heywood (in 1553
				and 1554). s.</p>
					<p>
				Street processions in relation to royalty did not always include royalty itself, and could
				sometimes, at least in the late thirteenth and early fourteenth centuries, involve portable
				pageants. In 1208 the Fishmongers paraded to Leadenhall on St Magnus Day, to celebrate
				a military victory by the king against the Scots, with a representation of the saint and with
				gilded sturgeons, silver salmon, and knights made to look like luces, all on horses. Other
				companies may also have had pageants. In 1312713 the Fishmongers rode through the city to
				Westminster with a ship pageant, to escort the queen from Westminster to Eltham after the
				birth of Prince Edward./ The city as a whole might also mark special royal events with street
				celebrations involving music, dance, and often bonfires, normally on the orders of the civic
				government or the Crown.2s In early 1377, when the city sent mummers to entertain Prince
				Richard (shortly to become Richard II), the mummers created a major moving spectacle as they
				rode through the city and across the Bridge on their way to the royal palace at Rennington, in
				a civic processional equivalent to the occasional fourteenth–century pre–tournament processions
				made by the nobility through Cheapside.:</p>
				</div>
				<div>
			<head>Mayoral Oath–Takings and Shrieval Presentations</head>

<p>The annual inaugurations of the mayor and of the sheriffs were, from early times, significant
				occasions of civic processional display. For most of the period between c 1200 and 1558, the
				newly chosen sheriffs swore their oath of office at the Guildhall on 28 September and took
				office immediately: then, usually on 30 September, they processed to Westminster to be
				presented there to the king or to the barons of the Exchequer as his representatives. In the
				early fourteenth century the city successfully argued that no shrieval oath to the Crown was
				necessary until the sheriffs submitted their accounts at the conclusion of their terms: this
				collection therefore refers throughout to the sheriffs presentation at Westminster, rather than
				to their oath–taking, even though they normally took an oath in any case. This terminology
				also provides a useful differentiation between the shrieval occasion and the oath–taking of the
				mayor. The newly chosen mayor swore an oath of office at the Guildhall on 28 October, but
				did not fully become mayor until processing to Westminster, usually on 2 October, to take
				his oath to the monarch or to the Exchequer barons. The processional route, by the early
				fifteenth century at least, was from the Guildhall along Cheapside, through Newgate, and
				along Fleet Street to Westminster. Occasionally, when neither the monarch nor the barons
				were available at Westminster, the inauguration procession was instead to the Tower of
				London, for the sheriffs presentation or the mayor&apos;s oath–taking there, before the Constable
				of the Tower as the monarchs representative. Tower–oath years for both the mayor and the
				sheriffs, 1208–1558, are listed in Appendix 8.57</p>
					<p>
				Although musicians – above all trumpeters– were probably part of both the shrieva
				and the mayoral processions from very early times, we have no records of processional music
				until, in the fourteenth century, some of the companies surviving accounts and court minutes
				begin, since the companies provided much of the ceremonial for mayoral and shrieval inaugura
				tions. The first company record of oath–taking music for the mayor is in 1360, and the first
				record of such music for a sheriff is in 1383. Both records are from the Goldsmiths early
				combined accounts and minutes (which also record mayoral–procession music in 1377
				and in 1388). The Grocers also record minstrels for a sheriff in 1386: and by the 1300s
				the records of the Grocers, Mercers, and Merchant Taylors all show one or more payments
				to minstrels on the mayor&apos;s riding to Westminster, the Mercers also recording minstrels
				three times with the sheriffs.2 In the fifteenth century, the records become more extensive
				Early on, the processions could be by land, on foot or on horseback, or by water: but by the
				late fourteenth century, processions by land, on horseback, appear to have become the norm
				Then, in 1389, it was determined that, as a cost–cutting measure, the sheriffs should hencefortk
				no longer ride each year to their Westminster presentations but should go either by water or
				by foot on land –a decision that does not appear to have taken consistent effect until 1435. 5
				In 1453, after an initial unsuccessful attempt in 1447, the decision was made that the mayor
				would regularly go to his Westminster oath–taking by water Prior to this, in the late fourteenth
				and early fifteenth centuries, the mayor is definitely recorded as going by water only in 1422:
				an unusual oath–taking year, because the mayoral inauguration was closely followed by the
				funeral in early November of Henry V. At first, from 1453, the mayor and his entourage went
				on foot to the Thames to take barges up the river: but in 1501, mayor [ohn Shaa began the
				practice of riding on horseback to the river.€ Either by land or by water, the procession (even
				when by water, still often called a riding) involved the city&apos;s governors – aldermen, other city
				officers, senior members of companies– in their formal liveries, in set processional order, with
				banners and with minstrels. 63</p>
					<p>
				By at least the late fifteenth century, some kinds of special displays were in use in the
				procession on land from the Guildhall to the Thames, and on land again when the mayoi
				returned from Westminster, as in 148I the city prohibited any disguising or pageant, at the
				mayor&apos;s oath–taking, either from the mayor&apos;s house to the water or from the water to the
				mayor&apos;s house. : We cannot be sure of just what these pageants were, given the common use
				at this time of the word pageant to mean simply an elaborate display (including elaborate
				banners, wall hangings, embroidered cushions, and the like, as well as images or wood–and
				canvas constructions): but it is difficult to see why something as usual as banners would
				have been prohibited. The term disguising also can be variously interpreted, but suggests
				costuming or masking at the least. It is unclear how long the 148I prohibition held: but the
				traditional belief that portable constructed pageants began to be carried (again€) in mayoral
				processions generally, in 1535 and in 1540, is not necessarily correct. This belief has been
				based on a Drapers record in 1540 which cites, as a precedent for a pageant in the 1540
				draper mayor&apos;s oath–taking procession, the carrying of a pageant in 1535 at the inauguration
				of a mercer mayor. Both 1535 and 1540, however, were unusual years in which the mayor
				swore his oath not at Westminster but at the Tower of London: and the Drapers in 1540
				cite the 1535 precedent as specifically involving a Tower oath (when the oath–taking procession,
				from the Guildhall to the Tower and back, was for a shorter distance than to Westminster
				and back, and without a water component). The 1540 record (actually two records) thus
				tells us nothing about the usual situation, before or after 1535, in Westminster oath–taking
				years. Also, given the elasticity of the use of the term pageant, just what the Drapers 1540
				pageant was, besides being a portable representation of the Assumption, is unclear, although
				presumably it – and the Mercers 1535 pageant– was something more substantial than a
				banner or in 1540 no precedent would have been thought necessary. The Drapers sixteenth
				century Midsummer Watch records provide examples of pageant variety, with representations
				of the Assumption ranging from elaborate banners to a wood–and–canvas construction in
				1536 carried by thirteen porters. Possibly a Drapers Assumption, carried in the mayoral
				inauguration procession from the water to the Guildhall in 1528, and again in 1533, was
				a constructed pageant. This pageant is associated in the records with agreement not to
				have a bachelors barge (a part of the mayoral ceremonial on the water): and the companys
				bachelors – responsible for much of the company&apos;s mayoral inauguration ceremonial– had
				a constructed Assumption pageant which they used in the 1520s in the Midsummer Watch.
				This bachelors Assumption pageant could possibly have been a substitute for the barge. s&amp;
				There is, however, no firm evidence.5 In 1543 the Drapers again provided a pageant for
				their mayor in a Tower–oath year, and in 1551, at the Westminster installation of a mayor
				from the Skinners Company, the records include a payment to a painter to make and
				throwlow to garnyshe a representation of a lynx (from the companys coat of arms) for the
				land procession, seemingly to be carried by two bearers. Also included in the procession
				and in the payment– were two wild men and a moor./ Finally, in 1553, merchant taylori
				Henry Machyn refers in his diary to a Merchant Taylors mayoral oath–taking pageant, with
				speeches, of St ]ohn the Baptist, along with woodmen with clubs and squibs, and a devil:
				and it is from this year that theatre historians have traditionally referred to London&apos;s annua
				mayoral inauguration procession as the Lord Mayor&apos;s Show./ Machyn continues to refer to
				pageants, in 1555 through 1558 (in 1558 the pageant clearly is moving with the procession):
				and our only surviving pageant manuscript with pre–Elizabethan material, a rough Merchant
				Taylors manuscript for the mayoral inaugurations of 1556, 1561, and 1568 (all involving
				merchant taylor mayors), contains records of extensive display in 1556, including a constructed
				portable pageant holding four child performers, along with wild men, squibs, and a hired
				(real or constructed) camel, derived (like the Skinners lynx) from the company&apos;s coat of
				arms.2 The mayoral show norm at this time appears to have been the display of only one
				large constructed pageant, although with other performance elements as well, such as wild
				men and devils.73</p>
				<p>Typically the first day of mayoral inauguration ceremonies consisted mainly of the incoming
				mayor&apos;s swearing of the oath of office at the Guildhall./ On the second day, the incoming
				mayor processed from his house to the Guildhall, and then (with the outgoing mayor) to
				Westminster by land or (from 1453) by water, escorted by the aldermen, other city officers,
				and company members in full livery dress. Embarkation seems normally to have been at
				a wharf at the Crane (later Three Cranes) in the Vintry, for the water procession up the
				river to the Exchequer: on the return trip the mayor landed at a wharf below St Paul&apos;s
				Cathedral.s The procession then proceeded by land up the hill, through Paul&apos;s Chain, into
				Paul&apos;s churchyard and through it to Cheapside, and to the mayor&apos;s feast: an inauguration
				banquet paid for by the new mayor. 8 Before 1501–2, when kitchens began to be installec
				at the Guildhall at the initiative of mayor ]ohn Shaa, the feast would be at either the mayor&apos;s
				house (many early London mayors had mansions suitable for this kind of occasion) or a
				company hall.7/ After dinner the procession returned to St Paul&apos;s, for prayers, then to
				Cheapside again, and finally back to the mayor&apos;s house.8 Because no early chamberlains
				accounts have survived, and because all or most of the dinner was at the expense of the
				incoming mayor, no city accountings for it–which might have given us details on matters
				such as music or entertainment – exist, although the records of the various mayors com–
				panies sometimes provide information on preparing the Guildhall with decorations, hire
				of plates, and the like. Ceremonial arrangements for the mayor&apos;s year in office, including
				for the oath–taking dinner, were largely the responsibility of the bachelors/yeomanry of
				the mayor&apos;s company, and, to 1558, no Great Company bachelor or yeomanry accounts
				or minutes have survived. Trumpeters at the feast appear, however, in company records
				for 1482 (the Goldsmiths) and in some other years.18 By at least the sixteenth century
				there was certainly entertainment in some years, for in 1526 we find the city providing
				court entertainer Thomas Brandon with the city&apos;s freedom, at no charge, in return for
				his provision of annual entertainment for the mayor&apos;s inauguration feast, as well as for
				another mayoral banquet on the Monday after Epiphany. How widespread such arrange–
				ments may have been, we do not know: the Brandon record exists only because the city
				at first required Brandon to pay a fee for his freedom but then refunded it.8 Guests at
				the feast would include privy councillors, members of the nobility, customs officials, and
				royal bureaucrats:৳ a guest list and seating plan for one table is extant for 1520, in Letter
				Book O.s2 Because the mayor was a member of one of the Great Twelve companies (always
				from 1435, and usually from before then as well) the most informative records of mayoral
				inauguration ceremonials come from those companies manuscripts: but some of the extant
				manuscripts of other companies also record payments for riders, barges, and minstrels, as
				their contributions to the occasion.</p>
					<p>
				From 1453, when the procession to Westminster was regularly by water on barges, a
				bachelors barge was usually part of the annual proceedings.s5 (A ceremonial barge at this
				time was a large vessel propelled by oars and usually highly decorated.) Arranged for by
				the bachelors of the incoming mayor&apos;s company, the bachelors barge is normally assumed
				to have carried the bachelors themselves, and some extant records do indicate this.5/ It
				served, however, during the mayoral year, in other civic water processions as well, and in
				the 1487 coronation water entry of Elizabeth of Tork it carried a great red dragon spouting
				flames of fire into the Thames. In the 1533 coronation water entry of Anne Boleyn, which
				involved another fire–breathing dragon and (as in 1487) various constructed pageants as
				well, carried on barges or boats, it was highly decorated with cloth of gold, silk, banners,
				flags, and small bells, and carried musicians (and perhaps also the bachelors). 85 Possibly
				therefore, at least sometimes, it carried pyrotechnical or other elaborate visual displays in
				the mayoral inauguration procession to and[or from Westminster. The Drapers bachelors
				in the 1520s had several pages of instructions (which unfortunately have not survived)
				concerning the bachelors barge. A Goldsmiths record for the mayor&apos;s Westminster oath*
				taking in 1545 refers to the masters (leaders) of the bachelors as overseeing payment of
				all the charges of the pageants for the barge: these pageants could have been decorations
				only, or actual constructions or other such devices. In the 1540s and 1550s, the Mercers
				records show that a foist – a vessel usually, in the mayoral procession, carrying fireworks
				or guns (the latter for celebratory shots) – might accompany the bachelors barge or might
				serve as a replacement for it. As early as the 1450s, the Grocers had a gret grefon for
				their bachelors barge (two griffins are featured in the Grocers coat of arms): processional
				barges in general may have identified themselves by large banners, or constructed figures, of
				company emblems. In 1540 the Armourers carried some sort of representation of St George
				(the company&apos;s patron saint) on their company&apos;s barge at the royal entry of Anne of Cleves
				by water from Greenwich to Westminster./ By the late sixteenth century and on into the
				seventeenth, constructed and performed pageants on the water were a normal part of the
				mayoral oath–taking procession.88</p>
					<p>
				The display involved in the presentation of the sheriffs annually at Westminster was
				considerably less than that for the mayor&apos;s oath–taking, although music was a usual feature
				These presentations do not seem ever to have included constructed pageants or other such
				festive forms of display. Cirty regulations were also made from time to time to cut back on
				various kinds of shrieval display in general, in order to privilege mayoral display or to
				reduce costs. The sheriffs in 1388, for example, as previously noted, were instructed to go
				to Westminster by water or on foot by land, while the mayor still had a land procession on
				horseback (apparently considered to be more impressive and expensive than a water proces.
				sion): and in August 1521 common council agreed that only the companies of the incoming
				sheriffs would accompany those sheriffs on the water to Westminster. Also the mayor and
				the sheriffs originally both gave a dinner, at their own expense, on the days of their respec
				tive Westminster inauguration processions: trumpeters were involved at least from the late
				fifteenth century: but to reduce costs also (and to save foodstuffs), from 1521 the mayoral
				and shrieval dinners were combined, to take place as one dinner, paid for by both the mayori
				and the sheriffs, on the mayor&apos;s oath–taking day. The costs of both the mayoralty and the
				shrievalty had always been high, requiring–especially from the mayor – large expenditures of
				personal funds: and at times the known financial burdens of office caused men to manoeuvre
				extensively to avoid election.)</p>
					<p>
				Occasionally a mayor or sheriff would die in office, and the replacement mayor or sheriff
				would therefore process to Westminster (or the Tower) at a time other than the usual
				25 October or 30 September. A record of the procession to Westminster in April 1544
				of replacement mayor Ralph Warren (mercer) shows that minor differences from the norms
				of the mayoral oath–taking could occur under such circumstances.
			</p>
				</div>
				<div>
			<head>	Midsummer Watch</head>
				<p>By the early sixteenth century the two–night London Midsummer Watch –on the eves to early
				mornings of the feasts of St [ohn the Baptist and of Sts Peter and Paul (24 and 20 ]une)
				had become the city&apos;s largest, most spectacular annual occasion for processional display, far
				surpassing the oath–taking ceremony of each year&apos;s incoming new mayori The Watch hac
				probably originated as in part a security measure and in part a military requirement: in 1181
				the Assize of Arms had required free men to own arms for use, if necessary, in national
				defence, and in 1252 and 1253 Henry IIl had ordered summer–season watches to be kept in
				cities, to preserve the peace, and had linked them with the Assize of Arms.8 Ordinary security
				watches in London probably much predated this order in any case, and midsummer, with
				its traditions of unruly folk celebrations, was a natural time for special armed watches.
				Then in 1285 the Statute of Winchester (regularly reconfirmed up to its repeal in 1558)
				confirmed watch provisions and also required every city and town in England twice a year
				to view its citizens arms, to ensure ongoing ability to provide soldiers in time of war.৳5 At
				some point the requirements for special watches and for a twice–yearly viewing of citizens
				arms seem to have become combined with one another, along with midsummer celebra
				tions, for in the 1540s London could not cancel the Midsummer Watch without the permis–
				sion of the Crown.8 By this time the city&apos;s Midsummer Watch was at its peak of military
				and theatrical spectacle, with large numbers of armed men, provided in part by the com–
				panies, marching through the city, and also– provided by the companies with a mayor or
				sheriff currently in office– musicians, giants, sword players, morris dancers, devils with
				squibs, other costumed performers, and constructed wood–and–canvas pageants (carried
				by porters) depicting subjects largely from the bible and saints lives but also from classical
				mythology, allegory, and (although rarely) history. Pageants would sometimes play on the
				names of the mayors and sheriffs: William the Conqueror, for example, for ironmonger
				sheriff William Denham in 1535. The mayor and the sheriffs each had their own desig
				nated parts of the parade: the mayor&apos;s watch and the sheriffs watch, presenting their
				companies pageants, morris dancers, and the like. All of this Watch display moved through
				the night streets of London along a fixed route, going (at least as of 1541) eastward along
				Cheapside and Cornhill to Aldgate, then looping around to the west via Fenchurch Street
				to Gracechurch Street and its conduit, north on Gracechurch Street back to Cornhill, and
				returning westward through Cheapside to St. Pauls.2 In some years, at least, there were
				also one or more stationary pageants on the processional route. Torches and cresset lights
				(flax burning in shallow basins on top of poles) were carried in the procession. The cresset
				men were accompanied by bagbearers to renew the flax when necessary. At least by 154C
				cresset lights were also specially positioned along the Watchs route, when the overall lighting
				for the Watch was deemed by the city to be otherwise insufficient and a number of the
				companies were ordered by common council to provide standing cressets, on an ongoing
				basis, all along the streets through which the Watch marched.10/ A famous, nostalgic de–
				scription of this marching watch, written by [ohn Stow in his 1508 S¥৲v£y of L¢₭₨¢₭.
				provides numbers on the size of the Watch in the early 1540s: 2, O00 armed men, over 240
				constables (120 on each night of the Watch), almost 2, O00 men carrying and tending to
				the cresset lights, and several pageants (plus additional armed men) for the mayor and for
				each sheriff, along with giants, musicians, morris dancers, sword players torch bearers, and
				700 standing cressets. 101</p>
				<p>The earliest record we have of a decorative rather than purely functional Watch at mid*
				summer, moving through the city, is from 1378. The armed men, from the various wards,
				were dressed in red and white, with cresset lights and with lances decorated in white, black,
				or red, with stars or wreaths.: They, with their aldermen, met in Smithfield: the actual
				Watch route they then took is not specified. The armed men in 1370 were also in red and
				white, and met in Smithfield: in 1384–6 they gathered in St Paul&apos;s cemetery.0s In 1406, in
				Letter Book I, we find a list of wards providing a total of over three hundred men to go
				with the mayor in the Watch on St Peter&apos;s Eve. (Normally some watchmen remained within
				their wards, and other men accompanied the mayor and other officers through the city.
				Subsequently, city records of the Watch up to the 1460s are minimal and largely formulaic
				(the aldermen are to provide watchmen in their wards), containing no information on watch
				elaboration: but that a good deal may lie behind the uninformative records is indicated when
				Bale&apos;s Ch৲¢₭€₯₮£ tells us that in 1445 the Watch was attended by royalty and was especially
				grand. lo৳ Perhaps it was augmented as part of the celebrations of the 30 May coronation of
				Margaret of Anjou, to which Bale implicitly connects it. Bales account does not sound,
				however, as though under normal circumstances the Watch was insignificant. 105</p>
				<p>In 1448 a [ournal record refers to men at arms, both of the aldermen (that is, within the
				wards€) and of the mayor and sheriffs.10s In 1454 each alderman was to send two men o
				more to go with the mayor.10/ By the 1460s or early 1470s, at least occasionally one or
				more companies may have been contributing men to the mayor&apos;s and sheriffs (marching.
				Watch: previously the system of providing watchmen seems to have been entirely ward.
				based (though of course the lack of records may not reflect a lack of company activity). ios
				By at least 1477 the companies were major contributors to the Watch on special occasions
				for in that year– the first year also of a record of a constructed pageant being carried in the
				Watch– twenty–six of the more substantial companies provided a total of S10 armed men
				because the city had been ordered by the Crown to put on an especially large or elaborate
				Watch (a greater Watch) on 28–0 ]une, to impress ambassadors from France and from
				Scotland.10৳ The pageant, which required fourteen men to carry it, may have been unusual
				or common but reported only in this unusual year: it was provided, along with a morris
				dance, by the Drapers, who had a mayor in office.1 From 1477 to 1503 come several more
				records of company involvement in the Watch:1 and in 1504 we find another list of companie
				(this time thirty–four) required to provide armed men for the Watch, to go with the mayor:
				also the Drapers, with a mayor in office, supplied thirteen Watch pageants. These were
				doubtless various kinds of displays (including elaborate banners), certainly not all wood–
				and–canvas constructions, but the total cost was an impressive 638 13s Io₽d.1€ Pageants
				in the marching Watch apparently had become a useful outlet for company display. The
				pageantry may have developed gradually: its development may have been accelerated by the
				148I prohibition (previously noted) of mayoral inauguration pageants and disguisings: or
				the 1501 spectacle of the royal entry of katherine of Aragon may have prompted an upswing
				in regular civic display activities, especially with the pageant stuff being sold off by the city
				to interested buyers in 1502.11 Given the vagaries of company accounting practices and of
				manuscript survival, however, there may have been considerable fifteenth–century Watch
				display, especially after 1477, about which we know nothing. In 1510 and 151I the companies
				were again required to provide armed men to accompany the mayor in the Watch, and in
				1518 a list was issued of the numbers of men they were required to provide on an ongoing
				basis.1/ A revised list was issued in 1525, and another in 1532.11 During the early sixteenth
				century, Watch display seems to have increased to the point at which eventually some
				boundaries had to be set: and in 1537 the court of aldermen limited the sheriffs (temporarily)
				to, among other items (such as no giants), no more than three Watch pageants each. lis
				In 1541 the Drapers complained among themselves about Watch costs having been driven
				up by lavish spending by the Mercers, but what remedy but go through wyth all. 1 In some
				years, however, there were no pageants: for example, in 1522, when a costly royal entry had
				just taken place, on 6 ]une, for the emperor Charles V, and in 1528, a plague year.118</p>
				<p>Because of the extensive involvement of the companies in the sixteenth–century Midsummer
				Watch, we know a good deal about the Watch during its apparent peak of theatrical and
				musical activity in the 1520s to early 1540s. We have extensive surviving payment records
				for the Watch, for about half of the years from 1519 to 1541, from the manuscripts of the
				Ironmongers, Skinners, and especially Drapers. Some pageant and other information is also
				to be found in the manuscripts of the Clothworkers, Goldsmiths, Grocers, and Vintners, and
				more routine information in those of a number of other companies as well. Unfortunately
				the Mercers Company, which had numerous mayors and sheriffs in office in the first half
				of the sixteenth century, did not include much in the way of Watch information in its
				court minutes, and its main accounts between 1464 and 1558 have not survived. Possibly
				also the Mercers, like the Drapers for the Watch at the start of the sixteenth century, kept
				Watch payment details in one or more separate bills or other manuscripts which were
				eventually discarded or lost. 11/ We do know that the Mercers spent lavishly on the Watch,
				as in 1541 (as noted above) the Drapers complained that the Mercers expenditures were
				driving up Watch costs. Watch information from the extant court minutes of the Mercers.
				however, though limited, is sometimes very useful: as in a 1537 reference, for example,
				to a presumably stationary (otherwise unspecified) pageant to be set up, as in 1536, at the
				Great Conduit in Cheapside, which was just outside the companys hall, on the route of
				the Watch marchers.120</p>
					<p>
				Both children and adults were costumed performers in the Watch, the former for reasons
				both of weight (since the pageants were carried by porters) and– if school/choir boys– of
				rhetorical and[or musical training. Both professional and amateur adult actors also participated,
				together with many musicians playing a variety of portable instruments. The names of
				specific musicians and of other kinds of entertainers, and of providers of armour, weaponry,
				and other essentials, recur in the records, including those of well–known actors Robert
				Hinstock and ]ohn English, both members of the king&apos;s players. The names of various
				painters, carpenters, and the like, responsible for the design and building of pageant elements
				also recur. All of these records require considerably more study, for the piecing together of
				the basic details of what appears to have been a thriving theatrical production industry in
				early–sixteenth–century London.1 Certainly the companies were home to many skilled
				individuals who could be employed regularly on the Watch and who would also be part
				of an ongoing experienced group to provide the displays (by at least mid–century) for
				the annual Lord Mayor&apos;s Show, as well as for the usually much–less–frequent major royal
				entries (although four of these elaborate entries did occur within thirteen years in the mid.
				sixteenth century, between February 154677 and [anuary 1558/9). The court also probably
				made use of many of the same personnel for its own elaborate shows, both at Westminster
				and at other royal palaces in the London area. The Watch was costly: but in February
				153475, when a group of citizens complained to the city government about the costs of
				the shrievalty, they specifically exempted the Midsummer Watch from the argument for
				expense reductions. 125 Company pageants might be worked on at Leadenhall, at company halls,
				or elsewhere.2/ Companies stored their pageants, between Midsummer Watches, sometimes
				in locations such as the Princes Wardrobe, or their own storehouses, and sometimes in their
				halls, where the pageants might be set up for display or hung from above. We find occasional
				company records of these pageants being moved when hall repairs are taking place. In a number
				of sixteenth–century years there are records of Henry vil either attending the Watch or being
				expected to do so.</p>
				<p>In 1530, however, despite the popularity, utility, and public–relations aspects of the
				Watch, the city came under pressure from Henry vili, increasingly involved in wars abroad,
				to substitute for the Midsummer Watch an annual muster. The city resisted, although
				obliged in 1530 to hold a muster in May, after which the king belatedly cancelled the Watch
				for that year, to the displeasure of those who had already made preparations for it૱1€৳ but
				after an elaborate Watch again in 1541 (and probably also in 1540, 1542, and 1543, for
				which we have very limited Great Company records extant€€s), the financial demands of
				the Crown in relation to the wars in France caused the cancellation of the Watch again,
				for three consecutive years, 1544 through 1546. After this three–year break, the Watch was
				revived in its full pageantic form in only one year, 1548, at the command of the council
				of the young Edward V1.12/ A low–key form of Midsummer Watch, fulfilling security and
				military requirements, and once again ward–based, continued for a number of subsequent
				years, involving the mayor and other civic officials riding through the wards, where standing
				watches were located৳৳ but the full Midsummer Watch never returned, despite an elabor*
				ate proposal in 1585 for its revival. 12/ The [ournals (with Letter Book copies) contain orders
				for minimal Midsummer Watches within the wards, several times specified as to be without
				lights or music, in about half of the years from 1540 to 1558. In 1557–8 the Armourers
				Company complained about the economic harm that the loss of the Watch had caused to
				its members.130</p>
				<p>Why was the full Midsummer Watch – apparently a flourishing spectacle up to the
				early 1540s– revived only once, in 1548, after the three cancellations in 1544 through
				1546: Various suggestions have been made, some of them relying on earlier assumptions
				that the last regular Midsummer Watch was in 1538 (as Stow&apos;s S¥৲v£y wrongly indicated)
				and that Watch–type pageants first began to be used in the mayoral oath–taking proces–
				sion in 1535 and 1540. It has been suggested that the decline was natural (an older theory), 1s₮
				or that the Crown or city suppressed the Watch because of its associations (pageant subject
				matter and performance dates) with Roman Catholicism, or that the oligarchic city
				government wanted to downgrade the Watch as an annual spectacle in order to promote
				such spectacle instead at the annual inauguration of the mayor. But, first, the Watch
				was still flourishing in 1541 (for which we have above all the Drapers records) and probably
				also in 1540, 1542, and 1543: and in 1537 the city was having to restrain the companies
				from providing more than three pageants each for the sheriffs, and in the late 1530s and
				early 1540s it was working to improve Watch lighting. Second, Henry vill was more anti
				Roman Catholic in the 1530s (when he enjoyed viewing the Watch) than in the 1540s:
				and in any case pageant content– the one visibly Roman aspect of the Watch, in that a
				good number of the pageants focused on saints– could easily have been changed if such
				content had been a problem.3/ Midsummer itself was as much a secular as a religious time
				of the year, and the revival of the full Watch in 1548 was at the direction of the Protestant
				council of Edward v1. Finally, when the king in 1530 – eager for a large military muster
				to impress foreign powers– had given the city authorities the opportunity to replace the
				Watch with an annual muster, and so to transfer pageants, giants, and the like to the mayoral
				oath–taking if they had so desired, a city committee had produced in response a list of
				cogent reasons for maintaining the Watch. 135</p>
				<p>In fact, the demise of the pageantic Midsummer Watch seems to have been essentially
				for financial reasons: the financial picture as of 1530 having changed by the mid–1540s.
				The citys Watch, as a major spectacle at least from the 1470s, had become elaborate above
				all through the support of the companies: costs were increasing: s and in the 1540s and
				1550s both the city itself and the companies were being hard pressed financially from all
				sides. In the 1540s the king required men and money for his wars: and in 1550 (and for
				several years thereafter) the companies found themselves having to purchase back their
				chantry lands which had been seized by the Crown, while the city also purchased from
				the king the liberties of Southwark. Between 1547 and 1554 the city and the companies
				also had to pay for three major royal entries. 1/ Some individuals of course might have
				wanted to eliminate the full Watch for reasons having to do with religion or politics: but
				it seems unlikely – especially after the 1530 city response to Henry viIl, arguing for the
				continuation of the Watch– that most aldermen and common council members would
				have favoured the elimination of the pageantic Watch had it not been for the extreme
				financial demands being made on the city and the companies in the 1540s and 1550s
				Then, with the elimination of the pageantic Watch, the Lord Mayor&apos;s Show became the
				only remaining city venue – and musical and theatrical employment opportunity– for an
				annual public display of pageants, devils, and the like, although it seems to have taken many
				years before, in the seventeenth century, the mayoral show reached the level of spectacle
				of the earlier Midsummer Watch.</p>
				<p>The Watch has not been much studied yet by historians for potential specific political
				allusions or themes. Its display has been largely regarded as traditional, perhaps politically
				controversial only in that some of its pageants used religious images, such as of saints, associated
				with Roman Catholicism. At least some of the pageants, however, were probably more than
				innocuous display, at least in times of political controversy. In 1534, for example, a Watch
				pageant of the Lady M (a lady carrying a gilt Romayn. M., or wearing a square diadem
				with an M at every corner, or aft£৲ onye other devyse as shall be Devysed bye M$৳t£৲ wardens)
				was likely an indirect show of support for the Lady (formerly Princess) Mary, now that
				Anne Boleyn had become queen and the Succession Act of March 1534 had made Mary
				illegitimate. 15/ In 1535, although the extant civic records themselves do not show this,
				the Watch included, to the delight of Henry viIl, a display of the beheading of Catholic
				ecclesiastics.140 The pageants in the Watch may have been largely traditional in their overt
				subject matter (castles, saints, the nine worthies, and the like): but as Richard Osberg has
				pointed out, recurring images in processions acquired particular meaning, at any given				time of display, through the realities of the moment.4 It has been suggested, for example,
				that the castle pageant in the 1521 Watch, with a Turkish horseman in pursuit, referred to
				the siege, then taking place, of Belgrade by the Turkish sultan Suleiman I. (Belgrade fell to
				Suleiman only a few weeks later.)143</p>
				<p>The Midsummer Watch did not exist in a vacuum in London, in relation to giants,
				morris dancers, swordsmen, fireworks, pageants, and the like. There was clearly inter*
				change between the spring celebrations of London&apos;s parishes, in May to ]une, and the
				Midsummer Watch. Company wardens on occasion rented giants and pageants from the
				parishes:  and children from parish choirs also participated in the Watch.1 Indeed, afte
				the mid–century demise of the traditional Midsummer Watch, the parishes may have
				taken up part of the slack (though we may simply lack earlier relevant records). In 1567
				for example, the mayor&apos;s riding in the Watch was augmented with diuer&apos;s prety showes
				done at the charges of yongemen in certayne Parishes. At midsummer 1571, St Giles
				Cripplegate provided a giant, morris dancers, and the like, to go in the Watch with the
				mayor. 145 Also, of course, company members were residents of the parishes, both in their
				homes and in their company halls: connections between parish activities and company
				Watch provisions would have been natural.146</p>
				<p>Companies might also provide membership to musicians and to others with the necessary
				skills in performance spectacle, in return for their expertise provided on occasions such as the
				Watch and, by at least the 1550s, the Lord Mayor&apos;s Show৳ and the city might waive its citizen:
				ship fees. In 1530, for example, Robert Wayt, dromslade (that is, drum player) was made
				free of the Painters Company, frely, the condition being that he provide his services without
				charge annually for the Midsummer Watch. 147
			</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Other Seasonal Festivities</head>				
				<p>The coming of spring was celebrated in London&apos;s wards, especially before and after the reigr
				of Mary (who prohibited May games in spring 1554), with maying festivities such as the
				erection of maypoles, morris dancing, and bonfires, at various times in the months of May
				and early ]une. [ohn Stow in his S¥৲v£y describes this, seemingly for the early sixteenth
				century (although with one specific reference to a mumming in the early fifteenth century),
				referring also to archers and to stage plays.148 The civic records also mention stage plays, in
				a 1554 prohibition of various maying activities, but otherwise tell us nothing about them,
				unless they were related to a parish play–performance tradition seen in the civic licences
				given in the 1520s to three different London churches for the exclusive right to perform a
				play in two cases from April to the end of September.1 Henry Machyn&apos;s diary also mentions
				a stage play at the Greyfriars, beginning in ]une 1557, on the Passion of Christ: by this date
				the monastery of the Grey Friars had been dissolved, and the monastic buildings bought
				by the city in the late 1540s for what had become by 1553 Christ&apos;s Hospital. Perhaps a
				non–church performance was involved, or perhaps Machyn meant his reference to be to the
				former church of the monastery, the chancel of which in 1547 had been renamed Christ
				Church and given a parish.150</p>

				<p>The city government itself, and the companies, seem to have had little to do with public
				May celebrations, since the civic records consist largely of prohibitions at times of unrest or
				of religious controversy in relation to such festivities:/ but company records of the hiring of
				giants and pageants from London parishes, for the Midsummer Watch, indirectly show us
				something about the city&apos;s apparently parish–focused mayings and other festive activities. 1s2
				In the 1550s, after the demise of the pageantic Watch, we find several references in Henry
				Machyn&apos;s diary to elaborate May games in London, most with guns, drums, and morris
				dances, and other features, in various years, such as a castle, giants, hobbyhorses, the nine
				worthies, a sultan, an elephant and castle, moors, and a lord and lady of the May. In 1550
				on 24 ]une– Machyn notes specifically the nine worthies (again), a giant, St George and the
				dragon, a pageant with a queen, and Robin Hood with Little [ohn, Maid Marian, and Friar
				Iuck, with speeches rond a–bowt London. 1133 Possibly London&apos;s mayings had always been
				welledeveloped, but without a Machyn to describe them, or possibly they became more elabor
				ate after the last pageantic Watch in 1548. 15/ They may also have had some civic–government
				involvement after all, for in 1553 Machyn records the participation of sheriff [ohn Maynard
				(a mercer) in a bringing in of the withe: a custom involving a bough, wand, or twist of
				branches being brought ceremonially into great houses at Easter time, here in 1553 with
				giants, hobbyhorses, a morris dance, a lord of misrule, a devil, a sultan, ]ake–of–Lent, and
				music.15s In 1555 the custom was forbidden, for the mayors and sheriffs, by common council
				as a cost–cutting measure.16 That the city&apos;s rulers traditionally celebrated May in their own
				or others halls, however, is indicated not only by the 1553 wythe record and the 1555
				prohibition but also, over a hundred years earlier, by the extant text of a mumming, by [ohn
				Lydgate, commissioned to be performed before the sheriffs and others on May Day, probably
				in 1430. 15/ It is unlikely that such entertainments were as limited as the surviving records
				are:1s perhaps they were included in the personal household costs of city and company officers
				or were funded by unrecorded collections from those commissioning or attending to them
				Despite the survival, for example, of Goldsmiths Company and Mercers Company accounts
				(and Goldsmiths minutes) for the early fifteenth century, no reference is made in them to
				the Lydgate mummings those companies commissioned for performance before the mayor
				on 12 [anuary and 2 February 1420730 (see below, p xliii): and we know about the 1553
				bringing in of the withe only from Machyn&apos;s diary.</p>
				<p>Hocking – a traditional annual activity on the second Monday and Tuesday after Easter*
				is found, in prohibitions, in the civic records of the first half of the fifteenth century. This
				activity involved men on the one day using ropes to stop and bind women in the streets,
				and women on the other day doing the same to men. The captured individuals would pay a
				fine to be freed, and the funds so collected were put to religious uses. 1 Customary popular
				activities at midsummer, other than the Watch, are also found in records of celebrations
				occasionally ordered by the civic government or the Crown, at other times of the year, to be
				as at midsummer: for example, bonfires and armed men ordered in ]uly 1510 at the coming
				of ambassadors from the emperor, and bonfires, children, music, and cresset lights ordered
				in March 1525 to celebrate a military victory abroad.160</p>
				<p>The civic Christmas season, which in London stretched from 3I October to 2 February
				(at least in the sixteenth century), included the feast of St Nicholas (6 December), when
				groups of boy bishops and clerks went mumming from door to door on the Eve or on
				the Day.11 In this traditional role–inversion activity, which had both carnivalesque and
				serious aspects, a boy chorister who was appointed in his parish a bishop for the celebra*
				tion of St Nicholas Eve/Day andor Holy Innocents Day (28 December) would go about
				the streets with his fellow choristers (as clerks), visiting houses and collecting money. The
				boy bishop might also preach a sermon and participate in mass on Holy Innocents Day. is:
				The appointing of boy bishops was apparently widespread in London: Erler, Eccl£৳€$৳૱€₯$₮
				L¢₭₨¢₭, p xxv, refers to perhaps two–thirds of London&apos;s parishes as having followed boy
				bishop observances. In the civic records, however, boy bishops and/or their clerks appear
				only in the early fifteenth–century Bridge House accounts and in the early sixteenth–century
				Brewers Company accounts, in the form of small payments to them on St Nicholas Eve
				or Day, and in the 1518 statutes of St Paul&apos;s grammar school in relation to a sermon and
				mass by the boy bishop on Holy Innocents Day.lss The boy–bishop custom was prohibited
				by the mayor in November 1538 as a vain and superstitious ceremony causing disquiet
				and financial hardship to parishioners, and was suppressed by royal command in 1541 as
				superstitious and childish, although briefly revived under Mary.: The citys concern in
				1538 may have been with religious practices, or with the potential for crime under the cover
				of festive activity, or both. The Christmas season in earlier times had presented special
				security problems for the city, as shown in the civic governments regular November/December
				prohibitions of going about at night wearing masks or visors and (in the fourteenth century)
				of entering peoples houses to play at dice. These prohibitions begin in the records in
				December 1334 and become regular from the 1370s on.165 Festive mumming activities
				with masks were apparently being used in some cases for criminal purposes. 166 The last
				prohibition recorded in the city&apos;s manuscripts in the fifteenth century is in the 1460s, but
				in 1512 face coverings were still a concern nationally. A statute was passed in 1512 prohibit*
				ing persons from owning or selling visors or disguising themselves as mummers: and the
				city again prohibited visors and painted faces in December 1526. 167</p>
				<p>Christmas–season festivities indoors, in individual households including those of the
				mayor and of the sheriffs, would have included music, mummings, and games, with lords
				of misrule at least in some cases appointed to direct the festivities. 16s Such activities in their
				households would probably have been largely at the discretion and expense of the indi–
				vidual city officers, whose records have not survived. Only the occasional civic record affords
				us a glimpse of civic Christmas celebrations: for example, a wassail and an interlude in
				Christmas week 1511–12 at a skinner sheriffs house: a wassail and disguising for a Skinners
				Company mayor on 23 [anuary 1510: Thomas Brandon, a court entertainer, given London
				citizenship in 1526 in return for providing entertainment annually at the mayoral banquet
				held on the Monday after Epiphany. ]ohn Turnour, a sergeant responsible for devising
				Christmas festivities– songs, pastimes, sports– in the sheriffs households, was provided
				in 1527 with a house rentfree in his infirm old age.16 In February 155677 it was agreed
				that henceforth the city&apos;s waits should attend on Candlemas Day (2 February) at the houses
				of the mayor and sheriffs, as they already did at Christmas. 17 Festive interchanges in the
				Christmas season between the city and the court took place in the late fourteenth and
				early fifteenth centuries, when the city presented mummings as seasonal gifts to Richard I1
				and to Henry IV. These would have been elaborate displays of costume and probably dance
				and music, performed by professionals and[or by the mumming–givers themselves: and
				we have company or chronicle history records of them in all of 1352–3, 1353–4, and
				1400–1, with a lengthy description also surviving for 1376–7 (when Richard Il was not
				yet king). The A₭¢₭€₱$₮₮£ Ch৲¢₭€₯₮£ tells us of 130 mummers – costumed as esquires, knights,
				an emperor, a pope, cardinals, and legates– riding at night from Newgate through Cheapside
				with music and torches, to the royal palace at Rennington (in Surrey), where they played
				at dice with the young prince and distributed gifts.1 In 1425–30 the city companies and
				the court both commissioned Christmas–season mummings from poet ]ohn Lydgate. We
				have no city or company records, but the mumming texts themselves have survived, perhaps
				because they were part of special celebrations that season of the November 1420 corona*
				tion of Henry vi and his upcoming departure in 1430 for coronation also in France. 1s One
				mumming was performed for the mayor (William Estfeld, a mercer) as a gift from the
				Mercers Company on Twelfth Night: the other was presented to the mayor by the Gold
				smiths Company on Candlemas night. 1/ In 1440–1 the Merchant Taylors accounts record
				a gift (collected from company members) toward the costs of the duke of Gloucester&apos;s
				mummers, riding through London to the company&apos;s hall at Christmas (the duke was an
				honorary member of the company). Perhaps Gloucester himself met part of the costs, or
				perhaps the mummers made the rounds of a number of halls in the city. Court and city
				festive interchanges in the Christmas season are also documented in the 1550s, although
				again (as with the Lydgate mummings) not in the civic records: here they appear in Henry
				Machyn&apos;s diary. In the Christmas seasons of 1551–2, 1552–3, 1556–7, and 1557–8 a lord
				of misrule from the court came to London with his entourage (including musicians, morris
				dancers or disguises, and in 1556–7 a devil with fire and a figure of Death with a dart in
				his hand), and visited the houses of the mayor, sheriffs, and aldermen (the sheriffs and
				aldermen are not always mentioned). In 1551–2 and 1552–3 he also made a proclama–
				tion at the Cross in Cheapside, and in 1552–3 he was met by a lord of misrule of one of
				the sheriffs. 1S In May 1555 common council, as a cost–cutting measure, forbade (as with
				the withe above) further lords of misrule in the mayor&apos;s and sheriffs households. 177</p>
				<p>Records of some of the London companies (such as the Cutlers in the fifteenth century)
				include payments for hall decorations at Christmas (the Cutlers, for example, paid for holly
				and ivy) and at midsummer. (This collection, however, does not include records of such
				decorations.) Plays during the Christmas season were also a regular entertainment for at least
				three of the London companies: see below, pp xlvii–xlviii, on the Blacksmiths, Carpenters,
				and Cutlers.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Company Feast Times and Similar Company Occasions</head>
				<p>
				Every London company, probably from its beginnings as a formal body (as opposed to a
				looser kind of grouping, whether religious, social, or craft[trade–associated), held an annual
				biennial, or sometimes triennial major feast time when the members came together at the
				hall (their own or rented) to choose new company officers for the next one, two, or three
				years.17 At this time company members also went to mass together, and also usually to a
				separate dirge for deceased members, and attended a major dinner at which the new master
				and[or wardens were presented, often in a ceremony that involved the new officers being
				crowned with garlands to the sound of trumpets or other music. 1/ Dinner entertainment
				might be provided, including music (instrumental and[or vocal), a play, tumbling, and
				the like: and such entertainment was doubtless much more widespread than the records
				indicate. High–ranking guests, in the case of the wealthier companies, might also be present.
				For many companies, early manuscripts of the kinds most likely to contain information
				about feast times (largely accounts, although sometimes court minutes and memorandum.
				ordinance books) either have not survived, or have survived only partially, or for some years
				are minimal summaries. Moreover the extant early accounts are of receipts and payments
				flowing through the companies: and collections for entertainers at a dinner or supper could
				be taken at the events without the collected money appearing in the companies accounts. 1s
				Provision of dinner to the performers might be part of the payment.s: Individual members
				(especially the wardens, who in some companies– for example, the Goldsmiths– were
				personally responsible for the costs of the feast–time dinner) might also pay personally for
				performers. Perhaps barter arrangements were sometimes made. Thomas Brandon, for
				example, who received the city&apos;s freedom in return for providing entertainments for the
				mayor on specific civic occasions, held his company membership with the Leathersellers
				who might well also have struck an entertainment agreement with him.s Bequests covering
				entertainment costs are also a possibility, since company members sometimes willed money
				for dinners to be held in their memory.1s Finally some companies recorded their detailed
				feast–time expenses not in their main accounts but in separate accounts which were not
				preserved.</p>
				<p>Companies of course also feasted together at times other than the election time: but the
				election–time occasion was usually the most extensive and elaborate of company occasions
				and the one for which entertainment was most often provided, although a few of the Londori
				companies instead record entertainment regularly at another annual or biennial time. Some
				companies also record entertainment on other miscellaneous or regular occasions, such as at
				a dinner when the accounts were audited, and in some cases on the day of the mayor&apos;s oath*
				taking at Westminster.</p>
				<p>A company&apos;s major feast time, at least by the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries, often
				extended over two days, or even three days or more for some of the larger companies, and
				its main date, usually set down in company ordinances, might be highly specific (for exam*
				ple, a particular saints day) or more general (for example, around midsummer). The ]une
				1502 ordinances of the Leathersellers combine specificity and flexibility, specifying that the
				company&apos;s feast is to be held on the Assumption of Our Lady (15 August) when it falls on a
				Sunday or a Monday, on the Sunday after the Assumption when the latter falls on a Saturday
				and otherwise is to be deferred at the wardens pleasure.186 The records of some companies
				demonstrate, however, that a company might even be flexible about a supposedly fixed date
				The Bakers accounts, for example, make clear that at least sometimes their St Clement€
				Day dinner took place shortly after St Clements Day (23 November), usually on the Sunday
				after. In 1535 the Goldsmiths held St Dunstan&apos;s Day (10 May) on 24 May. In 1547 the
				Drapers decided that since, in this year, their usual main feast–day of the Monday after the
				Assumption would fall on St Bartholomew&apos;s Eve (23 August), they would substitute for it
				the day after the Assumption. 187</p>
				<p>A company&apos;s feast time was normally at or around the time of the main festival of the
				company&apos;s patron saint, although not always. The Armourers, for example, held their feast
				time around Lammas (I August), although their patron saint was St George, whose annual
				feast–day was 23 April. A company&apos;s yeomanry might have the same feast time or a different
				one. The annual feast time of the main Merchant Taylors company, for example, was at
				the Nativity of St ]ohn the Baptist (24 [une), but the feast time for the company&apos;s yeomanry
				was at the Decollation of St ]ohn the Baptist (20 August). The Vintners had two major
				feast times a year, the two festivals of St Martin (4 [uly and II November): their election
				of new officers took place at the November festival. The feast times of the various London
				companies– with their mix of religious and secular events – are found on various dates
				spread throughout the mayoral year, although the time of the mayoral change–over in late
				October appears to have been largely avoided. 1ss Company officers seem normally to have
				changed over at, or shortly after, the feast time itself: but the time when the outgoing
				officers submitted their accounts for audit could vary from almost immediately after the
				change date to several or many months later.1s The accounts of outgoing wardens often
				included expenses incurred after the nominal closing date (usually the feast time, but
				sometimes before it) of the accounts, such as the expenses for the feast–time dinner, at the
				end of the wardens term, even when the dinner followed by a month or more the stated
				closing date.0 The audit itself could be within a month or so of account submission or
				could take more than a year.</p>
				<p>Records of music at company feast times can be difficult to interpret, given that such
				feast times always included both religious and secular components, and it is sometimes
				unclear whether musicians are being paid for performing at mass, in a religious procession,
				at a company dinner or supper, or at some combination of these. The problem exists in
				the records of a number of the companies, since feast–time expenses in general are usually
				grouped together, and sometimes the headings under which payments are found (for example
				Dinner, or Mass) are clearly misleading. The Grocers, for example, in 1527–8, list music
				expenses for ij dayes under the heading of the election banquet. Probably one or more
				musicians usually played at the election dinner, for the garlanding ceremony through which,
				in many companies, the newly chosen master and/or wardens were presented to the com
				pany, and sometimes they probably also provided dinner music. We seldom, however,
				have information beyond basic, unexplained payments and disquietingly, whatever the
				manuscript headings, the records occasionally tell us – and so at other times may not be
				telling us– that musicians are playing both at mass and at dinner, and[or on other feast*
				time occasions. Terminology in the records is also often unclear. In general, minstrels
				in the civic manuscripts appears to have been used as an all–purpose term for musicians
				and so we can see what kinds of music are being played, and in some cases by whom, only
				when more specific terms are employed. Minstrels, for example, in some records may have
				been one or two trumpeters, perhaps announcing new company officers at an election dinner
				In others they have been a varied group providing dinner music, and in yet others have been
				one or more musicians providing music of different kinds at different feast–time occasions.
				The term waits indicates specifically the citys own salaried musicians (see pp lx–lxi). The
				term players can also be problematic, given that in this time period it can refer, especially
				before the sixteenth century, both to instrumental musicians and to actors, or even to general
				entertainers: but company records normally differentiate between minstrels (musicians) and
				players, and in most companies with records of players there is also a pattern, or a continu*
				ing tradition, which over the years makes clear that the term is being used with reference to
				acting. It must be kept in mind, however, that early entertainers were versatile: musicians
				might also act, and actors could often sing and play musical instruments. The records never
				give us performance titles, and only once provide a performance description: in the Drapers
				minutes and records for 1518–10. 194</p>
				<p>For information generally on music, pageantry, and other entertainment sponsored by
				the London companies, for the fourteenth century we have only four companies– the
				Mercers, Grocers, Goldsmiths, and Merchant Taylors– with extant accounts, court minutes,
				and[or ordinance₮memorandum books (the types of manuscripts most likely to contain
				musical or theatrical information) which yield records for inclusion in this collection: and
				for only two are there manuscripts with relevant feast–time information. The Mercers
				extant manuscripts in general, from the fourteenth to the sixteenth century, supply no
				musical or theatrical information about company feast times or similar internal company
				occasions. The Grocers fourteenth–to–fifteenth–century Black Book (a mix of memoranda
				and accounts) contains no fourteenth–century records of feast–time music or entertainment
				The Goldsmiths combined accounts and minutes, however, which begin in 1334, provide
				the first extant record of music at a company feast time – on St Dunstans Day in 1366,
				when the company went into the fields with apples, wine, and music: ৳ and from 1384–5
				to 1402 the company continues to record St Dunstans Day minstrels, although the expenses
				of the religious and secular parts of the feast time are not differentiated from one another
				The minstrels may have played at feast–time processions and observances (religious, secular,
				or both), at the customary drinking on the eve, and[or at dinner on the day. (They are
				usually paid a considerable sum of money.) The company also owned its own musical instru
				ments. 12s The Merchant Taylors extant accounts begin only in 1358: but the company pays
				for minstrels at its ]une feast time in the 1308–0 account (and continues to pay regularly
				for musicians at the feast time in the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries).</p>
				<p>For the fifteenth century, more potentially relevant company manuscripts have survived,
				and also gradually they become, in some cases, more detailed./ Of the four companies with
				manuscripts already discussed for the fourteenth century, the Mercers accounts continue to
				supply no feast–time theatrical or musical information. The Goldsmiths combined minutes
				and accounts after 1402 rarely include any details of feast–time expenses, although one
				notable exception occurs in 1448 when payments are recorded to all of minstrels, a harper,				a piper, and morris dancers. 155 In 1473 a St Dunstans Day summarized accounting refers
				to the detail of feast–time expenses as recorded elsewhere.1/ The Grocers Black Book
				(1345–1463) and subsequent memorandum book (1463–1557) contain no records of
				fifteenth–century feast–time music or other feast–time entertainment, other than possibly
				the payment in 1431–2 to the players of Gloucester by the mayor and the company master
				(both grocers): the occasion involving the players is not noted.2o The company&apos;s regular
				accounts, however, which begin in 1447–8 (with a gap from 1471 to 1511) normally show,
				from 1455–6, an annual major dinner or supper involving musicians and often other
				entertainers.2l Sometimes the payments are specified as for two days. Musicians of various
				kinds (including three times, in 1463, 1467, and 1468, Henry Luter –or Henry, luter*
				and his children) are always paid, while payments to other entertainers are frequent from
				1456 to 1468. These other entertainers are a varied group: tumblers (1456, 1463, 1468), a
				juggler (1450), and players (1461, 1465, 1467, 1468, 1460): twice (1461, 1465) the players
				are named as William of Gracechurch&apos;s (perhaps a parish clerk with a playing group). The
				Merchant Taylors, who paid for minstrels at their ]une feast time in their 1308–0 account
				continue to pay regularly for musicians at the companys feast time in the fifteenth century.
				Largely the fifteenth–century musicians are trumpeters (usually eight of them in the mid
				1420s through the 1460s): and twice in the 1450s they are recorded specifically as participa*
				ting in a procession to and from the priory of St ]ohn of ]erusalem at Clerkenwell (the
				Merchant Taylors patron saint was St [ohn the Baptist). Perhaps both before and after this
				decade, in the fifteenth century, they are also sometimes or usually processing: they are
				regularly paid a large amount of money. There is additional feast–time music in 1454–5
				and especially 1455–6, with Henry Luter[luter and his boys paid in both of those years,
				and also other musicians (including the city waits) in 1455–6. (The waits also appear in a
				couple of other subsequent fifteenth–century years.) Unspecified entertainers are also paid
				in 1460–1, and additional musicians in 1457–8 and several times in the 1470s the minstrels
				are specified as being those of the king and other lords. Players are also paid in 1410–11:
				and unless these players are musicians – very unlikely, since minstrels are paid as well–
				this record significantly comes some two years after the last known performance, in 1400
				of the multi–day biblical London Skinners Well/Clerkenwell play (see pp liv–lvi), and is
				the first recorded appearance in the civic manuscripts of players at a company feast time. 202
				Twice in the fifteenth century (1455–6, 1473–4) the company also pays at the feast time
				for a tumbler. 203</p>
				<p>The most significant fifteenth–century records of continuing theatrical – and in one case
				musical –activity at company feast times are those of the Blacksmiths, Cutlers, and Drapers.
				The Cutlers have account rolls extant for only thirty–six years in the fifteenth century (and
				for none in the sixteenth century), between 1442–3 and 1457–8, but in every roll, payment
				is made for players or a play during the Christmas season, indicating a company tradition
				extending over more than fifty years. The Blacksmiths, who were associated with the Cutlers
				by trade, in 1426 mandated company funding for a play at their annual [anuary quarter day
				(that is, also during the Christmas season, rather than at their annual feast time in ]une):
				when their surviving century accounts begin, in 1455–7, the play is being regularly recorded
				(on into the mid–sixteenth century).2 The Drapers also have extant an early–to–mid–fifteenth*
				century ordinance (c 1418–62) mandating a regular company allowance to the wardens for the
				provision of players and minstrels (among other items) each year at the company&apos;s August feast
				time: the ordinance book also refers (some time between c 1436 and 1462) to plays and other
				sports in the hall at (the feast–time) dinner, and again in 1474 to minstrels and players in
				relation to the dinner€৳ The extant accounts, which begin probably in 1420, indicate players
				and musicians at the feast time in every year from 1425–30 to 1440–1 for which an account
				is extant, and then, after a gap in the accounts 1441–75, from 1480–1 in almost every year
				to the end of the fifteenth century (and on into the sixteenth). 206</p>
				<p>Other companies with extant fifteenth–century accounts, court minutes, and the like whick
				include musical and[or theatrical feast–time records are the Brewers (accounts 1418–10 to
				1438–0, with four years missing), Carpenters (incomplete accounts from 1437), Founders
				(incomplete accounts from 1497), and Ironmongers (incomplete accounts from 1455). The
				Brewers record a play/players at their feast time regularly from 1410 to 1435, except in 1430,
				when money was a problem: and five times the play is specifically noted as by (normally four
				clerks. Identification of playing troupes is unusual in fifteenth–century London company accounts,
				and these five particular identifications may indicate a theatrical situation (availability of clerks
				acting troupes) typical of the early fifteenth century shortly after the demise of Londons Skinners
				Well[ Clerkenwell play, which had been performed by clerks (see pp liv–lvi). Perhaps, however
				the Brewers simply had a preference for clerks as players: the companys employment of them fits
				with what seems to have been its close association (not seen in the records of any other London
				company), going right up to 1537, with the St Nicholas boy–bishop tradition previously dis*
				cussed.2/ The Brewers usually also pay one or more musicians at the feast time, and in four years
				they pay Thomas lesto¥r, and once singers (along with the players). Other occasional dinners
				also feature music and, once, players.2s The Carpenters pay one or more minstrels at their mid*
				summer feast time in probably every year from 1475 to 1400 (and on into the sixteenth century),
				and twice at the feast time (1454, 1480) they also pay for a play/players, and once (1401) for a
				tumbler€¢৳ Occasionally before 1400 they pay for a play₮players at other times (Easter quarter day,
				1482, an unspecified quarter day, 1466–7): and four times in the 1400s they have players (anc
				once a minstrel) at Candlemas quarter day (at the very end of the Christmas season), which
				in the sixteenth century becomes (with one exception) their only occasion for players. The
				Carpenters thus join the Blacksmiths and the Cutlers in preferring a winter to a summer occa*
				sion for theatrical entertainment, and like the Blacksmiths they feature music at their summer
				feast time. The Founders pay for minstrels at their feast–time dinner or supper regularly from
				1458–0 (and on into the sixteenth century). The Ironmongers consistently record payments
				to one or more minstrels at their biennial feast time from 1485 to 1400 (and also in 1470).
				For the sixteenth century, the Mercers records continue to provide no information on
				performances at company feast times, although it is hard to believe that the company did not
				have both plays and music on such occasions. The Mercers Company was first in precedence
				among all the London companies. Its court connections were extensive. It spent lavishly on
				the sixteenth–century Midsummer Watch (the Drapers records tell us), and in the first half
				of the sixteenth century its members included playwrights, musicians, and theatrical producers,
				such as [ohn Heywood, William Crane, and Henry Walton, and theatrically interested
				politicians/administrators such as Sir Thomas More. Mercer ]ohn Maynard, when sheriff in
				1552–3, is noted by Henry Machyn in his diary as a key figure both in Christmas–season
				misrule activities involving a city–court interchange and in a festive street celebration ir
				March. 210 Unfortunately the Mercers main accounts for 1464 to 1558 have not survived
				although their feast–time costs might well have been recorded elsewhere in any case. The
				Goldsmiths combined accounts and minutes are extant, but include only a couple of minori
				feast–time payments for music.2 The Grocers accounts continue, however, after their gap
				from 1471 to 151I, to provide significant information. As in the fifteenth century (from 1455)
				they normally show, although with decreasing frequency after 1536, an annual major dinner
				or supper involving musicians and often other entertainers.2 (The accounts for 1537–9 and
				1550–1 are missing, and for a number of other years the election dinner[supper entry is a
				summary only.) ]ugglers are paid in 1512 and 1526, jesters in 1541, and players in 1525
				(the king&apos;s players), 1526 (only one king&apos;s player, with a juggler), and perhaps 1535 (the
				children of the duke of Suffolk&apos;s house: perhaps a musical group only, perhaps both musical
				and theatrical).21 In 1531 clerks and choristers are paid for singing ballads and providing
				other pastimes: in 1532 payment is made to the clerk of St Magnus (that is, of St Magnus
				the Martyr Church) and his children, who perhaps were those paid in 1531 as well, as
				singing and[or playing choristers. (This group was also paid, in 1533, by the Vintners.)ai.
				Bowbank, a minstrel named in the Drapers accounts around this time as well, is paid in all
				of 1525, 1526, 1527, 1528, and 1530. Two days are specified for the feast time at least
				twice. In 1513–14 the king&apos;s players, along with musicians, are paid for performance at an
				account dinner.</p>
				<p>The extant Merchant Taylors accounts have a gap between 1484 and 1545: but, after the
				long gap, musicians (now usually the city waits), as in the fifteenth century, are still regularly
				recorded as employed at the feast time, with the children of Paul&apos;s (that is, the choristers of
				the choir school at St Paul&apos;s Cathedral) also being paid to play instruments and[or to sing
				at every feast–time dinner from 1549–50 to 1556–7. (The 1557–8 account is missing.) In
				1554–5 musicians of my lord of Pembroke are also paid. In both 1555–6 and 1556–7, the
				records tell us that the waits played all through the dinner and the election.
				Other companies with relevant manuscripts continuing from the fifteenth century are
				the Blacksmiths, Brewers, Carpenters, Drapers, Founders, and Ironmongers. The Brewers
				sixteenth–century main accounts (from 1500) differ from their fifteenth–century ones in
				recording no feast–time performance expenses, and their sixteenth–century court minutes
				are also silent on this matter: but the accounts of their yeomanry, extant from 1555–6,
				include payments to minstrels in a dinner context in both 1555–6 and 1556–7.21 The
				Ironmongers accounts (running only to 1538), despite their late–fifteenth–century consist*
				ent payments to minstrels, record in the sixteenth century only a couple of occasional
				payments to musicians. The records of the other four companies, however, indicate continu*
				ing feast–time performances. The Blacksmiths apparent fifteenth–century tradition of play
				performance at the [anuary quartereday dinner continues into the sixteenth century (where
				the dinner is regularly called the cony feast) until at least 1555: after a gap in the extant
				accounts from 1400 to ]anuary 1500/10, the play is recorded annually from 1510 to 1526
				(except in 1521 and 1524), and biennially, in odd–numbered (modern) calendar years, from
				1520 to 1541. (The accounts in the late 1520s are defective.) The details of the company&apos;s
				major feasts then begin to be recorded in another manuscript, no longer extant:s but in
				the 1547–) account the cony feast, with its play, reappears, and is recorded biennially once
				more, in 1540, 1551, and 1555.2/ Once, in 1525, the actors are identified: as the king&apos;£
				players: they are paid the unusually large sum– for the company at that time–of 6s 8d.
				The company also pays minstrels at its biennial major feast time, at midsummer, in about
				half of the relevant years from 1511 to 1523, and regularly (biennially) from 1525 to 1541:
				unlike the cony–feast play, however, the midsummer–feast musicians reappear only once, in
				1551, after 1541 and up to 1558.28 The Carpenters in the sixteenth century continue their
				regular feast–time payments to minstrels, often adding the waits and occasionally other music
				as well (for example, singers of ballads at dinner in 1505): and in 1502, 1505, and regularly
				from 1507 to 1513 they pay for players at Candlemas. 28 Like the Cutlers and the Blacksmiths,
				their preferred time for plays[players is thus the (London) Christmas season (though at
				its very end) and not their summer feast time (although they pay for morris dancers and
				barnard pleyer at the feast time in 1506): and they also pay for a jester[storyteller on May
				quarter day in 1505, and for a harper on All Hallows quarter day in 1506. After a gap in
				their extant accounts, however, from 1516 to 1545, no more of such entertainers are recorded.
				although feast–time minstrels continue on a regular basis to 1558.220</p>
				<p>The Founders pay for minstrels at their feast–time supper or dinner regularly from 1408–0
				to 1504–5, and frequently from 1511 or 1512 to 1529–30: once they pay for players, in
				1525–30. Information is limited, because some of their accounts are minimal and, from
				1531 to 1530, consist largely of headings only.</p>
				<p>The Drapers sixteenth–century feast–time records are the richest of those of any of the
				London companies. Their accounts drop, the previously regular recordings (from the fifteenth
				century) of feast–time minstrels and players after 1507–8, including them again only once
				before 1515–16: but the company&apos;s minutes and records manuscripts, extant from 1515–16,
				pick up the recording of such activities, and regularly record them from 1515–16 up to and
				including 1541. Moreover, for all the years in which we know that feast–time dinners were
				held and records are extant, there are usually two plays, over two days, at the feast time, and
				the records name in most years both the acting troupes and the musicians paid, although
				unfortunately –as with all the companies records of plays and players– we have no play titles,
				and only once any indication of what the actors were performing: a single actor playing a
				friar at a supper for the bachelors in 1510.2 A few other companies occasionally name the
				playing troupes they employ (often the king&apos;s players): the Drapers regular naming (often by
				the name of an actor£leader) is unusual, and shows a considerable range of acting companies
				employed, and the close cultural ties of the city and the court. Almost every troupe is one
				sponsored by royalty or the nobility: the king&apos;s players, the queen&apos;s players, the prince&apos;s players,
				the duke of Suffolk&apos;s players, the duke of Norfolk&apos;s players – and, only once, a parish clerk&apos;s
				company: The Drapers, unlike the Grocers, do not pay for a variety of types of entertain.
				ment: only once is an entertainer other than players and minstrels recorded: a bearward,
				accompanying some Dutch trumpeters, in 1521.23 The minstrel Bowbank (employed also by
				the Grocers) turns up in a number of years between 1520 and 1540. Records also indicate
				that the Drapers made use of performers on special occasions other than the feast time. In
				1525, for example, there is a play at a dinner at Michaelmas with the outgoing and incoming
				draper sheriffs, and in 1557 the company pays the children of Paul&apos;s– probably the cathedral&apos;s
				choristers, but the boys of St Paul&apos;s grammar school are also possible– to perform an inter*
				lude at a dinner for the Russian ambassador.22 A harper and a luter are specifically recorded
				as paid for the occasion of the election in 1524.</p>
				<p>A number of other companies begin only in the sixteenth century to have records, before
				1550, of feast–time performances: the Armourers, Bakers, Clothworkers, Coopers, Tallow
				Chandlers, Vintners, Wax Chandlers, and Weavers, and minimally the Pewterers and Stationers.
				The Armourers have court minutes extant from 1413 but minimal before 1536, and extant
				accounts beginning only in 1407. They regularly pay minstrels at their feast time from 1532
				to 1545 and again in 1551: and in all of 1553, 1555, and 1557 their court minutes note
				receipts from an old custom of contributions by the livery to the feast৳time wine and minstrels.
				Twice (1535 and 1543) the company also pays for minstrels at a dinner after the mayor&apos;s oath*
				taking. No players are ever recorded except baldock ye playr, named in the court minutes as
				dining in the hall on the mayoral oath–taking day in 1541. 225</p>
				<p>The Bakers, with incomplete accounts from 1400 and sixteenth–century minutes from
				]anuary 1536/7, record itemized expenses for their feast–time dinner in only six years between
				1400 and 1558 (the accounts sometimes note that dinner expenses are listed elsewhere): but in
				five of those six years (1525, 1528, 1531, 1532, 1546) minstrels are paid, and the waits and the
				king&apos;s players in the one other year (1536), with plays (likely also at the feast time though not so
				specified) also recorded in two years in which feast–time dinner expenses are not listed. One of
				the plays (in 1520) is by the children of [ohn Wilmot, a mayor&apos;s officer closely associated with
				the Bakers Company, whose troupe does not turn up elsewhere in any extant company records:
				and one (in 1530) is paid for in part only, as Iod for the rest of A play at the hall, perhaps
				indicating that a collection had been taken up among company members for the cost of the
				play and had come up somewhat short, thus requiring a further contribution from the company
				itself.26 The company might thus have had other plays, regularly or occasionally, funded by
				collections that were never entered into the accounts. Minstrels are also recorded in five other
				years, in the 1550s, where the costs of more than one occasion are grouped together: and in
				1531 4d was also given at the feast time to a man that pleyed w€t฿ A Dogg.'227</p>
				<p>The Clothworkers, formed in 1528 by a union of the Shearmen and the Fullers, and with
				accounts extant from 1528 and minutes from ]anuary 1536/7, regularly pay for minstrels in most
				vears, to 1558, at their annual election feast time. The minstrels apparently played at the choosing
				of the new company officers: they may also have played more widely at the feast time, but the
				records do not say. (See The Documents, p liii.) The Tallow Chandlers, with company accounts
				from 1549–51 and yeomanry accounts from 1518–1, record payments always for minstrels at
				the biennial company feast time (usually a two– to three–day occasion), and for players at two of
				the five feast times (1553 and 1550) listed in their extant accounts to 1550, the 1558–) payment
				being to the boys of the Hospital. Probably these were the schoolboys of St Anthony&apos;s Hospital,
				who also performed in a Merchant Taylors mayoral pageant in 1556, but also possible would
				be the schoolboys of Christ&apos;s Hospital (founded 1553).22 The company&apos;s yeomanry pay for
				minstrels in all but a few years of their recorded feast times, 1518–10 to 1558–0, for players
				steadily (for only two years are they missing) between 1522 and 1548,22 and for a dysour
				(jester, storyteller) in 1510. The Wax Chandlers, in their accounts beginning in 1528, have
				feast–time waits and minstrels who may be for religious or secular purposes, or both, although
				the minstrels seem normally associated with the dinner (see The Documents, pp cxxi–cxxii).
				Players are paid once, in 1538.</p>
				<p>The Vintners pay musicians– usually waits but sometimes minstrels and sometimes both
				at most [uly and November feast times recorded from 1508 to 1558. They name the min*
				strel Bowbank (also employed by the Drapers and the Grocers) several times from 1527 to
				1535, and twice pay one Golder for a play or interlude (in ]uly 1530 and ]uly 1542). Erler,
				E₯₯l£৳€$৳૱€₯$₮ L¢₭₨¢₭, p xxxv, has identified Golder as a conduct (that is, a salaried choir
				leader) at St Lawrence ]ewry in 1547 and at St Mary at Hill in 1540–50, and organist at St
				Georges Windsor c 1560–3. His playing group is presumably a clerks or choristers group.280
				Also once (uly 1542) the company pays Wyat the jester, and once (]uly 1533) the clerk of
				St Magnus (the Martyr) and his company: since the Grocers also paid this clerk&apos;s company
				for entertainment in 1532 and perhaps 1531, so here too we may suppose that entertainment
				rather than church music is involved, from a parish clerk with a company of musical (and
				theatrical€) choristers. Both Golder&apos;s plays and the clerk of St Magnus company&apos;s perform
				ance are at the [uly feast time rather than at the November election feast time. Uniquely, in
				November 1557, the company pays a Scottish woman who sang and played a lute.</p>
				<p>Miscellaneously, for feast times and other such occasions, the Coopers (accounts from 1527,
				minutes from e 1554), in 1545–6 pay 12d to minstrels at a venison supper (and also money to
				porters to carry regals), and in 1547–8 pay 2s 4d to minstrels at a general dinner. The Weavers
				accounts full, partial, or summarized, from 1406, and missing 1408–1528 and occasional
				other years) pay for players on their Christmas quarter day in 1552–3 (and for a minstrel at
				the Mermaid on October quarter day in 1548). The Stationers accounts begin in 1554, and
				in 1556–7 they pay I0s to minstrels at dinner. The Skinners (accounts from 1401) record two
				wassails: for a skinner sheriff, Thomas Mirfyn, at his house in 1511–12 (with an interlude),
				and for Mirfyn again, as mayor, at Skinners Hall in 1518–10 (with a disguising).
				The Pewterers Company (accounts from 1451, minutes from 1551) should also be men
				tioned, as a specific example of one reason why the absence in company manuscripts of
				records of feast–time theatrical activity cannot necessarily be taken as an indication of the
				absence of such activity. The Pewterers record no payments to players until 1558–0, probably
				(that is, in 1550) after the concluding date of this collection: but then the main company
				accounts include a payment of more for the playe then was gathered of the... Companye. 23
				As with perhaps the Bakers, did company members normally take up an unrecorded collec.
				tion, in advance or at the occasion itself, and in this year the company itself was obliged to
				contribute additional funds€ As we have seen, the Blacksmiths regularly combined a number
				of different funding sources to pay for their feast time, including a collection and a company
				subsidy€ The accounts of the Pewterers yeomanry, also in 1558–0, include an order that
				every man is to pay, as in the past, Id towards the play at the yeomanry dinner: the yeomanry
				accounts, extant from 1406–8, have not previously recorded any play. The play might have
				been a very recent development, or it might have been a (short or long) continuing tradition.
				In short, beginning in a few extant fourteenth–century manuscripts, and increasingly from
				the early fifteenth century and on into the sixteenth, a significant number of London companies
				record regular or occasional payments to players and/or musicians, as well as sometimes to
				other kinds of entertainers, at their regular major feast times and/or, in some cases, at another
				significant time in the company year, and sometimes also on other special occasions. Especially
				notable are the continuing plays and players recorded by the Cutlers, Blacksmiths, and Drapers,
				the latter two over a span of more than a hundred years, and the continuing employment of
				musicians recorded by the Carpenters, Drapers, Grocers, and Merchant Taylors. A number of
				other companies record significant activity by players, musicians, or both, for the short periods in
				which their relevant manuscripts are extant and are sufficiently detailed to include payments to
				entertainers. A few have manuscripts indicating the potential recording of such details elsewhere,
				or the use of some method of funding entertainment other than through the company and its
				accounting processes. One company– the Mercers – although not recording any feast–time
				entertainment seems extremely unlikely, given its wealth, status, and specific individual members
				not to have had such entertainment. The records we have are most likely the tip of the iceberg
				with many more companies enjoying special performance entertainment than having extant
				records of it between the fourteenth century and 1558.</p>
				<p>The companies in London, at a variety of economic levels, thus probably provided a
				steady source of employment for musicians, players, and other entertainers, through a regu*
				lar, dependable stream of both major and minor internal occasions – especially feast times
				spread throughout the mayoral year.2/ To this they added further employment through the
				regular processions, both religious and secular, in which they participated, including, on the
				secular side, the mayoral and shrieval inauguration processions to Westminster and the
				Midsummer Watch. The city also depended on musicians and players – as well as designers,
				producers, and craftsmen skilled in theatrical constructions– for occasions such as royal entries.
				Special company commissions for special occasions were also probably not unusual, at leas૱
				sometimes giving employment to musicians and[or actors. We have seen, for example, the
				mummings commissioned by the Mercers and the Goldsmiths for Christmas–season enter*
				tainment in 1425–30 (although we do not know whether the performers were amateur or
				professional),2 and two short Lydgate poems may also have been written for London civic
				performance or recitation of some kind. The Legend of St George, according to its manuscript
				rubric, is the devyse of a steyned halle of the lyf of Saint George, written with balades, at
				the request of the Armourers Company. It thus seems to have been a piece commissioned to
				have been recited or sung, on a special occasion, for the showcasing of a wall hanging or
				mural of St George (the company&apos;s patron saint). Bycorne and Chychevache, said in its
				manuscript rubric to be a deuise of a peynted or desteyned clothe for an halle a parlour or a
				chaumbre and to have been written at the request of a London citizen, deals with henpecked
				husbands and domineering wives, and may be descriptive of a wall hanging or a performed
				or recited representation of a wall hanging. The identity of the London citizen remains
				unknown, as does the reason for his request.28 The deuise may have been commissioned as
				an entertainment for a special company occasion, but a private household entertainment, or
				simply a design or memento, are also possibilities.2 There is no reason to think that suck
				commissions took place only in the early fifteenth century: in the seventeenth century, for
				example, we have extant commissioned texts from major playwrights, such as Thomas
				Middleton, to celebrate special civic occasions. Middleton wrote, for example, an entertain
				ment for performance before the mayor (a draper), aldermen, and other guests during the
				Easter holidays in 1622, and also an entertainment for the September 1613 opening of the
				New River, a water channel constructed to increase the city&apos;s water supply (goldsmith Hugh
				Middleton having been its prime mover: his brother in September 1613 was mayor–elect) a৳
				Companies might sometimes have recruited members to provide them with the musical,
				theatrical, and production skills which the companies would have needed on occasions such
				as regular feast times, seasonal celebrations, civic inaugurations, the Midsummer Watch, and
				so forth. Such members would likely, at least sometimes, have been musical or theatrical
				professionals, not amateurs largely practising the craft or trade of the companies concerned
				Also companies were sometimes pressured by the king or by other powerful sponsors into
				admitting such members: not necessarily against the companies wills.2 The needs of the
				companies in general, however, would have been sufficiently extensive for paid employment
				also to have been available, on a fairly steady basis, for the non–member musicians, other
				performers, crastsmen, and event producers, part–time or full–time, who made London and
				Westminster their headquarters. The companies were regular and reliable income sources for
				a London theatre industry.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>The Skinners Well/ Clerkenwell Play</head>
				<p>In at least the late fourteenth and early fifteenth centuries, and perhaps earlier as well, a
				multi–day biblical play was performed in London, just outside the city walls to the northwest,
				at Skinners Well or Clerks Well (the two wells were close to one another and the records
				appear to use the names interchangeably).2 From the subject matter as described both in
				royal accounts and in chronicle histories, the play was similar to the great biblical dramas
				performed in Cornwall in the fourteenth century (the Cornish Ordinalia, a three–day perform*
				ance event) and in the late fourteenth to sixteenth centuries in centres outside London, such
				as Tork and Coventry. It covered materials from both the Old Testament and the New (the
				creation to the Passion or Doomsday): and it took place over what seem to have been three
				to five days of performance, the number of performance days varying in different years.
				It may have been in existence as early as c 1300 (or before), for c 1300–1 a complaint
				was made by the prioress of St Mary Clerkenwell that crowds at miracles et lutes were
				trampling on priory crops, hedges, and ditches. 4 We have, in the civic records, a 1385 prohibi
				tion of a iew at Skinners Well৳૱ and other sources record what were clearly large–scale
				play performances in all of 1384, 1300, 1301, and 1400.2 Possibly the play was performed
				regularly but was recorded only when some special factor was involved: a prohibition, an
				especially elaborate production, a performance before royalty. (Richard II seems to have
				attended in 1300, and Henry IV certainly in 1400.) Possibly it was performed only on
				special occasions, in relation to the wishes or needs of the court: in both 1300 and 1400, for
				example, it preceded a major international tournament hosted by the king.2 Whatever the
				case, no records of its performance have been found after 1400, although chronicle histories
				multiplied in the fifteenth century and the civic records also became increasingly detailed:
				the play thus appears not to have outlived the early fifteenth century.2/ Its performers and
				producers were London clerks, both parish and other (that is, conventual and perhaps also
				administrative and legal)৳૱6 and given London&apos;s over one hundred parishes and its multitude
				of religious houses (three at or near Clerkenwell alone) and of secular institutions and
				households employing clerks, there would have been no shortage of manpower2/ We do not
				know, however, what organization(s) might have sponsored the performances. London&apos;s own
				city government was apparently not a direct sponsor, as in such a case we would have
				expected at least one or two records of, or references to, its involvement to have survived by
				the late fourteenth or early fifteenth century. The London Parish Clerks Company has been
				suggested by numerous historians: but it is uncertain whether at this time the company was
				strong enough to have organized, logistically and financially, a major multi–day production
				(although as a (religious) fraternity of St Nicholas, its membership extended well beyond
				parish clerks only).22 Other possible sponsors include one or more major religious houses.
				such as that of the Priory of St [ohn of [erusalem at Clerkenwell (the English headquarters
				of the religious order of the Rnights Hospitaller), a combination of two or three of the three
				religious houses at or near Clerkenwell, the Merchant Taylors (then Tailors) Company (which
				had a special connection with St ]ohns), and the Skinners Company (which sponsored an
				annual Corpus Christi procession from at least the end of the late fourteenth century).2¢
				Both companies had strong religious fraternities associated with them, and could also have
				worked with a religious institution such as St ]ohn&apos;s or– indirectly– with the city.250</p>
				<p>The demise of the Skinners Well/Clerkenwell play after 1400 does not mean that civic
				playing by clerks– parish and otherwise– in London then ceased. Indeed, it may have
				increased, in terms of the availability of small troupes for individual performances. Records of
				payments by the London companies for plays[players at their feast times or on other specia
				occasions begin shortly after the 1400 end of the Skinners Well/Clerkenwell play€৳: The first
				known record of players at a company feast time (the Tailors) is dated 141I (the players are
				not identified): and five times between 1418 (when their extant fifteenth–century accounts
				begin) and 1430 (when they end), the Brewers pay clerks (normally four) to perform for them
				On nine other occasions they also have players but do not identify them. Some other com.
				panies payments to players also are seen as their records begin to become extant: and largely
				the troupes involved are not named: but the Grocers pay one William of Gracechurch (and
				his fellows) for a play in both 1461 and 1465.2 Also the children who regularly performed
				in the street music and pageantry of royal entries were perhaps often under the leadership
				of a parish clerk. The Bridge House accounts, for example, as previously noted, record the
				clerk of St Magnus (the Martyr) and his children as participating in the 1465 coronation entry
				of Elizabeth Woodville, queen to Edward IV. 253</p>
				<p>In the sixteenth century, performing groups identified as clerks companies are outnumbered
				in the records by other named troupes. The Drapers Company, for example, usually names
				its feast–time players from 1516 on, and only once records a performance by a parish clerk&apos;s
				company: otherwise its named play performers are all royal and aristocratic troupes. The
				Grocers, however, at least once, in 1532, pay for a feast–time performance by the clerk of
				St Magnus and his children (although only music might have been involved), as do the
				Vintners, in 1533, and the Vintners are also probably paying for a clerk&apos;s group in 1530 and
				1542.2/ Parish clerks and their children continued to be active in the street pageantry of
				royal entries and the Midsummer Watch. Also the city issued licences, between 1520 and
				1520, to three different London parishes to perform plays. These, however, did not necessarily
				involve parish clerks, and in any case, apart from the licences, are the province of REEDS
				Ecclesiastical London. 255</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>School Drama, Music, and Pageantry</head>
				<p>
				In the 1560s or early 1570s, the boys of the London grammar school founded in 1561 by
				the Merchant Taylors Company began to perform plays for paying audiences at Merchant
				Taylors Hall€ and by at least the 1570s the boys of the choir school of St Paul&apos;s Cathedral (and
				by 1576 those of the Chapel Royal as well) began to present in the city so–called rehearsals,
				for a paying London audience, of plays they were preparing for performance at court before
				the queen.2 The civic records of school musical and theatrical activities before 1550, however,
				are of limited school performances for London companies and of limited school involvement
				in civic street theatre. The boys of the grammar school at St Paul&apos;s Cathedral, (re)founded
				in 1512 by the cathedral&apos;s dean, ]ohn Colet, but placed by him under the governance not
				of the church but of the London Mercers Company, had performed at least two or three
				plays privately, before Cardinal Wolsey and others, in the 1520s.2/ These plays themselves,
				household/court entertainments which do not appear in the civic records, are not the province
				of the C€৲€₯ L¢₭₨¢₭ collection: but their existence makes possible the speculation that the
				grammar–school boys could have been the children of Paul&apos;s recorded as performers of an
				interlude when the Russian ambassador was entertained at Drapers Hall in April 1557. 258
				The likelihood, of course, is that the 1557 children of Paul&apos;s were from the St Paul&apos;s choir
				school. As noted previously, the St Paul&apos;s choristers performed music at the feast times of the
				Merchant Taylors in every year from 1549–50 to 1556–7: possibly, given their abilities and
				history, plays were also sometimes involved, or possibly the 1557 Drapers Hall interlude
				was musical. The boys of the grammar school are not known to have performed any plays
				(or music), at court or elsewhere, after the 1520s.255 It may be significant, however, that in
				December 1557 the Mercers Company reprimanded the masters of St Paul&apos;s grammar school
				for letting the boys go to play: perhaps merely with reference to holidays[recreational time,
				but perhaps also with indirect or direct reference to theatrical activity. A similar reprimand
				had been issued in December 1527 after a high–profile play performance by the Paul&apos;s grammar*
				School boys before Wolsey and Henry VII1. 260</p>
				<p>The Boyes of the hospitall who performed at a Tallow Chandlers feast time in 1558–0
				were, as previously noted, probably the boys of the grammar school of St Anthony&apos;s Hospital
				who participated for the Merchant Taylors in a mayoral oath–taking show in 1556, although
				the 1558–) performers could instead have been from Christ&apos;s Hospital (founded by the city,
				for orphan children, in 1553). 26 An unidentified schoolmaster taught child performers in
				the 1535 Midsummer Watch (when a skinner was mayor): it is unclear from the records
				whether the performers were from his school.2: School groups also participated in royal
				entries: but the civic records seldom note this.2 The Paul&apos;s children recorded in Repertory
				12(1) as standing outside Paul&apos;s school when Edward vi formally passed through the city in
				1548–) were apparently the choristers. 264</p>				
				<p>Other children&apos;s groups found in the civic records are not school groups, unless the few
				recorded as performing at company dinners or suppers or as participating in royal entries
				and the Midsummer Watch, under the leadership of a parish clerk or musician, were from
				choir schools.25 Most often unidentified children– though sometimes individually noted to
				be the sons or daughters of named individuals – are recorded as singing or playing instru*
				ments in civic street theatre, or as performing in pageants, or both. Children, because of
				their light weight and often their choir–school or grammar–school training in music and[or
				rhetoric, were in demand as performers in the music and pageants of royal entries, the
				Watch, and eventually (once it had reintroduced, in the sixteenth century, its pageantic
				elements) the mayoral oath–taking procession. Children were also called upon to participate,
				singing, or merely dressed up, at the street celebrations, with bonfires, sometimes orderec
				by the city at the request or order of the Crown: the children at street bonfires in March
				1524–5 are said to be from the aldermen&apos;s wards, and the childen singing there are parish
				clerks groups.266</p>
				<p>A unique record in 1517–18 is significant for what it shows of the potential relationship
				between city apprenticeships and child performers. One Richard Nesshe (or Nasshe), a wax
				chandler and parish clerk, had a group of boy singers – at least one of them being his wax
				chandler apprentice– whom he hired out to parish churches. Another unique record in
				1485–6, is of the Merchant Taylors paying one Crane– possibly the father or other older
				relative of the William Crane who was master of the Chapel Children from 1523 and died
				in 1545–for participation with his children and organs, on a barge, in a civic welcome by
				water of Henry VI1. The identity of this group is otherwise unknown.2/ A children&apos;s group
				led by [ohn Wilmot, a city officer, performed for the Bakers Company in 1528–9: this
				group&apos;s identity also is otherwise unknown.26</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Play Prohibitions and Hall Rentals</head>
				<p>The Reformation brought a new dimension to theatrical activity in London: use, or fear of
				the use, of theatre for purposes of religious/political propaganda, along with the authorities
				usual fear of any public assembly which might lead to unrest and rioting.2/ In the 1540s
				we begin to find, in the civic records, prohibitions of plays, either in general or in certain
				kinds of locations, along with restrictions on playbills, on specific individuals houses as
				playing places, and on Sunday performances. The city authorities might act for the Crown or
				because of their own fears of civil unrest. The effort seems in part to have been to drive
				playing troupes, at times when plays were not banned altogether, into specific types of
				allowed performance locations. After an initial ban in April 1542 on common plays and
				interludes in company halls and in any public places, and a general prohibition in Apri
				1543, allowed locations included, in a (perhaps) October 1544 royal proclamation appar
				ently repeated in both 1545 and 1546, the London houses of the nobility, gentry, and
				respectable citizens, the open streets, and company halls. 27 Presumably one purpose of
				the 1544–6 proclamations was to avoid stopping non–controversial kinds of hall perform.
				ances which had routinely been taking place, before April 1542, on occasions such as
				company feast times. Significantly, however, company halls, though now allowed as perform*
				ance locations, were still under a restriction: any performance in a company hall had to
				be at the request of the company and in its presence. This would seem to be aimed perhaps
				at preventing the rental or offer otherwise of company halls to acting troupes or to any*
				one else who intended to hire an acting troupe, or perhaps at stopping a small group of
				members of a company from arranging for a performance not acceptable to the company
				as a whole. 271</p>
				<p>It is only in the 1540s, however, that we find a clustering– though a small one–of hall
				rentals to players. The Founders accounts include receipts at least two and perhaps three to
				four times, between October 1543 and October 1540, from players for playing in the hall.
				(Twice players are specified, with Ss 4d noted in one receipt and IOs in the other, and twice
				playing(s), one at 6s and the other combined with receipts from hall weddings and from
				the Waterbearers feast.) The Founders also note receipt of 16d, in 1546–7, for a play in the
				hall: this seems meagre for a rental and might instead be a sum collected towards a play
				performance for the company itself, but there is no payment out to players.22 (Similarly the
				Armourers record Iad received, in ]une 1537–]une 1535, for a play in their hall.2) The
				Weavers, like the Founders, record a receipt from players for playing in the hall (6s), in theii
				case some time between August 1545 and August 1547. Other records of hall entertainment
				rentals also appear in company accounts in the 1540s: the Weavers rent to an individual for
				playng, sometime between August 1543 and August 1544, the Founders to a gentleman for
				making pastyme during the Christmas season 1544–5, and the Pewterers, in apparently six
				years between September 1540 and September 1552, to the Spanish proprietor of a dancing
				School. The Barber–Surgeons in March 1556 issued an order against rentals– which had
				been damaging the hall– for bridal parties, dinners, sports, games, and dancing, unless with
				the consent of the whole company.274</p>
				<p>The restrictions on company hall rentals in the proclamations of 1544–6, together with
				the limited extent of the extant records of hall entertainment rentals in the 1540s, prevents
				any reliable speculation that playing companies at this time turned to renting company halls
				to any significant extent. But only in the 1540s and early 1550s do the civic records yield any
				such cluster of entertainment rentals, however small: and general hall rentals (for example
				for the dinners of other companies without their own halls) had always been a valuable
				income source for some companies. Companies, especially those below the level of the
				wealthiest, certainly had an incentive to rent their halls as much as possible at this time,
				although the political situation in relation to players was also a disincentive. As previously
				noted in relation to the Midsummer Watch, in both the 1540s and 1550s the companies were
				being financially hard–pressed to an unusual extent. 275</p>
				<p>The April 1542 ban on common plays and interludes in company halls might lie, at least in
				part, behind the ending, after 1541, of the Drapers feast–time play tradition (or at least of the
				recording of it), stretching back to the early fifteenth century–although performances in
				company halls for the companies themselves were legitimized again in the royal proclama*
				tions of 1544–6. The Blacksmiths recording of their by–now£biennial cony feast (tradition
				ally with a play) also briefly moved, for 1543, 1545, and 1547, out of the company&apos;s main
				accounts, although it then returned in 1540, 1551, and 1555. Plays were banned again in
				both August 1553 and, in association with May games, in April/ May 1554. Cost–cuttings
				uncertainties, and new funding or accounting mechanisms, however, may have been entirely
				responsible for the ending of the Drapers play records and the fluctuations in the Blacksmiths,
				or may have been factors as strong as, or stronger than, specific bans or restrictions on plays.
				The yeomanry of the Tallow Chandlers, for example, continued to pay players throughout
				the 1540s. The main Tallow Chandlers Company paid players in ]une/August 1553 and in
				1550. The Weavers paid players in the Christmas season of 1552–3. The best we can say
				is that the unsettled period from 1540 to 1558 (during which the Midsummer Watch also
				ended), which led on into the 1560s, when we begin to find records of playhouse building in
				London, seems to have been a time of transition for London–centred acting troupes: including
				transitions in at least some of their relationships with the London companies which had
				traditionally, either occasionally or regularly, employed them. 276</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>Music</head>
				<p>Music was everywhere in preElizabethan London: an important part of royal entries, various
				other kinds of formal processions, the Midsummer Watch, mayings, company feast times
				and other occasions both formal and informal. References to music in general, to spe
				cific kinds of music, and to individual musicians are found throughout the civic records.
				Three specific musical groups and one other kind of London music should, however, be
				briefly noted.</p>
				<div>
					<head>THE PUY</head>
				<p>The city&apos;s earliest musical records are the articles of the London puy –a late–thirteenth–century
				socialsreligious society, like other puys at this time in France, devoted to the Virgin Mary and
				to music performed and composed in her honour. Although some puys were involved in
				theatrical as well as musical performances, there is no indication that this was the case with
				the London puy. Members would have been from the city&apos;s wealthy mercantile elite (and
				perhaps would even have included royalty): and the articles refer to one purpose of the puy
				as being to bring renown to London. The puy&apos;s articles are found not in the Letter Books
				but in a custumal, the Liber Custumarum (initially compiled c 1324), and so are cited in
				Appendix I (under e 1270–Early IAth Century). A detailed study of puys in general and of
				the London puy in particular was published in 1002 by Anne Sutton: and the London puy
				is also placed within the context of London music and theatre in Loz. The London puy does
				not seem to have survived beyond the early fourteenth century, and little is known about its
				musical activities beyond the information in its articles. Its existence shows, however, an
				early focus of London&apos;s civic elite on an international form of musical culture and on its
				importance to the city&apos;s reputation.</p></div>
				<div>
					<head>THE WA1TS</head>
				<p>Originally (in the thirteenth century) city watchmen who carried with them on their rounds
				loud instruments such as shawms or horns, city waits gradually developed into salaried
				musicians employed by the city to play on established formal occasions both religious and
				secular. Routinely, for example, they would go in civic processions with the mayor and other
				city officers, playing their instruments. The earliest London civic record of a wait is perhaps
				a 1287 note in Letter Book A of a woyte: but this may be a record simply of a watchman.2s By
				November 1442, however, the city&apos;s waits (then numbering nine) were sufficiently established
				that they successfully petitioned to be allowed a city livery. 2/ In February 1453/4, they were
				to walk around with their minstrels each night for the people&apos;s enjoyment as well as to
				prevent robberies. This record associates them with music beyond sounding the watch
				although apparently they were not playing it themselves, at least at this particular time, unless
				some of the waits served as watchmen while others played music. By at least 1455 they were
				receiving additional paid employment, presumably for playing, from the Merchant Taylors
				Company at its ]une feast time. 280</p>
				<p>Civic records of the waits, in relation to secular music, largely involve their participation
				in mayoral and shrieval processions, royal entries, and the Midsummer Watch, and thei૱
				employment also by some of the London companies to play at company feast times.2 The
				feast₯time music might involve religious ceremonies, secular occasions, or both: and or
				the secular side it could be limited to music at the presentation of new company officers or
				could be more extensive. The civic manuscripts also include records of the waits petitions,
				admissions, and illnesses, the special city collars they wore, the purchase for them of musical
				instruments, and their responsibility to attend at the houses of the mayor and the sheriffs
				at certain times of the year, such as Christmas. From c 1475 to 1558 their standard numbei
				appears to have been six૱૱€ and from April 1502, at their petitioning of the city, they were
				approved to become members, without paying a fee, of the city&apos;s Minstrels Company
				which was insisting that the waits– city employees – lacked professional[civic rights with
				out Minstrels Company membership.2s Twice in the first half of the sixteenth century
				the city agreed to increase their wages. The first time was in April 1524, after the annual
				church dedication days, which had provided the waits with numerous additional paid
				employment opportunities spread throughout the year, had been moved in 1523 onto a
				single day.2: The second time was in September and October 1536, when a number of
				annual holy days, on which the waits also previously had received some additional paid
				employment, had been abrogated.2s Earlier, in 1515 (and for the next nine years), they
				had received additional wages from a bequest by mercer [ohn Tate, mayor 1406–7 and ]une to
				October 1514.26 Their musical range seems gradually to have expanded,2 but they continued
				to have watch duties: in 1553 a city order controlling minstrels specifies that its forbidding of
				the playing of instruments in the streets between IO PM and S AM does not apply to the waits
				in pleying or in keping their accustomed watch at the usual hours. 288</p>
				<p>The waits are probably also included, within the general term minstrel, in other early
				civic records, in all of Latin, Anglo–French, and English, but they can normally now be
				identified as waits only when that specific term is used or the context makes the identification
				clear. In 1455–6, for example, ]ohn Wikes is clearly a wait from the record concerned, but
				is called not a wait but a minstrel.2s</p></div></div>
				<div>
					<head>THE MINSTRELS COMPANY</head>
				<p>In 1350 the minstrels of London established a guild: their ordinances have survived as part of
				a return made in 1388 to an inquiry by Richard II into the activities of guilds in general.
				Nothing more is then heard of the guild, however, until 1500, when, as a guild[company,
				the city&apos;s minstrels petitioned common council in relation to competition from non–citizen
				minstrels and received the council&apos;s support of their proposed new ordinances.2 The city
				waits–who were city employees– then complained to common council about having to
				become members of the Minstrels Company, and were granted free admission to it. A Ring€
				Minstrels guild had existed since at least 1468 (and had its charter confirmed by Henry V111
				in 1520), and all minstrels in the kingdom (except in the county of Chester) supposedly had
				to be members in order to practise their profession€૱ but this evidently had not stopped the
				London minstrels from (re)forming their own company, which did not include (by their own
				1500 ordinances) royal minstrels, or minstrels of any lord of the parliament, unless permanently
				resident in the city. ]ohn Chambre, marshal of the king&apos;s Minstrels, joined the city company
				in 1510 and later served as a company warden. 293</p>
				<p>In January 1517/18 the company brought forward new ordinances, and again in 1552,
				the latter perhaps leading to the city&apos;s move in March 1552/3 to control both foreign (that
				is, non–citizen) minstrels and the members also of the Minstrels Company. 2/ Foreign
				minstrels, for example, were not to play in any common hall, tavern, or like location, and
				no minstrel was to teach dancing. In March 1554/5 all minstrels were barred from singing
				and playing in taverns, alehouses, and the like. The Minstrels Company apparently pro–
				tested, but in vain. 295</p>
				<p>Various other miscellaneous civic records involving the Minstrels Company have also
				survived. The company, for example, swore its acceptance of the Act of Succession in April
				1534. 2/ Its participation in formal entries into the city is specified in October 1540 (a passage
				by Edward vi through the city) and in August 1553 (Mary&apos;s accession entry).2/ The company
				is included in 1540 in a list of companies to provide cressets for the Midsummer Watch.
				Some entrances of individuals into the company are recorded. In 1547 the company complained
				that the Weavers were admitting minstrels into their company. The problem was resolved by
				the translation of two minstrels from the Weavers to the Minstrels. 299</p>
				<p>Richard Crewdson in his history of the company notes the major areas in the city where
				city musicians seem to have lived in the sixteenth and early seventeenth centuries, the largest
				number being in the parish of St Giles Cripplegate: but he does not break down the numbers
				more specifically by date, 80c</p>
				</div>
				<div><head>ROUGH MUSIC</head>				
				<p>Loud and discordant rough music, involving trumpets, pipes, and[or the banging of pots
				and pans, was often specified as to be used in a form of punishment involving the parading
				through the city streets to the pillory and, in many cases, eventually to a gate for expulsion
				from the city of those convicted of crimes such as prostitution and bawdry. The earliest such
				record in the civic manuscripts is from 1364–55 and records continue to appear in the Letter
				Books, [ournals, and Repertories, sporadically and sometimes in clusters, in a number of
				instances before 1470 and in all decades from the 1470s right up to 1558.21 There are many
				judgments against bawds, prostitutes, charlatans, and the like, in the city&apos;s records, which do
				not specify music, and it is unclear from the records of specific punishments as to whether
				music was usual, although only sometimes mentioned, or was used in particular cases only:
				but regulations indicating its use as general are extant from 1381–2 and from 1438–0, and
				the latter, which refer back to the previous regulations, are still being cited in the sixteenth
				century.€¢€ Such music called special attention to the parading of the convicted individuals to
				the pillory and[or out of the city, both as part of the shaming processes involved and as an
				aid to the citizens clear identifying of the individuals concerned (the judgments sometimes
				specified that the individuals must not return to London, and offered a reward to anyone
				subsequently finding them in the city and turning them in to the authorities). The vile
				Mynstralcy, as one record calls it, was a key part of the criminal procession as an inversion
				of the city&apos;s formal religious and secular processions of worship and of celebration.
			</p>
			</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
