<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>CivicLondon_HistoricalBackground</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l1' n='N001'/>Historical Background
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l2' n='N002'/>Only some twenty–five years ago, with the discovery and initial excavations in 1087–8 of a
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l3' n='N003'/>Roman amphitheatre under what is today the citys Guildhall Tard, London was shown to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l4' n='N004'/>have been a city with significant public, civic–sponsored entertainments from very close to its
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l5' n='N005'/>founding by the Romans c 50–2 AD. In the amphitheatres of the Roman Empire, city mag*
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l6' n='N006'/>istrates routinely provided entertainments on public festive occasions: and Roman Londons
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l7' n='N007'/>amphitheatre, first built of timber in 70–I aD and then dismantled and rebuilt partly in stone
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l8' n='N008'/>in the early second century, would probably have been the site of public wild–animal shows,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l9' n='N009'/>gladiatorial contests, athletic competitions, and military drills and exhibitions. (By c 120–5 AD
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l10' n='N010'/>London&apos;s Roman military fort was nearby, to the northwest.:) Doubtless the amphitheatre
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l11' n='N011'/>most recently estimated to have held, at first, around 6, 9O0 spectators, and around 7, O00 to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l12' n='N012'/>10, S00 after the structure was rebuilt– hosted other public entertainments as well, such as
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l13' n='N013'/>mime (variety entertainment) and pantomime (dance drama), if Roman London did not also
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l14' n='N014'/>have a separate theatre.S Music would have been part of some of these entertainments. It
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l15' n='N015'/>would have been unusual for a Roman centre as large and important as Londinium not to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l16' n='N016'/>have had a theatre as well as an amphitheatre, or perhaps an odeon, but no theatrical structure
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l17' n='N017'/>other than the amphitheatre has been found by archaeologists to date. Also missing today is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l18' n='N018'/>any evidence of the mock naval battles (naumachia) which the Romans enjoyed watching in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l19' n='N019'/>other parts of the Empire and for which the Thames at London would have been a convenient
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l20' n='N020'/>site. Roman London was, however, a flourishing city: one of the major cities of the western
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l21' n='N021'/>Roman Empire (recently estimated to have had perhaps ten thousand inhabitants by 60 AD
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l22' n='N022'/>and up to thirty thousand inhabitants by the early second century), an important trading
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l23' n='N023'/>port, and the centre of Roman roads leading out to other parts of Britain.: It prospered unti
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l24' n='N024'/>the third century, and we are probably safe in speculating that types of public and private
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l25' n='N025'/>entertainment common in other western parts of the Empire, both musical and theatrical
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l26' n='N026'/>would have normally been available in Londonium as well. S
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l27' n='N027'/>No written evidence of theatrical activities in Roman London, or for over seven hundred years
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l28' n='N028'/>after the Romans left Britain in A10 AD, has come down to us today. Roman London seems to
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l29' n='N029'/>have been abandoned by probably the early fifth century, and the Saxon town of Lundenwic
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l30' n='N030'/>was built in the late seventh century just upstream from what had been the walled Roman
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l31' n='N031'/>city (although the first St Paul&apos;s cathedral church was founded, c 604, within the old walls,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l32' n='N032'/>and a royal palace may have been built there as well). From this period on, through London&apos;s
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l1' n='N001'/>HISTORICAL BACkGROUND
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l2' n='N002'/>xi1
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l3' n='N003'/>late–ninth–century re–establishment within the walls by king Alfred,s until the late twelfth
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l4' n='N004'/>century, we have no material remains or written records indicating anything about theatrical
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l5' n='N005'/>entertainment specifically in London: and we also do not know about city governance in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l6' n='N006'/>much particularity, although a history of the city can be pieced together from a variety of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l7' n='N007'/>sources, such as early chronicles, charters, and other legal documents.* It is inconceivable,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l8' n='N008'/>however, that Lundenwic and then London – a centre of national and international trade in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l9' n='N009'/>the late seventh and early eighth centuries, and a flourishing and wealthy international port
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l10' n='N010'/>and economic centre at the time of the 1066 Norman Conquest€¢– would have been without
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l11' n='N011'/>a variety of entertainments and music: indeed that musical activity would have continued in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l12' n='N012'/>early London, at this time, has not been questioned. All we know about theatrical performance
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l13' n='N013'/>in London for this period, however, are generalities: the persistence, in societies throughout
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l14' n='N014'/>human history, of a love of performance entertainment in general: the persistence also of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l15' n='N015'/>entertainers in their profession: the normal continuity therefore of performance traditions
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l16' n='N016'/>from one generation to the next: the survival, after the Romans, of a knowledge of their
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l17' n='N017'/>drama through the reading of classical texts among the educated classes: a few surviving
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l18' n='N018'/>Christian ecclesiastical records of hostility towards ludi (games/plays) and spectaculi in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l19' n='N019'/>Britain generally৳ and an Old English and Latin working vocabulary including words for
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l20' n='N020'/>amphitheatre, theatre, and actors. Christian drama also, as it developed in the tenth to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l21' n='N021'/>twelfth centuries, was demonstrably being performed elsewhere in England (for example, in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l22' n='N022'/>Winchester from the tenth century), and so is unlikely not to have existed as well in populous
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l23' n='N023'/>and wealthy London (now back within its walls), with its bishopric of St Paul&apos;s, numerous
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l24' n='N024'/>churches (many founded in the eleventh century), and many religious houses.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l25' n='N025'/>By the later twelfth century, we have texts extant of sophisticated religious plays which
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l26' n='N026'/>though without any specific London connection, show the highly developed state of the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l27' n='N027'/>Christian drama at this time in various parts of Europe, including England and France./ A
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l28' n='N028'/>secular Latin comedy, B$₽€¢, is also extant, possibly a court piece (to be performed or read)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l29' n='N029'/>by author/scholar Walter Map, whose patron was Henry 11: but whoever the audience or the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l30' n='N030'/>readership was for B$₽€¢, the work is unlikely to have been unique, and plays for the court
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l31' n='N031'/>and for a London mercantile audience would probably not have differed, given the wealth
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l32' n='N032'/>and sophistication of London&apos;s civic leaders and their interactions with royalty and nobility.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l33' n='N033'/>Towards the end of the twelfth century comes our first written evidence of theatrical
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l34' n='N034'/>activity specifically in London. Some time between c 1170 and 1182, William fitz Stephen,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l35' n='N035'/>the London–born, church–educated secretary to Thomas Becket (before Becket&apos;s murder in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l36' n='N036'/>1170), wrote his now famous Descriptio Londoniae (Description of London), in which
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l37' n='N037'/>he seems to refer to a thriving religious theatre – as well as other forms of entertainment
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l38' n='N038'/>in the city৳ and c 1103, Winchester monk Richard of Devizes wrote in his Chronicle about
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l39' n='N039'/>city secular entertainments. 5 Fitz Stephen, comparing London favourably with ancient Rome,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l40' n='N040'/>writes of London&apos;s holier plays, on miracles by holy confessors or the sufferings of martyrs,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l41' n='N041'/>and even if these (as some historians have suggested) might not have been plays in the modern
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l42' n='N042'/>sense of the word, fitz Stephen certainly seems to be writing about something theatrical and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l43' n='N043'/>significant. He does not mention sponsorship: but such plays seem unlikely to have been
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l44' n='N044'/>performed by small, independent acting troupes, and could have been organized by one or
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l45' n='N045'/>more religious institutions or by the city. He also mentions cockfighting, dancing, wrestling,
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l1' n='N001'/>HISTORICAL BACkGROUND
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l2' n='N002'/>xiii
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l3' n='N003'/>boar–fighting, bull and bear baiting, and other sports and games.S The material in Richard
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l4' n='N004'/>of Devizes Chronicle is also significant. In a story about a smooth–talking villain attempting
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l5' n='N005'/>to lure a young man to his death, Richard puts into the villain&apos;s mouth warnings about
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l6' n='N006'/>the iniquities of London, which include the theatrum, along with dice, gambling, and the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l7' n='N007'/>tavern, and evildoers, such as jesters, dancers, quacks, magicians, pimps, sorceresses, mimes,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l8' n='N008'/>and histriones (actors/entertainers).1 The sinful city was a common trope in medieval liter*
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l9' n='N009'/>ature: and the villain in the Chronicle is attempting to mislead the young man into going to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l10' n='N010'/>Winchester (where he will subsequently be murdered). Nevertheless, the list of locations and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l11' n='N011'/>activities (on a factual basis rather than in terms of the moral slant of the narrative) presumably
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l12' n='N012'/>had some recognizable contemporary applicability to London as a place where one could find
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l13' n='N013'/>various kinds of (non–religious) entertainment. Richard of Devizes entertainers certainly
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l14' n='N014'/>were not city–sponsored: but unless his description of activities in London is to be taken as
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l15' n='N015'/>purely literary, the performers listed would seem to be signs of a thriving secular entertain*
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l16' n='N016'/>ment business in the late–twelfth–century city, as we might expect given the size, wealth, and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l17' n='N017'/>prominence of London under Richard I (1185–00) and then ]ohn (1155–1216).2
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l18' n='N018'/>Twelfth–century London was indeed a thriving and international mercantile centre, ideally
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l19' n='N019'/>situated on the Thames at a strategic point that could be reached by ocean–going vessels and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l20' n='N020'/>yet where a bridge could also be constructed across the river, with roads running from the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l21' n='N021'/>city both north and south, making London the hub of the country&apos;s trading and travelling
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l22' n='N022'/>networks. It was the largest and richest city in Britain,2 and its importance continued to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l23' n='N023'/>grow throughout the medieval and early Tudor periods, despite a significant population
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l24' n='N024'/>reduction at the time of the Black Death.2 Although the monarchy was peripatetic, moving
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l25' n='N025'/>around the country as it suited each monarch, the wealth, the location, the abundance of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l26' n='N026'/>goods both local and international, and the general stability of London served as a magnet foi
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l27' n='N027'/>royalty, the nobility, and the upper echelons of the clergy. A number of religious institutions
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l28' n='N028'/>were founded in and around the city during the twelfth century₮€৳ Wealthy aristocrats and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l29' n='N029'/>ecclesiastics began by c 1200 to build imposing townhouses in and close to the city, as bases
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l30' n='N030'/>for carrying out business there, and the palace at Westminster was a royal favourite.2 By
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l31' n='N031'/>the late twelfth century, the Exchequer had become established at Westminster. By the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l32' n='N032'/>mid–fourteenth century, most of the other administrative functions of the Crown had become
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l33' n='N033'/>located there as well, where the parliament also regularly met, while the Great Wardrobe,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l34' n='N034'/>a major provisions department for the court, had been established in London itself.25 Cirty
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l35' n='N035'/>and court, involved in a relationship of mutual self–interest from very early times, became
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l36' n='N036'/>increasingly dependent upon one another. The city was a source of money, of manpower,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l37' n='N037'/>and of goods for the Crown: the Crown was expected by the city to maintain the political
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l38' n='N038'/>stability necessary for its mercantile activities to flourish. London&apos;s support was essential if
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l39' n='N039'/>a monarch was to gain or to retain power: but the favour of the monarch was also essential
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l40' n='N040'/>to London&apos;s economy both nationally and internationally. This interdependence of court
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l41' n='N041'/>and city was cultural as well as economic and political, extending throughout the period
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l42' n='N042'/>(1287 to 1558) covered by the records in this collection.2
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l43' n='N043'/>London&apos;s privileges of self–government existed, at least in part, from very early times.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l44' n='N044'/>From apparently the end of the twelfth century, London was given the right by the Crown to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l45' n='N045'/>elect its own mayor annually, although this privilege was not formally set down until king
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l1' n='N001'/>HISTORICAL BACkGROUND
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l2' n='N002'/>xiv
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l3' n='N003'/>]ohn&apos;s 9 May 1215 charter to the city. The chosen individual was, however, required to
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l4' n='N004'/>swear an oath to the Crown, and from time to time, until the fifteenth century, the king
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l5' n='N005'/>intervened strongly in the election process or even sometimes took the city into his hand
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l6' n='N006'/>that is, took it under his direct governance via an appointed warden, in place of the mayor,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l7' n='N007'/>when he became displeased with the conduct of the current mayor or of the city government
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l8' n='N008'/>in general.2 By the fifteenth century, the king still exercised considerable influence over
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l9' n='N009'/>the election, but diplomatic pressures – although sometimes considerable– had replaced
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l10' n='N010'/>direct interventions. London also, by 1150–1, chose for itself two sheriffs annually (althougk
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l11' n='N011'/>the shrievalty had existed for more than a hundred years before that).2 The sheriffs were
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l12' n='N012'/>answerable to the kings Exchequer barons, and normally served for only one term,8 whereas
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l13' n='N013'/>the mayor until 1380 might be re–elected for several consecutive years and subsequently
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l14' n='N014'/>between 1380 and 1424–35, might serve for more than two non–consecutive terms. 21
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l15' n='N015'/>Gradually, over the years, the shrievalty became less important than the mayoralty, and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l16' n='N016'/>in 1385 the citys common council decreed that the office of sheriff was a necessary step
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l17' n='N017'/>before an individual could reach the mayoralty.€ The city jealously guarded its rights in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l18' n='N018'/>relation to the mayoral and shrieval elections, and political changes over the decades and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l19' n='N019'/>centuries led to increasingly greater freedom from royal interference. The processions
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l20' n='N020'/>of the sheriffs and mayor annually to Westminster, however, to be confirmed in office by
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l21' n='N021'/>the king or by his Exchequer barons, remained throughout this period (that is, to 1558)
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l22' n='N022'/>important ceremonial occasions involving music and, eventually for the mayor&apos;s proces
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l23' n='N023'/>sion, pageant display.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l24' n='N024'/>Under the sheriffs and, by the late twelfth century, the mayor with their various officers
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l25' n='N025'/>London was divided for governing purposes into wards (around twenty–four by at least
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l26' n='N026'/>the early twelfth century), each headed by an alderman (a fairly full list is extant from
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l27' n='N027'/>c 1127) / The aldermen, who held office for life throughout most of the twelfth to sixteenth
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l28' n='N028'/>centuries, had judicial responsibilities in their wards, were responsible for keeping order in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l29' n='N029'/>times of crisis, put civic regulations into effect, collected taxes, presided at the wardmote
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l30' n='N030'/>and kept ward records.5 As the court of Aldermen, they met about once a week in the early
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l31' n='N031'/>fifteenth century and about three times a week by the mid–fifteenth century.s London also
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l32' n='N032'/>had, from at least the fourteenth century, a common council (in part the successor of the city&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l33' n='N033'/>original folkmoot) composed of representatives of the wards and responsible for taxation
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l34' n='N034'/>decisions, often taxation assessments and audits, negotiations with the Crown, civic projects
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l35' n='N035'/>requiring expenditures, disputes between craft/trade guilds, and regulations concerning the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l36' n='N036'/>city&apos;s freedom (citizenship)./ The aldermen and the common council cooperated in admin*
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l37' n='N037'/>istration, and formed joint committees on a number of significant matters (finances, repairs,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l38' n='N038'/>etc). 88 Both the aldermen and the common council were involved with civic activities and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l39' n='N039'/>decisions in relation to musical and theatrical matters. Various city officers involved with
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l40' n='N040'/>these activities also appear regularly in the civic manuscripts before 1558 – especially, in the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l41' n='N041'/>records transcribed, the chamberlain, common clerk, and recorder. The chamberlain was the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l42' n='N042'/>city&apos;s chief financial officer, whose office dealt with city income and expenditures. The
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l43' n='N043'/>common clerk gradually became responsible for the creation and safekeeping of city records
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l44' n='N044'/>The recorder, who had primarily legal responsibilities, also made formal public speeches of
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l1' n='N001'/>HISTORICAL BACkGROUND
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l2' n='N002'/>xv
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l3' n='N003'/>welcome to visiting dignitaries, including those who were accorded a pageantic entry through
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l4' n='N004'/>the city.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l5' n='N005'/>In part in return for its considerable political independence, the city served as a cash cow
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l6' n='N006'/>for the monarchy, frequently taxed to fund royal activities such as wars abroad, and obliged
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l7' n='N007'/>to provide loans to the king. It was also expected not only to maintain defensive capabilities
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l8' n='N008'/>in case of need at home but also at times to provide actual manpower for foreign wars.1o
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l9' n='N009'/>With Westminster as the favoured seat of the monarchy, London was also often called upon
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l10' n='N010'/>to offer a formal welcome, as well as sometimes lodgings and feasts, and often gifts, to royal
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l11' n='N011'/>and other important visitors (for example, ambassadors, papal emissaries) to the court from
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l12' n='N012'/>abroad. It was also expected to escort English monarchs themselves, and sometimes members
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l13' n='N013'/>of the royal family, on formal passages through the city, going to or from Westminster. Foreigr
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l14' n='N014'/>monarchs of considerable importance would be accorded especially elaborate welcomes. Also
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l15' n='N015'/>since coronations of English monarchs from the late eleventh century regularly took place
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l16' n='N016'/>at Westminster Abbey, London was as well the standard site for the formal pre–coronation
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l17' n='N017'/>procession, from the Tower of London through the city to Westminster, which was requirec
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l18' n='N018'/>of the monarch from at least the time of Richard Il: the king was to show himself bare₯headed
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l19' n='N019'/>to his subjects on the day before his coronation. (Both Edward I and Edward II are also known
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l20' n='N020'/>to have made a pre–coronation procession through the city, but no document requiring this
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l21' n='N021'/>has survived for those early years, and the recording chronicles do not specifically mention
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l22' n='N022'/>the Tower as a starting point.8) Cueen consorts, when crowned later than the king, also made
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l23' n='N023'/>a pre–coronation procession through London, the earliest described seemingly being that
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l24' n='N024'/>of Eleanor of Provence in 1236. From at least the late fifteenth century there were standard
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l25' n='N025'/>requirements set down for this kind of procession as well (including the Tower to Westminster
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l26' n='N026'/>route), which likely date back to at least 1445.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l27' n='N027'/>All of this ceremonial activity required from the city established procedures of welcoming
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l28' n='N028'/>and of escorting, and often considerable expenditure. Coronation and other such major
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l29' n='N029'/>entries had particularly elaborate and highly expensive requirements, including constructed
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l30' n='N030'/>and[or role–playing pageants: and these entries were sometimes well spaced out, but at other
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l31' n='N031'/>times clustered together. Three coronations, for example, took place, with elaborate entries
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l32' n='N032'/>in the twelve years between February 1546/7 and [anuary 1558/98, along with a similarly
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l33' n='N033'/>elaborate royal welcome– for Philip of Spain, the new husband of Oueen Mary– in 1554.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l34' n='N034'/>Far more than any other city or town in England, London was called upon to spend atten*
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l35' n='N035'/>tion, time, and very large sums of money, with comparative frequency, on a full range of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l36' n='N036'/>welcoming/honouring occasions – although these occasions, of course, not only honoured
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l37' n='N037'/>those being welcomed, escorted, or celebrated, but also were a demonstration of the city&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l38' n='N038'/>wealth, power, and importance to the Crown. London&apos;s nearness to Westminster was both a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l39' n='N039'/>source of wealth and independence (through privileges granted by the Crown, through the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l40' n='N040'/>purchasing activities of all of the Crown, the aristocracy, and the upper levels of ecclesiastics,
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l41' n='N041'/>and through the city&apos;s demonstration of its power) and a drain on wealth and independence, and
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l42' n='N042'/>turned the formal receiving of royal and other important personages into an ongoing activity
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l43' n='N043'/>such as existed nowhere else in England. London probably thus also became a centre, from
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l44' n='N044'/>very early times, for those who could provide, for the higher level of entries, the components
			</p>
			<pb n='6'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l1' n='N001'/>HISTORICAL BACkGROUND
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l2' n='N002'/>xvi
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l3' n='N003'/>of these kinds of significant musical and theatrical occasions. Meanwhile the fondness of the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l4' n='N004'/>court for its own musical and theatrical entertainments, and the close relationships between
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l5' n='N005'/>the city elite and the court, also made inevitable the existence from very early times of a
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l6' n='N006'/>flourishing indoor musical and theatrical culture in the great halls of civic London. ]ohn
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l7' n='N007'/>Lydgate, for example, was commissioned in 1425–30 both by the court and by at least two
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l8' n='N008'/>city guilds/companies (for which, see below) to produce special hall entertainments for the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l9' n='N009'/>fall, winter, and spring of the year of Henry vi&apos;s English coronation, which took place in
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l10' n='N010'/>November 1420.2
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l11' n='N011'/>For London&apos;s civic musical and theatrical activities before 1300, we are largely dependent
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l12' n='N012'/>on sources other than civic records (see Appendix I), but in 1275/6 the city began its first
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l13' n='N013'/>ongoing series of written records of city business, the Letter Books, which are extant today.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l14' n='N014'/>Beginning largely as registers of bonds and recognizances,88 they soon became the essential
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l15' n='N015'/>record of the business of the city, as conducted by its mayor, aldermen, and common council,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l16' n='N016'/>with important external documents (such as orders from the king) also copied in. The earliest
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l17' n='N017'/>Letter Books, A through C, have yielded only one record for this edition, but from Letter
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l18' n='N018'/>Book D on (that is, beginning c 1300), relevant records gradually increase, although largely
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l19' n='N019'/>from the late fourteenth century into the fifteenth. In 1416 a second manuscript series was
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l20' n='N020'/>begun, the [ournals, for the recording specifically of the business conducted by the common
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l21' n='N021'/>council and the court of Aldermen. In 1405 the business of the aldermen was split off into
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l22' n='N022'/>yet a third series of manuscripts, the Repertories. Significant items from the [ournals, from
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l23' n='N023'/>1416, and from the Repertories, from 1405, were copied into the Letter Books. For music
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l24' n='N024'/>and theatre historians today, therefore, as the fifteenth century moves along, the Letter Books
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l25' n='N025'/>gradually become less important than the ]ournals and the Repertories as original sources of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l26' n='N026'/>information. Unfortunately no chamberlain&apos;s accounts, which would have been a major source
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l27' n='N027'/>of information on all city activities and occasions involving receipts and expenditures, have
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l28' n='N028'/>survived for London before the late sixteenth century, other than a few summaries copied
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l29' n='N029'/>into the Letter Books in the 1330s and 1340s, and one subsidiary account, for 1535–6,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l30' n='N030'/>kept by a chamberlain&apos;s clerk.*
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l31' n='N031'/>In addition to the Letter Books, [ournals, and Repertories, as early civic series of manu*
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l32' n='N032'/>scripts with information on London&apos;s musical and theatrical activities, are two partially
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l33' n='N033'/>extant accounts series belonging to London Bridge, which was run by the city as a separate
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l34' n='N034'/>enterprise (essentially a trust). The Bridge House, headed by two elected wardens (or
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l35' n='N035'/>bridgemasters), was mandated in part to generate income for Bridge maintenance, the key
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l36' n='N036'/>components of which were tolls and the rentals of Bridge properties both on the Bridge
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l37' n='N037'/>itself and elsewhere in the city.* The annual accounts of the bridgemasters are partially
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l38' n='N038'/>extant for 1381–1405 (17 rolls) and 1404–60 (only one rental, and weekly receipts), and
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l39' n='N039'/>extant in full from 1460 to the end date of this collection: and their detailed series of weekly
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l40' n='N040'/>payments are extant, up to 1558, for 1404–45, 1505–38, and 1552–5. These records are
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l41' n='N041'/>important for historians of London theatre and music because, almost invariably before the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l42' n='N042'/>last part of the fifteenth century, and occasionally after, major entries into the city involved a
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l43' n='N043'/>ceremonial crossing of London Bridge, with music and pageantry paid for by the Bridge
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l44' n='N044'/>itself. In some years in the fifteenth century, detailed costs are included in the extant Bridge
			</p>
			<pb n='7'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l1' n='N001'/>HISTORICAL BACkGROUND
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l2' n='N002'/>xvii
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l3' n='N003'/>House manuscript accounts.* No such payment records have survived – although they must
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l4' n='N004'/>have originally existed– for pageants provided within the city directly by the civic govern*
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l5' n='N005'/>ment.৳ The only records, for example, of constructed pageantry for the 1465 coronation
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l6' n='N006'/>entry of Elizabeth Woodville, queen to Edward Iv, come from the Bridge House manu
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l7' n='N007'/>scripts, which provide details of the Bridges expenditures on displays and music.2 Edward
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l8' n='N008'/>1v&apos;s marriage was not popular, either at the court or outside it, so possibly there was major
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l9' n='N009'/>display only at the Bridge: but more likely the pageantry was more extensive and chroniclers
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l10' n='N010'/>our main source of information today on early royal entries– simply did not report on
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l11' n='N011'/>the entry because of the absence either of popular interest or of royal pressure. (In 1533
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l12' n='N012'/>when the unpopular Anne Boleyn made her coronation entry through London, pressure
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l13' n='N013'/>from Henry viIi led not only to elaborate displays but also probably to the lengthy chronicle
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l14' n='N014'/>descriptions of them which we now have. 5) The civic rulers spent a considerable amount
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l15' n='N015'/>of money in 1465 on the decorating of the city, but we have no information on what that
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l16' n='N016'/>involved.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l17' n='N017'/>After 1465 the Bridge House manuscripts tell us little about Bridge pageants and music:
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l18' n='N018'/>but after 1483 the Bridge House becomes, in any case, a much less important potentia
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l19' n='N019'/>source of pageant information than before. From 1483, coronation entries through London
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l20' n='N020'/>increasingly came to involve a water procession to the Tower of London– the starting point
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l21' n='N021'/>for the mandated pre–coronation procession through the heart of the city– rather than a land
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l22' n='N022'/>procession from Southwark across the Bridge. Richard IIl, perhaps for reasons of security, went
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l23' n='N023'/>to the Tower before his coronation by water, and although Henry vil crossed the Bridge, his
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l24' n='N024'/>consort, Elizabeth of Tork, went to the Tower by barge, with pageantry on the water– for
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l25' n='N025'/>example, a fire–spouting dragon– instead of the traditional Bridge pageantry. Henry VIII, for
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l26' n='N026'/>his coronation entry in 1500, crossed the Bridge, but all subsequent sixteenth–century
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l27' n='N027'/>coronation entrants, except Edward vi, went to the Tower by water. Edward did not process
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l28' n='N028'/>to the Tower by land or by water: he had remained in the Tower, after his accession, until
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l29' n='N029'/>his entry through the city the day before his coronation. One–day non–coronation entries
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l30' n='N030'/>in 1501 by Ratherine of Aragon, coming to marry Prince Arthur (heir to the English throne),
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l31' n='N031'/>and in 1522 by the visiting emperor Charles V– continued to use the Bridge, but after
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l32' n='N032'/>1522 no such major non–coronation entries took place for the rest of the sixteenth century.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l33' n='N033'/>Unfortunately, even where detailed Bridge House records are extant for the years of the few
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l34' n='N034'/>major royal entries using the Bridge after 1465, they no longer provide detailed information
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l35' n='N035'/>on Bridge pageants. Chronicle histories become our main information source.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l36' n='N036'/>London&apos;s city government– of the mayor, sheriffs, aldermen from the wards, and common
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l37' n='N037'/>council– was considerably dependent on two other forms of local government in carrying
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l38' n='N038'/>out its civic functions. One of these was religious government: the territory, in part, of REEDS
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l39' n='N039'/>E₯₯₮£৳€$৳૱€₯$₮ L¢₭₨¢₭ collection, which deals with the surviving records of the city&apos;s parishes,
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l40' n='N040'/>St Paul&apos;s Cathedral, and the diocese of London. The other was the internal government and
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l41' n='N041'/>authority of each of the various London craft or trade guilds, organizations whose extant
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l42' n='N042'/>records of pre–1550 music and theatre, some from as early as the fourteenth century, are a
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l43' n='N043'/>major part of this collection. These guilds were originally formed by particular occupational
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l44' n='N044'/>groups (for example, bakers, goldsmiths, pewterers, saddlers) for purposes of crast or trade
			</p>
			<pb n='8'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l1' n='N001'/>HISTORICAL BACkGROUND
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l2' n='N002'/>xviii
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l3' n='N003'/>regulation, religious worship, and/or mutual social support (they largely included reli.
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l4' n='N004'/>gious/social fraternities as part of their organizational structure). By the thirteenth to four*
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l5' n='N005'/>teenth centuries they had become political groups of businessmen, through which a sub–
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l6' n='N006'/>stantial amount of the city&apos;s governing was directly or indirectly carried out. Throughout
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l7' n='N007'/>this collection, these organizations are called companies, to distinguish them from purely
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l8' n='N008'/>religious guilds and to be consistent in terminology over a time period during which gradually,
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l9' n='N009'/>from the fourteenth century on, most of the organized crast or trade guilds surviving from
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l10' n='N010'/>earlier times acquired royal charters and became what are today called livery companies:
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l11' n='N011'/>incorporated organizations, able to hold property, whose senior, more substantial members
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l12' n='N012'/>wore (and still wear today) a distinctive company gown andlor hood (livery) on formal occa*
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l13' n='N013'/>sions. S Today the surviving companies from the pre–1550 period, along with numerous others
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l14' n='N014'/>created later, are essentially London private associations involved in charitable work, education,
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l15' n='N015'/>and social activities, sometimes with links to their original crafts or trades. In early London,
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l16' n='N016'/>however, although differing from one another to (sometimes widely) varying extents in financial
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l17' n='N017'/>means, interests, and operation, generally they regulated their crafts and trades, settled their
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l18' n='N018'/>members disputes, and carried out various religious, social, and charitable responsibilities
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l19' n='N019'/>These included praying for the souls of departed members, walking or riding (on horseback
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l20' n='N020'/>or on barges) in procession on specific city religious and secular occasions (such as the mayoral
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l21' n='N021'/>and shrieval inauguration processions to Westminster), and looking to the welfare of impecuni.
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l22' n='N022'/>ous members (which could include, for the better–off companies, the establishing of alms–
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l23' n='N023'/>houses). The companies carried out other important functions as well for the city, such as
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l24' n='N024'/>providing funds for royal loans and taxes and for routine civic projects and special initiatives
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l25' n='N025'/>(such as the building of kitchens at the Guildhall in the early sixteenth century). Most
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l26' n='N026'/>importantly for this collection, all of the companies – at least all of those stable and sufficiently
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l27' n='N027'/>solvent at any given time – also contributed to the city&apos;s formal street music and pageantry.
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l28' n='N028'/>Especially active in this were the Great Twelve companies, a group of companies wealthier
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l29' n='N029'/>and more influential than the rest, standing one to twelve in the order of precedence that,
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l30' n='N030'/>although fluctuating somewhat, from its informal beginnings in the fourteenth on into the
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l31' n='N031'/>early sixteenth century, ranked all city companies in relation to one another.₺s Like othei
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l32' n='N032'/>companies, the Great Twelve (known as such by the late fifteenth century) processed frequently
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l33' n='N033'/>in their livery gowns and hoods, and often with music, with the mayor and other city officials
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l34' n='N034'/>on various kinds of occasions (such as mayoral and shrieval inaugurations and ridings to
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l35' n='N035'/>meet entering royalty: the processional responsibility itself was normally included in companies
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l36' n='N036'/>ordinances). But they also contributed in a major way–at least from the late fifteenth century
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l37' n='N037'/>to the annual Midsummer Watch, a night–time parade held yearly on the eves to mornings
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l38' n='N038'/>of 23–4 and 28–0 ]une (see below, pp xxxiv–xl). All of the companies able to do so con–
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l39' n='N039'/>tributed men to the Watch when required: but it was largely the Great Twelve– from whose
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l40' n='N040'/>membership by this time came always the mayor and usually the sheriffs– that were responsible
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l41' n='N041'/>for the constructed portable pageants, morris dancers, giants, fireworks, and the like which
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l42' n='N042'/>were normally a part of the Watch by at least the early sixteenth century. The companies
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l43' n='N043'/>with a mayor or a sheriff in office at midsummer in any given year provided the display and
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l44' n='N044'/>entertainment in that year. Occasionally a sheriff was not from a Great Company, and his
			</p>
			<pb n='9'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l42' n='N042'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l43' n='N043'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l44' n='N044'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='10'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l42' n='N042'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l43' n='N043'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l44' n='N044'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='11'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l15' n='N015'/>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
