<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>DramaMusicCeremony_Civic</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l1' n='N001'/>Drama, Music, and Ceremonial
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l2' n='N002'/>Customs
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l3' n='N003'/>Ceremonial occasions involving music and often other performance activities abounded in
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l4' n='N004'/>medieval and early Tudor London: from religious processions, on set feast–days, in which the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l5' n='N005'/>city officers and the companies took part (which are not the concern of REED), to the secular
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l6' n='N006'/>processions of the mayor&apos;s oath–taking and sheriffs presentation annually, to and from
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l7' n='N007'/>Westminster, to the formal entries – at a variety of musical and visualedisplay levels– of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l8' n='N008'/>royalty and other important personages into the city. In at least the late fourteenth and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l9' n='N009'/>early fifteenth centuries a multi–day biblical play– the London equivalent of the Cornish
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l10' n='N010'/>Ordinalia and of the biblical play cycles of centres such as Tork– was performed just outside
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l11' n='N011'/>the city walls at Clerkenwell/Skinners Well. Street celebrations of occasions such as a roya
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l12' n='N012'/>birth, a military victory abroad, or the conclusion of a peace treaty, might also be ordered
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l13' n='N013'/>by the civic authorities (usually in response to a directive from the Crown). More informal
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l14' n='N014'/>occasions of street revelry might involve hockings, mayings, and officially or unofficially
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l15' n='N015'/>sanctioned –or sometimes prohibited – misrule and other festivities in the Christmas or
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l16' n='N016'/>May seasons. At midsummer every year came two nights of festive celebration, including
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l17' n='N017'/>from at least the late fourteenth century, a visually impressive and (from some time in the
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l18' n='N018'/>fifteenth century) increasingly theatrical marching watch: the Midsummer Watch. The
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l19' n='N019'/>companies had their annual, biennial, or triennial feast times, mixing religious and secular
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l20' n='N020'/>observances, such as dirges, masses, election of company officers, and dinners with enter*
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l21' n='N021'/>tainments of various kinds, and other special occasions could also involve performances.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l22' n='N022'/>The city might send entertainments to the court, or itself entertain royalty, nobility, foreign
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l23' n='N023'/>ambassadors, and the like, at magnificent dinners and on occasions such as the Midsummer
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l24' n='N024'/>Watch. Almost all of these occasions would have involved music, especially trumpeters for
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l25' n='N025'/>processions, although manuscript records often do not note it. Some involved constructed
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l26' n='N026'/>wood–and–canvas pageants, with or without performers, either carried through the streets by
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l27' n='N027'/>porters (as in the Midsummer Watch) or placed on fixed stages along a processional route
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l28' n='N028'/>(as in royal entries). Some involved mummings, plays, acrobats, juggling, and other forms
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l29' n='N029'/>of entertainment, such as tumbling and animal acts.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l30' n='N030'/>Formal Entries
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l31' n='N031'/>Information on entries into London, from the basic to the highly elaborate, comes in large
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l32' n='N032'/>part from sources such as chronicle histories, supplemented to varying extents, from the late
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxiii
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l3' n='N003'/>fourteenth century on, by the civic records. London&apos;s proximity to Westminster, as already
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l4' n='N004'/>noted, resulted in the city being frequently called upon to provide– below the level of corona*
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l5' n='N005'/>tion and other such major ceremonial entries into and through the city– welcomes, escortings
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l6' n='N006'/>lodgings, feasts, gifts, and the like, to important visitors to the court such as ambassadors,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l7' n='N007'/>papal emissaries and minor royalty. The city also often met and escorted the monarch or his[her
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l8' n='N008'/>consort, by land or by water, on standard comings and goings to and from Westminster. These
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l9' n='N009'/>activities in large part do not appear in this collection, because sources do not often mention
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l10' n='N010'/>music or theatrical activity in relation to them, although music was doubtless often involved€
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l11' n='N011'/>but in a few cases, especially in the sixteenth century, music is recorded. The most important
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l12' n='N012'/>and expensive occasions are normally recorded in the sources with reference to music and
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l13' n='N013'/>pageantry, and so appear in this collection&apos;s records, Appendix I, or both. These occasions
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l14' n='N014'/>were the formal entries provided only for especially important visitors to the court, such as
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l15' n='N015'/>the emperor Charles V in 1522, and for English monarchs themselves, and their consorts,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l16' n='N016'/>usually only on the occasion of their coronations. Some historical background on coronation
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l17' n='N017'/>entry requirements has already been provided above (p xv). Before the late fourteenth century,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l18' n='N018'/>our information on coronation and similarly elaborate royal entries comes largely from the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l19' n='N019'/>chronicles, and not at all from the civic records: from 1377 on, we have a varying mix of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l20' n='N020'/>civic records and other sources. By the late fourteenth century it is possible to talk about a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l21' n='N021'/>standard format, which probably existed much earlier, for major formal entries, although
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l22' n='N022'/>not all of such entries conformed to all aspects of the pattern, and in some cases we have
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l23' n='N023'/>insufficient entry information to know.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l24' n='N024'/>The standard coronation or other such major entry, by at least the late fourteenth centu*
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l25' n='N025'/>ry, seems normally to have involved the individual concerned– English monarch, royal
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l26' n='N026'/>consort, visiting foreign monarch– being met just outside the city (most often to the south,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l27' n='N027'/>at Blackheath) by the mayor and other city officers on horseback, accompanied by a large
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l28' n='N028'/>number of citizens, all in formal liveries, and by musicians (doubtless especially trumpeters)
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l29' n='N029'/>After official greetings, the individual and his[her entourage would be escorted by the civic
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l30' n='N030'/>party into and through London. The streets would be decorated with banners and rich
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l31' n='N031'/>cloths hung from windows and doors: the streets would be gravelled (and the Bridge sanded
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l32' n='N032'/>or gravelled) for the passage of the horses. Along the processional route, stationary pageants
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l33' n='N033'/>consisting of constructed set pieces, role–playing performers, or both, and featuring saints,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l34' n='N034'/>angels, castles, personified virtues, genealogical trees, and the like– would normally be
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l35' n='N035'/>displayed at customary locations. Mechanical devices would often be incorporated into
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l36' n='N036'/>one or more of the pageants: and one or more water conduits would usually (especially
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l37' n='N037'/>for coronation entries) run with wine. Individual pageants could be designed with special
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l38' n='N038'/>reference to the honoured entrant: St Margaret, for example, in one pageant welcoming
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l39' n='N039'/>Margaret of Anjou in 1445, and biblical mothers (such as St Anne), with children, in a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l40' n='N040'/>pageant for the pregnant Anne Boleyn at her 1533 coronation entry. The ordered series
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l41' n='N041'/>of pageants could be designed according to a particular relevant theme: for example, as
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l42' n='N042'/>Gordon kipling has argued, that of the elegiac dream vision of ascent to glory, for the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l43' n='N043'/>1501 entry of Ratherine of Aragon coming to marry the heir to the English throne, Prince
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l44' n='N044'/>Arthur.5 From at least the late fifteenth century, and probably earlier, the companies in
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l45' n='N045'/>their liveries would line the streets for a major entry, using standings (also called rails,
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxiv
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l3' n='N003'/>scaffolds, frames, or sometimes stages): these, provided by the companies themselves, were
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l4' n='N004'/>wooden constructions temporarily set up along the sides of the streets and consisting of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l5' n='N005'/>rails along the front of low platforms. The companies in their liveries functioned both as
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l6' n='N006'/>an official part of entry display and as a means of crowd control, since other spectators
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l7' n='N007'/>of the entry would be behind them. The rails also served as protection from the passing
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l8' n='N008'/>horses for those in the front line.S Each company was assigned to a particular stretch of
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l9' n='N009'/>the entry route: and ecclesiastics would also have their arranged positions, at the locations
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l10' n='N010'/>of their churches or religious houses where these were on the route.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l11' n='N011'/>The traditional land route for major entries, from at least the fourteenth century and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l12' n='N012'/>probably long before, was from Southwark across London Bridge and then, for non–coronation
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l13' n='N013'/>entrants, up Bridge Street and (New) Fish Street to Gracechurch Street and to Cornhill
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l14' n='N014'/>then west along Cornhill, Poultry, and Cheapside to St Paul&apos;s, and beyond St Paul&apos;s through
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l15' n='N015'/>Ludgate and along Fleet Street, past Temple Bar to Westminster (unless the entrant was to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l16' n='N016'/>stay at the Bishop&apos;s Palace at St Paul&apos;s, or elsewhere between St Paul&apos;s and Westminster).
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l17' n='N017'/>Non–coronation entries took place entirely on one day. Coronation entries, from at least
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l18' n='N018'/>the end of the fourteenth century, were two–day affairs, as the monarch was required (as
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l19' n='N019'/>noted above, p xv), from at least 1377 and probably earlier, to process, on the day before
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l20' n='N020'/>the coronation, from the Tower of London (royal territory although within the city walls)
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l21' n='N021'/>through the city to Westminster. The monarch&apos;s procession to the Tower (usually, before
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l22' n='N022'/>1483, across the Bridge) on a preceding day (usually, until 1485, the day before) had thus
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l23' n='N023'/>probably also become a part of the formal entry from very early on.s From at least the mid–
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l24' n='N024'/>fifteenth century, royal consorts coming to be crowned at Westminster were also required
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l25' n='N025'/>to follow the two–day process, and sources show a two–day format for their entries from at
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l26' n='N026'/>least 130677. The specifics of the coronation land–entry route for the first day, from the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l27' n='N027'/>Bridge to the Tower, are not usually provided in entry descriptions: but in 1420 Henry vi
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l28' n='N028'/>went via Fenchurch Street, that is, by a circuitous route up Bridge Street and (New) Fish
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l29' n='N029'/>Street to Gracechurch Street (northwest of the Tower), then east along Fenchurch Street
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l30' n='N030'/>to Mark Lane, and back south down Mark Lane to Tower Street and the Tower. In 1485
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l31' n='N031'/>Henry viI and in 1500 Henry vi1 are said to have gone to the Tower via Grace Church,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l32' n='N032'/>which suggests that the same route was followed (Bridge Street, Fish Street, Gracechurch
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l33' n='N033'/>Street, and so forth) as that taken by Henry vi in 1420.10 Perhaps this was the traditional
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l34' n='N034'/>route– not direct, but a ceremonial loop, along comparatively wide streets. On a second
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l35' n='N035'/>day (from 1485 not usually the next day) the entrant proceeded from the Tower back to
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l36' n='N036'/>Gracechurch Street via Tower Street, Mark Lane, and Fenchurch Street, and then along
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l37' n='N037'/>the established route, from Gracechurch Street to Cheapside, St Paul&apos;s, and eventually
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l38' n='N038'/>Westminster. The coronation took place the next day. From 1483 a water procession to the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l39' n='N039'/>Tower, with elaborate water pageants in at least both 1487 and 1533, began to replace the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l40' n='N040'/>preTower coronation land procession across the Bridge. From 1483 to 1558, only two of eight
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l41' n='N041'/>coronation entrants, Henry vil in 1485 and Henry vIl in 1500, made a land procession
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l42' n='N042'/>across the Bridge to the Tower.12
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l43' n='N043'/>Constructed land pageants for major entries, coronation and non–coronation, go back at
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l44' n='N044'/>least as far as 1357, and probably at least to the thirteenth century. The city&apos;s own manuscript
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxv
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l3' n='N003'/>records of such pageants, together with the pageant records of the companies, do not go back
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l4' n='N004'/>further than 1377: but chroniclers earlier use words such as prodigialibus adinventionibus
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l5' n='N005'/>to describe city entry display, and Appendix I includes a number of pre–1377 entries, which
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l6' n='N006'/>may have included (and in 1357 definitely included) one or more constructed or performed
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l7' n='N007'/>pageants.8 The castle– perhaps from 1200, 1308, and[or 1357 and definitely from 1377–is SC
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l8' n='N008'/>far the earliest identified type of stationary constructed pageant, although the entry activity
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l9' n='N009'/>up to 1415, of scattering real or mock gold and[or silver coins or leaves, can be found as
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l10' n='N010'/>early as 1274, and from at least 1377 is associated with a castle./ The castle was apparently a
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l11' n='N011'/>staple of constructed pageantry: at first always in Cheapside, with the coins or leaves scatterec
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l12' n='N012'/>by maidens. Castles emblematically could represent, separately or in combinations, a variety
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l13' n='N013'/>of physical and spiritual entities: for example, a city, a political state, heaven, hell, the Nev
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l14' n='N014'/>]erusalem, the virgin body.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l15' n='N015'/>Constructed pageants for major entries were normally located along the traditiona
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l16' n='N016'/>processional route at customary points where street width permitted and [or where existing
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l17' n='N017'/>structures along or in the streets (such as water conduits) could serve as a foundation or
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l18' n='N018'/>backdrop for them: and the number of pageants in a major entry grew over time, perhaps not
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l19' n='N019'/>only because of the natural pressures for each celebration not simply to equal but to surpass
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l20' n='N020'/>preceding celebrations but also in part because of the increasing number of advantageous
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l21' n='N021'/>structural locations for pageants. The Great Conduit in Cheapside, for example, had beer
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l22' n='N022'/>built by c 1245 and was in use in 1200 (for the entry of Margaret of France) at least as an
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l23' n='N023'/>entry wine outlet and perhaps as a pageant location.S The Little Conduit, at the western
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l24' n='N024'/>end of Cheapside, was begun in 1380 (and rebuilt or completed in 1440–1), and pageants
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l25' n='N025'/>start to be recorded there at least by 1415.1 The conduit in Gracechurch Street was begun
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l26' n='N026'/>in 1401, and pageants were sometimes located there in the sixteenth century.s A good
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l27' n='N027'/>number of other pageant locations are recorded, in recurring references, over various
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l28' n='N028'/>different time periods: Fenchurch Street, Leadenhall (at the intersection of Gracechurch
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l29' n='N029'/>Street and Cornhill), the Cornhill conduit, the Stocks, the Standard and the Cross (both in
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l30' n='N030'/>Cheapside), St Paul&apos;s, Ludgate, the Fleet Street conduit, Temple Bar.1/ There was always
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l31' n='N031'/>at least one pageant in Cheapside– by the fifteenth century usually more than one – and
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l32' n='N032'/>although the specific location of early pageants there is not clear, the Cross was especially
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l33' n='N033'/>important in the fifteenth century.2 Particular locations in some periods regularly featured
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l34' n='N034'/>the same kind of pageant: for example, the castle in Cheapside in perhaps consecutive
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l35' n='N035'/>entries from at least 1377 to 1432.2 On London Bridge, with houses and shops lining
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l36' n='N036'/>the roadway on both sides, three locations have been identified as suitable for constructed
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l37' n='N037'/>pageant displays and singing choirs: at the foot of the Bridge at its south end, in Southwark:
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l38' n='N038'/>at the Stonegate (a defensive gatehouse, with towers, on the second pier from the south
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l39' n='N039'/>end): and at the Drawbridge gate (a gatehouse with towers, a drawbridge, and a portcullis
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l40' n='N040'/>on the seventh pier from the south end).2€ These locations provided both some open space,
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l41' n='N041'/>unavailable otherwise on the narrow roadway, and towers and facades not only convenient
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l42' n='N042'/>for the positioning of costumed figures and the hanging of decorative cloths and banners, but
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l43' n='N043'/>also providing useful support and background for constructed figures and stages.€ From at
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l44' n='N044'/>least 1413 to 1554 one or more giants – gatekeepers in folklore৳s– were traditional parts of
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxvi
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l3' n='N003'/>Bridge display for male entrants€€৳ and angels and[or maidens (sometimes specified as in a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l4' n='N004'/>tower) were featured between at least 1415 and 1465.2 Otherwise Bridge pageants seem to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l5' n='N005'/>have varied by entry, suited each time to the particular entrant and occasion. Peace and Plenty:
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l6' n='N006'/>for example, and Noahs ark greeted Margaret of Anjou in 1445, since her marriage to Henry vi
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l7' n='N007'/>had been arranged to confirm peace between England and France.2 The presence on the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l8' n='N008'/>Bridge of a chapel of St Thomas, with singing priests and clerks, and of St Magnus the Martyr
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l9' n='N009'/>Church near the Bridge&apos;s north end, doubtless meant that the Bridge did not lack for readily
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l10' n='N010'/>available musical resources for entries (although it could reach farther for them as well). The
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l11' n='N011'/>Bridge House accounts record payment, for example, to the child choristers of St Magnus the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l12' n='N012'/>Martyr for their part in the 1465 entry of Elizabeth Woodville.2
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l13' n='N013'/>The Bridges liminal status for entrants into London has been emphasized by several recent
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l14' n='N014'/>historians, along with its key position as the location of the first pageant(s) in a major entry,
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l15' n='N015'/>able to set the tone and theme for the whole.2 The break of one day or more, however, for
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l16' n='N016'/>coronation entries, between Bridge pageantry and other city pageantry, would have required
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l17' n='N017'/>any thematic connection between Bridge pageants and the city&apos;s pageants to have been
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l18' n='N018'/>designed with the break in mind. Also, from 1483, as previously noted, the Thames itself
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l19' n='N019'/>began to replace the Bridge in coronation entries, with water pageantry replacing Bridge
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l20' n='N020'/>pageantry, although land pageants were featured as usual in the pre–coronation procession
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l21' n='N021'/>from the Tower to Westminster. (Non–coronation welcomings, escortings, and the like
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l22' n='N022'/>could also involve the Thames. Henry vii, for example, in 1486, was welcomed by the city
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l23' n='N023'/>on the water, with celebratory gunfire or other pyrotechnical display, when he returned
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l24' n='N024'/>to Westminster from a progress in the North. Anne of Cleves in 1535/40 was met by
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l25' n='N025'/>Londoners at Blackheath and then escorted by land to Greenwich, where London put on a
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l26' n='N026'/>water show for her. A month later, Londoners escorted her by water from Greenwich to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l27' n='N027'/>Westminster: she made no actual formal entry into the city.so)
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l28' n='N028'/>Not all major royal entries necessarily followed all aspects of the pattern described above.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l29' n='N029'/>The decoration of the streets with rich hangings, for example, is not always referred to
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l30' n='N030'/>though it was almost certainly a standard major–entry feature, and perhaps some coronation
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l31' n='N031'/>entries did not have pageants, although we may simply have insufficient information on
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l32' n='N032'/>these entries. Chronicles and other non–civic manuscripts are usually our major sources of
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l33' n='N033'/>information on entry pageants, and chroniclers followed their own interests in what they
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l34' n='N034'/>wrote about, and also their own political agendas, even where royalty was concerned. No
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l35' n='N035'/>chronicler, for example, tells us about the Cheapside pageant for Anne of Bohemias 1382
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l36' n='N036'/>royal entry: we learn about it only from an early Goldsmiths manuscript.3 Chroniclers also
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l37' n='N037'/>can merely generalize, or use ambiguous wording (although the records too can sometimes be
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l38' n='N038'/>frustratingly minimal or unclear). Constructed pageants seem to have been regularly provided
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l39' n='N039'/>however, from at least 1421, for the coronation entries of queen consorts when crowned
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l40' n='N040'/>separately from their husbands: and since Anne of Bohemia in 1382 was welcomed with an
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l41' n='N041'/>entry pageant although she was not yet married to Richard II (her marriage and then corona*
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l42' n='N042'/>tion came shortly after her entry), it is certainly possible that one or more pageants were alsC
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l43' n='N043'/>provided for queen consorts Isabella of France in 1306/7 and ]oan of Navarre in 140273.3
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l44' n='N044'/>For ruling monarchs, the picture is less clear than for consorts. Coronation–entry pageants
			</p>
			<pb n='6'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxvii
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l3' n='N003'/>were provided possibly for Edward I (1308) and Henry 1v (1300), and definitely for Richard II
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l4' n='N004'/>(1377), Henry V (14133 though we know only of singers and one or more giants, at the Bridge),
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l5' n='N005'/>and Henry vi (1420), and again in the sixteenth century for Edward vi, Mary, and Elizabeth 1:
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l6' n='N006'/>but for Edward IIl (1327), Edward 1v (1460), Richard I (1483), Henry vi1 (1485), and (with
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l7' n='N007'/>one possible exception) Henry vii1 (1500), we have no evidence of coronation–entry pageants
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l8' n='N008'/>The lack of information for Edward III, Edward Iv, Richard IIl, and Henry vii, and lack of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l9' n='N009'/>clarity for Henry Iv, could be ascribed to factors such as the chroniclers greater interest in–
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l10' n='N010'/>or caution because of– the political circumstances of these monarchs accessions: and the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l11' n='N011'/>political circumstances could also explain any actual absence of pageants. Henry VIII, however,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l12' n='N012'/>was a legitimate heir in an orderly succession process. Unless the chronicle references to
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l13' n='N013'/>virgins in white at the goldsmiths stalls in Cheapside (at Old Change), at Henry vi11s 1500
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l14' n='N014'/>coronation entry from the Tower to Westminster, are to a pageant of some kind, Henry vIIl is
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l15' n='N015'/>not recorded as having had coronation–entry pageants. Perhaps a pageant norm had lapsed
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l16' n='N016'/>over the preceding eighty years: or perhaps pageants after all were not a coronation–entry
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l17' n='N017'/>norm for ruling monarchs until the mid–sixteenth century. 2
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l18' n='N018'/>Normally, a monarch seems to have been given a pageantic entry only once during his[her
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l19' n='N019'/>reign, immediately preceding his/her coronation. In the late fourteenth and early fifteentk
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l20' n='N020'/>centuries, however, on three occasions a ruling monarch who had already received a corona
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l21' n='N021'/>tion entry with one or more pageants was given an additional pageantic entry because of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l22' n='N022'/>unusual circumstances: Richard II in 1302 (a gift from the city after a major quarrel with
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l23' n='N023'/>the king): Henry V in 1415 (a celebration of his military victory at Agincourt): and Henry vi
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l24' n='N024'/>in 1432 (a welcoming of him from his coronation in France). Also, although pageants seem
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l25' n='N025'/>normally to have been reserved for ruling monarchs (native or foreign) and the consorts of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l26' n='N026'/>English rulers, in 1426, for the entry from France of the duke of Bedford, Lord Protectori
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l27' n='N027'/>with his duchess, pageantry was provided on London Bridge. Perhaps only the Bridge provided
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l28' n='N028'/>pageantry (including music) on this occasion, or perhaps the city did as well but Bedford&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l29' n='N029'/>arrival simply did not interest fifteenth–century chroniclers.৳ Either the occasion was unusual
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l30' n='N030'/>or there were other such individuals, over the centuries, who were similarly honoured
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l31' n='N031'/>but for whose entries the records – along with any mention in chronicle histories– have
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l32' n='N032'/>not survived.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l33' n='N033'/>Usually the Crown directed the city on the level of entry to be orchestrated for any given
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l34' n='N034'/>entrant, and the city made and paid for arrangements accordingly8 For a coronation entry
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l35' n='N035'/>or other major display entry, regularly from 1483 (and at least occasionally before then) a
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l36' n='N036'/>special financial assessment, or tax, would be approved by the city&apos;s common council to
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l37' n='N037'/>cover all or part of the citys costs for gifts, entry preparations, or both. From 1483 this ta৲
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l38' n='N038'/>was regularly in the form of one or more fifteenths – a fifteenth being a fixed amount of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l39' n='N039'/>money, little changed since the early fourteenth century, levied on the citys wards rather
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l40' n='N040'/>than directly on individuals. This form of tax was used for many funding purposes by the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l41' n='N041'/>city (not only for activities such as major entries), and gave the wards the discretion to spare
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l42' n='N042'/>the poor from payment. The companies with halls seem normally to have paid fifteenths
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l43' n='N043'/>usually a fixed sum, per fifteenth, for each company, also largely unchanged over the years*
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l44' n='N044'/>in the wards where their halls were located. Sometimes this money was called a benevolence:
			</p>
			<pb n='7'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxviii
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l3' n='N003'/>that is, supposedly a voluntary contribution. The coronation tax in 1483, 1485, and 1500
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l4' n='N004'/>was one fifteenth: for coronations and other major entries in all of 15Ol, 1522, and on to
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l5' n='N005'/>1554, it was one–and–a₯half fifteenths: and for the coronation of Elizabeth 1 (1550), the tax
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l6' n='N006'/>was two fifteenths. Sometimes the fifteenths were specified to be for more than entry costs
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l7' n='N007'/>and gifts: in 1547, for example, for the costs of the funeral of Henry viIl as well as for the
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l8' n='N008'/>coronation of Edward vi, and in 1522, for bowmen for the kings service as well as for the
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l9' n='N009'/>entry of the emperor Charles v.2s Special collectors would be appointed to receive the tax
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l10' n='N010'/>money, and sometimes the citizens reluctance to pay was considerable, as in 1533 for th
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l11' n='N011'/>coronation entry of the unpopular Anne Boleyn. Not only London citizens were taxed
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l12' n='N012'/>From at least 1522 on, the records show that all residents in London, non–citizens as well as
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l13' n='N013'/>citizens, were required to pay৳ and in 1522, 1533, 1553, and 1554, London residents from
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l14' n='N014'/>various foreign states, such as Venetians and Florentines, were specifically obliged either to
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l15' n='N015'/>contribute to the one–and–a₯half fifteenths or to contribute their own constructed pageants
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l16' n='N016'/>to the entries.1
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l17' n='N017'/>There were important entries into London, other than the major ones already discussed
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l18' n='N018'/>which followed a different pattern. Accession entries– being the immediate movement of a
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l19' n='N019'/>new monarch to take possession of the Tower upon accession to the throne – also occurred,
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l20' n='N020'/>and varied somewhat in the initial route they followed: but at least those in the 155os fell
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l21' n='N021'/>into what appears to have been, by then, an expected ceremonial pattern once the monarch
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l22' n='N022'/>had entered through one of the city&apos;s gates. The entry point seems in part to have depended,
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l23' n='N023'/>as a practical consideration, on where the new monarch was located at the time of acces
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l24' n='N024'/>sion. Elizabeth I, for example, was at Hatfield, to the north of London, and when she
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l25' n='N025'/>reached London, she first stayed at the Charterhouse (outside the walls to the northwest)
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l26' n='N026'/>and so entered from the northwest, through Cripplegate.  Her predecessor Mary had to
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l27' n='N027'/>manoeuvre militarily for the throne, outside London, because of the proclamation of the
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l28' n='N028'/>Lady [ane Grey as queen upon the death of Edward vi: her headquarters were to the northeast:
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l29' n='N029'/>and when an accession entry to the Tower finally became possible for her, Mary entered from
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l30' n='N030'/>east of the city, through Aldgate. Both Elizabeth and Mary, however, then made their way
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l31' n='N031'/>to Leadenhall and followed the same basic route: from Leadenhall down Gracechurch Street to
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l32' n='N032'/>Fenchurch Street, then east along Fenchurch Street and down Mark Lane to the Tower, and fo*
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l33' n='N033'/>Mary, this entailed going out of her way, from Aldgate west along Aldgate Street to Leadenhall
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l34' n='N034'/>before moving south and then east again to the Tower. The route from Leadenhall to the
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l35' n='N035'/>Tower was not only practical (given street widths), but likely also ceremonially customary:
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l36' n='N036'/>from the intersection of Gracechurch Street and Fenchurch Street, it was the same route
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l37' n='N037'/>followed (as described above, p xxiv) by all of Henry vi, Henry vil, and Henry viII on the
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l38' n='N038'/>first day of their two–day coronation entries. In 1547, however, Edward vi, although north
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l39' n='N039'/>of the city at his accession, perhaps for security reasons entered through Aldgate and turned
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l40' n='N040'/>directly south, along by the city wall and past the Crutched Friars to the Tower.€ Accession
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l41' n='N041'/>entries – about which we have very little information before the sixteenth century – appear
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l42' n='N042'/>usually to have involved cheering crowds, speeches, and music, but no pageants until 1603
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l43' n='N043'/>[when one was prepared, but then not presented after all). Pageants would have been precluded
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l44' n='N044'/>by the unpredictability and speed of accessions, and also sometimes by their difficult or
			</p>
			<pb n='8'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxix
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l3' n='N003'/>unusual political circumstances. Where accession entries appear in The Records, Appendix I,
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l4' n='N004'/>or both, it is because music is recorded
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l5' n='N005'/>Other kinds of welcoming or escorting occasions in London, below the level of the major
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l6' n='N006'/>entries, might involve, on land, one or more of the decoration of the streets, the companie:
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l7' n='N007'/>lining the streets, and music. The routes could vary. The king, for example, might require
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l8' n='N008'/>only a welcoming escort when he returned to the city from a journey within England or
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l9' n='N009'/>abroad: or more elaboration might be required even on a minor occasion, such as a riding
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l10' n='N010'/>from Westminster to a palace south of the Thames. Different levels of activity and display
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l11' n='N011'/>were also involved in welcomings and escortings by water.
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l12' n='N012'/>The city could prepare quickly for a non–pageantic entry or other escort requirement,
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l13' n='N013'/>needing only to order the companies to provide riders (company members, either on horse–
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l14' n='N014'/>back or on barges on the water), in full livery, to meet the entrant, and, if required for a
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l15' n='N015'/>land entry, company members to line the streets. Also the occupants of buildings along the
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l16' n='N016'/>land–entry route needed little time to hang from their windows any required decorative
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l17' n='N017'/>rich cloths and banners: and barges could be quickly decorated for a water escort. Choristers
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l18' n='N018'/>and instrumental musicians from city churches could also be called into service rapidly, as
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l19' n='N019'/>could the city waits (the city&apos;s own paid musicians) and, at least from e 1500, the members
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l20' n='N020'/>of the Minstrels Company.S In 1549, for example, when the city had only some forty–eight
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l21' n='N021'/>hours to provide a musical welcome for Edward vi riding through the city from the Bridge
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l22' n='N022'/>to Westminster, orders went out for the gravelling of the streets, for citizens to hang out cloths,
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l23' n='N023'/>for the companies of Parish Clerks and of Minstrels to provide singers and musicians, and
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l24' n='N024'/>for the waits to play. The children of Paul&apos;s (presumably the cathedral choristers) were also
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l25' n='N025'/>required to turn out.1/ Pageants, however, took some time to prepare, although once made
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l26' n='N026'/>they could be stored between occasions and then mended or otherwise renovated when
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l27' n='N027'/>required again.18 One reason for the elaborateness of the pageants prepared for the entry of
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l28' n='N028'/>Xatherine of Aragon, arriving in 1501 to marry the heir to England&apos;s throne, Prince Arthur,
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l29' n='N029'/>was that some two years had passed between the conclusion of the marriage negotiations and
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l30' n='N030'/>katherines arrival in England. The city&apos;s first record of its preparations is dated I) Novembei
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l31' n='N031'/>1400: and the entry finally took place on 12 November 1501. When necessary, however,
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l32' n='N032'/>pageants could be prepared quickly, as in 1547 when the city had only three weeks from the
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l33' n='N033'/>accession of Edward vi to his coronation entry. In 1533 the coronation entry of Anne Boleyn,
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l34' n='N034'/>by both water and land, had to be provided in less than two weeks. Elaborate entries, whether
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l35' n='N035'/>prepared slowly or speedily, called upon the expertise not only of designers, craftsmen, and
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l36' n='N036'/>producers but also of scholars and writers. Names of the latter occurring in the sixteenth–
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l37' n='N037'/>century records of royal entries include, for example, those of grammarian William Lily (in
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l38' n='N038'/>1522), playwright/printer[producer [ohn Rastell (in 1522), scholars and writers Nicholas Udall
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l39' n='N039'/>and [ohn Leland (in 1533), and playwright and court entertainer ]ohn Heywood (in 1553
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l40' n='N040'/>and 1554). s.
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l41' n='N041'/>Street processions in relation to royalty did not always include royalty itself, and could
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l42' n='N042'/>sometimes, at least in the late thirteenth and early fourteenth centuries, involve portable
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l43' n='N043'/>pageants. In 1208 the Fishmongers paraded to Leadenhall on St Magnus Day, to celebrate
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l44' n='N044'/>a military victory by the king against the Scots, with a representation of the saint and with
			</p>
			<pb n='9'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxx
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l3' n='N003'/>gilded sturgeons, silver salmon, and knights made to look like luces, all on horses. Other
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l4' n='N004'/>companies may also have had pageants. In 1312713 the Fishmongers rode through the city to
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l5' n='N005'/>Westminster with a ship pageant, to escort the queen from Westminster to Eltham after the
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l6' n='N006'/>birth of Prince Edward./ The city as a whole might also mark special royal events with street
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l7' n='N007'/>celebrations involving music, dance, and often bonfires, normally on the orders of the civic
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l8' n='N008'/>government or the Crown.2s In early 1377, when the city sent mummers to entertain Prince
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l9' n='N009'/>Richard (shortly to become Richard II), the mummers created a major moving spectacle as they
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l10' n='N010'/>rode through the city and across the Bridge on their way to the royal palace at Rennington, in
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l11' n='N011'/>a civic processional equivalent to the occasional fourteenth–century pre–tournament processions
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l12' n='N012'/>made by the nobility through Cheapside.:
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l13' n='N013'/>Mayoral Oath–Takings and Shrieval Presentations
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l14' n='N014'/>The annual inaugurations of the mayor and of the sheriffs were, from early times, significant
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l15' n='N015'/>occasions of civic processional display. For most of the period between c 1200 and 1558, the
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l16' n='N016'/>newly chosen sheriffs swore their oath of office at the Guildhall on 28 September and took
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l17' n='N017'/>office immediately: then, usually on 30 September, they processed to Westminster to be
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l18' n='N018'/>presented there to the king or to the barons of the Exchequer as his representatives. In the
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l19' n='N019'/>early fourteenth century the city successfully argued that no shrieval oath to the Crown was
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l20' n='N020'/>necessary until the sheriffs submitted their accounts at the conclusion of their terms: this
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l21' n='N021'/>collection therefore refers throughout to the sheriffs presentation at Westminster, rather than
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l22' n='N022'/>to their oath–taking, even though they normally took an oath in any case. This terminology
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l23' n='N023'/>also provides a useful differentiation between the shrieval occasion and the oath–taking of the
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l24' n='N024'/>mayor. The newly chosen mayor swore an oath of office at the Guildhall on 28 October, but
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l25' n='N025'/>did not fully become mayor until processing to Westminster, usually on 2 October, to take
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l26' n='N026'/>his oath to the monarch or to the Exchequer barons. The processional route, by the early
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l27' n='N027'/>fifteenth century at least, was from the Guildhall along Cheapside, through Newgate, and
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l28' n='N028'/>along Fleet Street to Westminster. Occasionally, when neither the monarch nor the barons
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l29' n='N029'/>were available at Westminster, the inauguration procession was instead to the Tower of
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l30' n='N030'/>London, for the sheriffs presentation or the mayor&apos;s oath–taking there, before the Constable
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l31' n='N031'/>of the Tower as the monarchs representative. Tower–oath years for both the mayor and the
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l32' n='N032'/>sheriffs, 1208–1558, are listed in Appendix 8.5
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l33' n='N033'/>Although musicians – above all trumpeters– were probably part of both the shrieva
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l34' n='N034'/>and the mayoral processions from very early times, we have no records of processional music
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l35' n='N035'/>until, in the fourteenth century, some of the companies surviving accounts and court minutes
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l36' n='N036'/>begin, since the companies provided much of the ceremonial for mayoral and shrieval inaugura
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l37' n='N037'/>tions. The first company record of oath–taking music for the mayor is in 1360, and the first
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l38' n='N038'/>record of such music for a sheriff is in 1383. Both records are from the Goldsmiths early
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l39' n='N039'/>combined accounts and minutes (which also record mayoral–procession music in 1377
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l40' n='N040'/>and in 1388). The Grocers also record minstrels for a sheriff in 1386: and by the 1300s
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l41' n='N041'/>the records of the Grocers, Mercers, and Merchant Taylors all show one or more payments
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l42' n='N042'/>to minstrels on the mayor&apos;s riding to Westminster, the Mercers also recording minstrels
			</p>
			<pb n='10'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxxi
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l3' n='N003'/>three times with the sheriffs.2 In the fifteenth century, the records become more extensive
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l4' n='N004'/>Early on, the processions could be by land, on foot or on horseback, or by water: but by the
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l5' n='N005'/>late fourteenth century, processions by land, on horseback, appear to have become the norm
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l6' n='N006'/>Then, in 1389, it was determined that, as a cost–cutting measure, the sheriffs should hencefortk
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l7' n='N007'/>no longer ride each year to their Westminster presentations but should go either by water or
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l8' n='N008'/>by foot on land –a decision that does not appear to have taken consistent effect until 1435. 5
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l9' n='N009'/>In 1453, after an initial unsuccessful attempt in 1447, the decision was made that the mayor
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l10' n='N010'/>would regularly go to his Westminster oath–taking by water Prior to this, in the late fourteenth
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l11' n='N011'/>and early fifteenth centuries, the mayor is definitely recorded as going by water only in 1422:
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l12' n='N012'/>an unusual oath–taking year, because the mayoral inauguration was closely followed by the
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l13' n='N013'/>funeral in early November of Henry V. At first, from 1453, the mayor and his entourage went
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l14' n='N014'/>on foot to the Thames to take barges up the river: but in 1501, mayor [ohn Shaa began the
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l15' n='N015'/>practice of riding on horseback to the river.€ Either by land or by water, the procession (even
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l16' n='N016'/>when by water, still often called a riding) involved the city&apos;s governors – aldermen, other city
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l17' n='N017'/>officers, senior members of companies– in their formal liveries, in set processional order, with
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l18' n='N018'/>banners and with minstrels. S
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l19' n='N019'/>By at least the late fifteenth century, some kinds of special displays were in use in the
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l20' n='N020'/>procession on land from the Guildhall to the Thames, and on land again when the mayoi
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l21' n='N021'/>returned from Westminster, as in 148I the city prohibited any disguising or pageant, at the
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l22' n='N022'/>mayor&apos;s oath–taking, either from the mayor&apos;s house to the water or from the water to the
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l23' n='N023'/>mayor&apos;s house. : We cannot be sure of just what these pageants were, given the common use
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l24' n='N024'/>at this time of the word pageant to mean simply an elaborate display (including elaborate
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l25' n='N025'/>banners, wall hangings, embroidered cushions, and the like, as well as images or wood–and
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l26' n='N026'/>canvas constructions): but it is difficult to see why something as usual as banners would
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l27' n='N027'/>have been prohibited. The term disguising also can be variously interpreted, but suggests
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l28' n='N028'/>costuming or masking at the least. It is unclear how long the 148I prohibition held: but the
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l29' n='N029'/>traditional belief that portable constructed pageants began to be carried (again€) in mayoral
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l30' n='N030'/>processions generally, in 1535 and in 1540, is not necessarily correct. This belief has been
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l31' n='N031'/>based on a Drapers record in 1540 which cites, as a precedent for a pageant in the 1540
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l32' n='N032'/>draper mayor&apos;s oath–taking procession, the carrying of a pageant in 1535 at the inauguration
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l33' n='N033'/>of a mercer mayor. Both 1535 and 1540, however, were unusual years in which the mayor
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l34' n='N034'/>swore his oath not at Westminster but at the Tower of London: and the Drapers in 1540
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l35' n='N035'/>cite the 1535 precedent as specifically involving a Tower oath (when the oath–taking procession,
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l36' n='N036'/>from the Guildhall to the Tower and back, was for a shorter distance than to Westminster
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l37' n='N037'/>and back, and without a water component). The 1540 record (actually two records) thus
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l38' n='N038'/>tells us nothing about the usual situation, before or after 1535, in Westminster oath–taking
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l39' n='N039'/>years. Also, given the elasticity of the use of the term pageant, just what the Drapers 1540
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l40' n='N040'/>pageant was, besides being a portable representation of the Assumption, is unclear, although
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l41' n='N041'/>presumably it – and the Mercers 1535 pageant– was something more substantial than a
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l42' n='N042'/>banner or in 1540 no precedent would have been thought necessary. The Drapers sixteenth
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l43' n='N043'/>century Midsummer Watch records provide examples of pageant variety, with representations
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l44' n='N044'/>of the Assumption ranging from elaborate banners to a wood–and–canvas construction in
			</p>
			<pb n='11'/>
			<pb n='12'/>
			<pb n='13'/>
			<pb n='14'/>
			<pb n='15'/>
			<pb n='16'/>
			<pb n='17'/>
			<pb n='18'/>
			<pb n='19'/>
			<pb n='20'/>
			<pb n='21'/>
			<pb n='22'/>
			<pb n='23'/>
			<pb n='24'/>
			<pb n='25'/>
			<pb n='26'/>
			<pb n='27'/>
			<pb n='28'/>
			<pb n='29'/>
			<pb n='30'/>
			<pb n='31'/>
			<pb n='32'/>
			<pb n='33'/>
			<pb n='34'/>
			<pb n='35'/>
			<pb n='36'/>
			<pb n='37'/>
			<pb n='38'/>
			<pb n='39'/>
			<pb n='40'/>
			<pb n='41'/>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
