<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">DramaMusicCeremony_Civic</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1" />
			<p>
				Drama, Music, and Ceremonial Customs Ceremonial occasions involving music and
				often other performance activities abounded in medieval and early Tudor London: from religious processions, on set feast–days, in which the city officers and the companies took part (which are not the concern of REED), to the secular processions of the
				mayor&apos;s oath–taking and sheriffs presentation annually, to and from Westminster, to the formal entries – at a variety of musical and
				visualedisplay levels– of royalty and other important personages into the city. In at least the late fourteenth and early fifteenth centuries a multi–day biblical play– the London equivalent of the Cornish Ordinalia and of the biblical play cycles of centres
				such as Tork– was performed just outside the city walls at Clerkenwell/Skinners Well. Street celebrations of occasions such as a roya birth, a military victory abroad, or the conclusion of a peace treaty, might also be ordered by the civic
				authorities (usually in response to a directive from the Crown). More informal occasions of street revelry might involve hockings, mayings, and
				officially or unofficially sanctioned –or sometimes prohibited – misrule and other festivities in the Christmas or May seasons. At midsummer every year came two nights of festive celebration, including from at least the late fourteenth century, a visually
				impressive and (from some time in the fifteenth century) increasingly theatrical marching watch: the Midsummer Watch. The companies had their annual, biennial, or triennial feast times, mixing religious and secular observances, such as dirges, masses,
				election of company officers, and dinners with enter* tainments of various kinds, and other special occasions could also involve performances. The city might send entertainments to the court, or itself entertain royalty, nobility, foreign ambassadors, and
				the like, at magnificent dinners and on occasions such as the Midsummer Watch. Almost all of these occasions would have involved music, especially
				trumpeters for processions, although manuscript records often do not note it. Some involved constructed wood–and–canvas pageants, with or without performers, either carried through the streets by porters (as in the Midsummer Watch) or placed on
				fixed stages along a processional route (as in royal entries). Some involved mummings, plays, acrobats, juggling, and other forms of entertainment, such as tumbling and animal acts. Formal Entries Information on entries into London, from the basic to the highly elaborate, comes in large part from sources such as chronicle histories,
				supplemented to varying extents, from the late </p>
			<pb n="2" />
			<p>
				DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS xxiii fourteenth century on, by the civic
				records. London&apos;s proximity to Westminster, as already noted, resulted in the city being frequently called upon to provide– below the level of
				corona* tion and other such major ceremonial entries into and through the city– welcomes, escortings lodgings,
				feasts, gifts, and the like, to important visitors to the court such as ambassadors, papal emissaries and minor royalty. The city also often met and
				escorted the monarch or his[her consort, by land or by water, on standard comings and goings to and from Westminster. These activities in large part do not appear in this collection, because sources do not often mention music or theatrical activity in
				relation to them, although music was doubtless often involved€ but in a few cases, especially in the sixteenth century, music is recorded. The most
				important and expensive occasions are normally recorded in the sources with reference to music and pageantry,
				and so appear in this collection&apos;s records, Appendix I, or both. These occasions were the formal entries provided only for especially important
				visitors to the court, such as the emperor Charles V in 1522, and for English monarchs themselves, and their consorts, usually only on the occasion of their coronations. Some historical background on coronation entry requirements has already been
				provided above (p xv). Before the late fourteenth century, our information on coronation and similarly elaborate royal entries comes largely from
				the chronicles, and not at all from the civic records: from 1377 on, we have a varying mix of civic records and
				other sources. By the late fourteenth century it is possible to talk about a standard format, which probably existed much earlier, for major formal
				entries, although not all of such entries conformed to all aspects of the pattern, and in some cases we have insufficient entry information to know. The standard coronation or other such major entry, by at least the late fourteenth centu* ry, seems normally to have involved the individual concerned– English monarch, royal consort, visiting foreign
				monarch– being met just outside the city (most often to the south, at Blackheath) by the mayor and other city officers on horseback, accompanied by
				a large number of citizens, all in formal liveries, and by musicians (doubtless especially trumpeters) After
				official greetings, the individual and his[her entourage would be escorted by the civic party into and through London. The streets would be
				decorated with banners and rich cloths hung from windows and doors: the streets would be gravelled (and the Bridge sanded or gravelled) for the passage of the horses. Along the processional route, stationary pageants consisting of constructed set pieces,
				role–playing performers, or both, and featuring saints, angels, castles, personified virtues, genealogical trees, and the like– would normally be
					displayed at customary locations. Mechanical devices would often be incorporated into one or more of the
				pageants: and one or more water conduits would usually (especially for coronation entries) run with wine. Individual pageants could be designed with
				special reference to the honoured entrant: St Margaret, for example, in one pageant welcoming Margaret of Anjou
				in 1445, and biblical mothers (such as St Anne), with children, in a pageant for the pregnant Anne Boleyn at her 1533 coronation entry. The ordered
				series of pageants could be designed according to a particular relevant theme: for example, as Gordon kipling
				has argued, that of the elegiac dream vision of ascent to glory, for the 1501 entry of Ratherine of Aragon coming to marry the heir to the English
				throne, Prince Arthur.5 From at least the late fifteenth century, and probably earlier, the companies in their
				liveries would line the streets for a major entry, using standings (also called rails, </p>
			<pb n="3" />
			<p>
				DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS xxiv scaffolds, frames, or sometimes
				stages): these, provided by the companies themselves, were wooden constructions temporarily set up along the sides of the streets and consisting of
					rails along the front of low platforms. The companies in their liveries functioned both as an official part of
				entry display and as a means of crowd control, since other spectators of the entry would be behind them. The rails also served as protection from the
				passing horses for those in the front line.S Each company was assigned to a particular stretch of the entry route:
				and ecclesiastics would also have their arranged positions, at the locations of their churches or religious houses where these were on the route.
					The traditional land route for major entries, from at least the fourteenth century and probably long before,
				was from Southwark across London Bridge and then, for non–coronation entrants, up Bridge Street and (New) Fish Street to Gracechurch Street and to
				Cornhill then west along Cornhill, Poultry, and Cheapside to St Paul&apos;s, and beyond St Paul&apos;s through Ludgate and along Fleet Street, past Temple Bar to Westminster (unless the entrant was to stay at the Bishop&apos;s Palace at St Paul&apos;s, or
				elsewhere between St Paul&apos;s and Westminster). Non–coronation entries took place entirely on one day. Coronation entries, from at least the end of the fourteenth century, were two–day affairs, as the monarch was required (as noted above, p xv),
				from at least 1377 and probably earlier, to process, on the day before the coronation, from the Tower of London (royal territory although within the
				city walls) through the city to Westminster. The monarch&apos;s procession to the Tower (usually, before 1483,
				across the Bridge) on a preceding day (usually, until 1485, the day before) had thus probably also become a part of the formal entry from very early
				on.s From at least the mid– fifteenth century, royal consorts coming to be crowned at Westminster were also required to follow the two–day process, and sources show a two–day format for their entries from at least 130677. The specifics of the
				coronation land–entry route for the first day, from the Bridge to the Tower, are not usually provided in entry descriptions: but in 1420 Henry vi
					went via Fenchurch Street, that is, by a circuitous route up Bridge Street and (New) Fish Street to
				Gracechurch Street (northwest of the Tower), then east along Fenchurch Street to Mark Lane, and back south down Mark Lane to Tower Street and the
				Tower. In 1485 Henry viI and in 1500 Henry vi1 are said to have gone to the Tower via Grace Church, which
				suggests that the same route was followed (Bridge Street, Fish Street, Gracechurch Street, and so forth) as that taken by Henry vi in 1420.10
				Perhaps this was the traditional route– not direct, but a ceremonial loop, along comparatively wide streets. On a second day (from 1485 not usually the next day) the entrant proceeded from the Tower back to Gracechurch Street via Tower Street, Mark Lane,
				and Fenchurch Street, and then along the established route, from Gracechurch Street to Cheapside, St Paul&apos;s, and eventually Westminster. The coronation took place the next day. From 1483 a water procession to the Tower, with elaborate
				water pageants in at least both 1487 and 1533, began to replace the preTower coronation land procession across the Bridge. From 1483 to 1558, only
				two of eight coronation entrants, Henry vil in 1485 and Henry vIl in 1500, made a land procession across the
				Bridge to the Tower.12 Constructed land pageants for major entries, coronation and non–coronation, go back at least as far as 1357, and probably at least to the thirteenth century. The city&apos;s own manuscript </p>
			<pb n="4" />
			<p>
				DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS xxv records of such pageants, together
				with the pageant records of the companies, do not go back further than 1377: but chroniclers earlier use words such as prodigialibus adinventionibus
					to describe city entry display, and Appendix I includes a number of pre–1377 entries, which may have included
				(and in 1357 definitely included) one or more constructed or performed pageants.8 The castle– perhaps from 1200, 1308, and[or 1357 and definitely
				from 1377–is SC far the earliest identified type of stationary constructed pageant, although the entry activity up
				to 1415, of scattering real or mock gold and[or silver coins or leaves, can be found as early as 1274, and from at least 1377 is associated with a
				castle./ The castle was apparently a staple of constructed pageantry: at first always in Cheapside, with the coins or leaves scatterec by maidens. Castles emblematically could represent, separately or in combinations, a variety of physical and
				spiritual entities: for example, a city, a political state, heaven, hell, the Nev ]erusalem, the virgin body. Constructed pageants for major entries were normally located along the traditiona processional route at customary points where street width
				permitted and [or where existing structures along or in the streets (such as water conduits) could serve as a foundation or backdrop for them: and the number of pageants in a major entry grew over time, perhaps not only because of the natural pressures for
				each celebration not simply to equal but to surpass preceding celebrations but also in part because of the increasing number of advantageous structural locations for pageants. The Great Conduit in Cheapside, for example, had beer built by c 1245 and was
				in use in 1200 (for the entry of Margaret of France) at least as an entry wine outlet and perhaps as a pageant location.S The Little Conduit, at the
				western end of Cheapside, was begun in 1380 (and rebuilt or completed in 1440–1), and pageants start to be
				recorded there at least by 1415.1 The conduit in Gracechurch Street was begun in 1401, and pageants were sometimes located there in the sixteenth
				century.s A good number of other pageant locations are recorded, in recurring references, over various different
				time periods: Fenchurch Street, Leadenhall (at the intersection of Gracechurch Street and Cornhill), the Cornhill conduit, the Stocks, the Standard
				and the Cross (both in Cheapside), St Paul&apos;s, Ludgate, the Fleet Street conduit, Temple Bar.1/ There was always at least one pageant in Cheapside– by the fifteenth century usually more than one – and although the specific location of early
				pageants there is not clear, the Cross was especially important in the fifteenth century.2 Particular locations in some periods regularly featured
					the same kind of pageant: for example, the castle in Cheapside in perhaps consecutive entries from at least
				1377 to 1432.2 On London Bridge, with houses and shops lining the roadway on both sides, three locations have been identified as suitable for
				constructed pageant displays and singing choirs: at the foot of the Bridge at its south end, in Southwark: at
				the Stonegate (a defensive gatehouse, with towers, on the second pier from the south end): and at the Drawbridge gate (a gatehouse with towers, a
				drawbridge, and a portcullis on the seventh pier from the south end).2€ These locations provided both some open space, unavailable otherwise on the narrow roadway, and towers and facades not only convenient for the positioning of costumed figures and
				the hanging of decorative cloths and banners, but also providing useful support and background for constructed figures and stages.€ From at least 1413 to 1554 one or more giants – gatekeepers in folklore৳s– were traditional parts of </p>
			<pb n="5" />
			<p>
				DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS xxvi Bridge display for male entrants€€৳
				and angels and[or maidens (sometimes specified as in a tower) were featured between at least 1415 and 1465.2 Otherwise Bridge pageants seem to have varied by entry, suited each time to the particular entrant and occasion. Peace and Plenty: for example, and
				Noahs ark greeted Margaret of Anjou in 1445, since her marriage to Henry vi had been arranged to confirm peace between England and France.2 The
				presence on the Bridge of a chapel of St Thomas, with singing priests and clerks, and of St Magnus the Martyr Church near the Bridge&apos;s north end, doubtless meant that the Bridge did not lack for readily available musical resources for entries
				(although it could reach farther for them as well). The Bridge House accounts record payment, for example, to the child choristers of St Magnus the
					Martyr for their part in the 1465 entry of Elizabeth Woodville.2 The Bridges liminal status for entrants
				into London has been emphasized by several recent historians, along with its key position as the location of the first pageant(s) in a major entry,
					able to set the tone and theme for the whole.2 The break of one day or more, however, for coronation
				entries, between Bridge pageantry and other city pageantry, would have required any thematic connection between Bridge pageants and the city&apos;s
				pageants to have been designed with the break in mind. Also, from 1483, as previously noted, the Thames itself began to replace the Bridge in coronation entries, with water pageantry replacing Bridge pageantry, although land pageants were featured as usual
				in the pre–coronation procession from the Tower to Westminster. (Non–coronation welcomings, escortings, and the like could also involve the Thames. Henry vii, for example, in 1486, was welcomed by the city on the water, with celebratory gunfire or
				other pyrotechnical display, when he returned to Westminster from a progress in the North. Anne of Cleves in 1535/40 was met by Londoners at Blackheath and then escorted by land to Greenwich, where London put on a water show for her. A
				month later, Londoners escorted her by water from Greenwich to Westminster: she made no actual formal entry into the city.so) Not all major royal entries necessarily followed all aspects of the pattern described above. The decoration of
				the streets with rich hangings, for example, is not always referred to though it was almost certainly a standard major–entry feature, and perhaps
				some coronation entries did not have pageants, although we may simply have insufficient information on these
				entries. Chronicles and other non–civic manuscripts are usually our major sources of information on entry pageants, and chroniclers followed their
				own interests in what they wrote about, and also their own political agendas, even where royalty was concerned. No chronicler, for example, tells us about the Cheapside pageant for Anne of Bohemias 1382 royal entry: we learn about it only from an early
				Goldsmiths manuscript.3 Chroniclers also can merely generalize, or use ambiguous wording (although the records too can sometimes be frustratingly minimal or unclear). Constructed pageants seem to have been regularly provided however, from at
				least 1421, for the coronation entries of queen consorts when crowned separately from their husbands: and since Anne of Bohemia in 1382 was welcomed
				with an entry pageant although she was not yet married to Richard II (her marriage and then corona* tion came
				shortly after her entry), it is certainly possible that one or more pageants were alsC provided for queen consorts Isabella of France in 1306/7 and
				]oan of Navarre in 140273.3 For ruling monarchs, the picture is less clear than for consorts. Coronation–entry pageants </p>
			<pb n="6" />
			<p>
				DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS xxvii were provided possibly for Edward I
				(1308) and Henry 1v (1300), and definitely for Richard II (1377), Henry V (14133 though we know only of singers and one or more giants, at the
				Bridge), and Henry vi (1420), and again in the sixteenth century for Edward vi, Mary, and Elizabeth 1: but for
				Edward IIl (1327), Edward 1v (1460), Richard I (1483), Henry vi1 (1485), and (with one possible exception) Henry vii1 (1500), we have no evidence of
				coronation–entry pageants The lack of information for Edward III, Edward Iv, Richard IIl, and Henry vii, and lack of clarity for Henry Iv, could be ascribed to factors such as the chroniclers greater interest in– or caution because of– the political
				circumstances of these monarchs accessions: and the political circumstances could also explain any actual absence of pageants. Henry VIII, however,
					was a legitimate heir in an orderly succession process. Unless the chronicle references to virgins in white
				at the goldsmiths stalls in Cheapside (at Old Change), at Henry vi11s 1500 coronation entry from the Tower to Westminster, are to a pageant of some
				kind, Henry vIIl is not recorded as having had coronation–entry pageants. Perhaps a pageant norm had lapsed over
				the preceding eighty years: or perhaps pageants after all were not a coronation–entry norm for ruling monarchs until the mid–sixteenth century. 2
					Normally, a monarch seems to have been given a pageantic entry only once during his[her reign, immediately
				preceding his/her coronation. In the late fourteenth and early fifteentk centuries, however, on three occasions a ruling monarch who had already
				received a corona tion entry with one or more pageants was given an additional pageantic entry because of unusual circumstances: Richard II in 1302 (a gift from the city after a major quarrel with the king): Henry V in 1415 (a celebration of his
				military victory at Agincourt): and Henry vi in 1432 (a welcoming of him from his coronation in France). Also, although pageants seem normally to have been reserved for ruling monarchs (native or foreign) and the consorts of English rulers, in
				1426, for the entry from France of the duke of Bedford, Lord Protectori with his duchess, pageantry was provided on London Bridge. Perhaps only the
				Bridge provided pageantry (including music) on this occasion, or perhaps the city did as well but Bedford&apos;s arrival simply did not interest fifteenth–century chroniclers.৳ Either the occasion was unusual or there were other such individuals, over the
				centuries, who were similarly honoured but for whose entries the records – along with any mention in chronicle histories– have not survived. Usually the Crown directed the city on the level of entry to be orchestrated for any given entrant, and the city made and paid for arrangements accordingly8 For a coronation entry or other major display
				entry, regularly from 1483 (and at least occasionally before then) a special financial assessment, or tax, would be approved by the city&apos;s
				common council to cover all or part of the citys costs for gifts, entry preparations, or both. From 1483 this ta৲ was regularly in the form of one or more fifteenths – a fifteenth being a fixed amount of money, little changed since the early fourteenth
				century, levied on the citys wards rather than directly on individuals. This form of tax was used for many funding purposes by the city (not only for activities such as major entries), and gave the wards the discretion to spare the poor from
				payment. The companies with halls seem normally to have paid fifteenths usually a fixed sum, per fifteenth, for each company, also largely unchanged
				over the years* in the wards where their halls were located. Sometimes this money was called a benevolence: </p>
			<pb n="7" />
			<p>
				DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS xxviii that is, supposedly a voluntary
				contribution. The coronation tax in 1483, 1485, and 1500 was one fifteenth: for coronations and other major entries in all of 15Ol, 1522, and on to
					1554, it was one–and–a₯half fifteenths: and for the coronation of Elizabeth 1 (1550), the tax was two
				fifteenths. Sometimes the fifteenths were specified to be for more than entry costs and gifts: in 1547, for example, for the costs of the funeral of
				Henry viIl as well as for the coronation of Edward vi, and in 1522, for bowmen for the kings service as well as for the entry of the emperor Charles v.2s Special collectors would be appointed to receive the tax money, and sometimes the citizens
				reluctance to pay was considerable, as in 1533 for th coronation entry of the unpopular Anne Boleyn. Not only London citizens were taxed From at least 1522 on, the records show that all residents in London, non–citizens as well as citizens, were
				required to pay৳ and in 1522, 1533, 1553, and 1554, London residents from various foreign states, such as Venetians and Florentines, were
				specifically obliged either to contribute to the one–and–a₯half fifteenths or to contribute their own constructed pageants to the entries.1 There were important entries into London, other than the major ones already discussed which followed a different pattern. Accession entries– being the immediate movement of a new monarch to take possession of the Tower
				upon accession to the throne – also occurred, and varied somewhat in the initial route they followed: but at least those in the 155os fell into what appears to have been, by then, an expected ceremonial pattern once the monarch had entered through one
				of the city&apos;s gates. The entry point seems in part to have depended, as a practical consideration, on where the new monarch was located at the
				time of acces sion. Elizabeth I, for example, was at Hatfield, to the north of London, and when she reached
				London, she first stayed at the Charterhouse (outside the walls to the northwest) and so entered from the northwest, through Cripplegate. Her
				predecessor Mary had to manoeuvre militarily for the throne, outside London, because of the proclamation of the Lady [ane Grey as queen upon the death of Edward vi: her headquarters were to the northeast: and when an accession entry to the Tower finally
				became possible for her, Mary entered from east of the city, through Aldgate. Both Elizabeth and Mary, however, then made their way to Leadenhall and followed the same basic route: from Leadenhall down Gracechurch Street to Fenchurch Street,
				then east along Fenchurch Street and down Mark Lane to the Tower, and fo* Mary, this entailed going out of her way, from Aldgate west along Aldgate
				Street to Leadenhall before moving south and then east again to the Tower. The route from Leadenhall to the Tower was not only practical (given street widths), but likely also ceremonially customary: from the intersection of Gracechurch Street and
				Fenchurch Street, it was the same route followed (as described above, p xxiv) by all of Henry vi, Henry vil, and Henry viII on the first day of their two–day coronation entries. In 1547, however, Edward vi, although north of the city at his
				accession, perhaps for security reasons entered through Aldgate and turned directly south, along by the city wall and past the Crutched Friars to
				the Tower.€ Accession entries – about which we have very little information before the sixteenth century – appear usually to have involved cheering crowds, speeches, and music, but no pageants until 1603 [when one was prepared, but then not presented after
				all). Pageants would have been precluded by the unpredictability and speed of accessions, and also sometimes by their difficult or </p>
			<pb n="8" />
			<p>
				DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS xxix unusual political circumstances.
				Where accession entries appear in The Records, Appendix I, or both, it is because music is recorded Other kinds of
				welcoming or escorting occasions in London, below the level of the major entries, might involve, on land, one or more of the decoration of the
				streets, the companie: lining the streets, and music. The routes could vary. The king, for example, might require only a welcoming escort when he returned to the city from a journey within England or abroad: or more elaboration might be required even on a
				minor occasion, such as a riding from Westminster to a palace south of the Thames. Different levels of activity and display were also involved in welcomings and escortings by water. The city could prepare quickly for a non–pageantic entry or other escort
				requirement, needing only to order the companies to provide riders (company members, either on horse– back or on
				barges on the water), in full livery, to meet the entrant, and, if required for a land entry, company members to line the streets. Also the
				occupants of buildings along the land–entry route needed little time to hang from their windows any required decorative rich cloths and banners: and barges could be quickly decorated for a water escort. Choristers and instrumental musicians from city
				churches could also be called into service rapidly, as could the city waits (the city&apos;s own paid musicians) and, at least from e 1500, the
				members of the Minstrels Company.S In 1549, for example, when the city had only some forty–eight hours to
				provide a musical welcome for Edward vi riding through the city from the Bridge to Westminster, orders went out for the gravelling of the streets,
				for citizens to hang out cloths, for the companies of Parish Clerks and of Minstrels to provide singers and musicians, and for the waits to play. The children of Paul&apos;s (presumably the cathedral choristers) were also required to turn out.1/ Pageants,
				however, took some time to prepare, although once made they could be stored between occasions and then mended or otherwise renovated when required again.18 One reason for the elaborateness of the pageants prepared for the entry of Xatherine of
				Aragon, arriving in 1501 to marry the heir to England&apos;s throne, Prince Arthur, was that some two years had passed between the conclusion of the
				marriage negotiations and katherines arrival in England. The city&apos;s first record of its preparations is dated I) Novembei 1400: and the entry finally took place on 12 November 1501. When necessary, however, pageants could be prepared
				quickly, as in 1547 when the city had only three weeks from the accession of Edward vi to his coronation entry. In 1533 the coronation entry of Anne
				Boleyn, by both water and land, had to be provided in less than two weeks. Elaborate entries, whether prepared
				slowly or speedily, called upon the expertise not only of designers, craftsmen, and producers but also of scholars and writers. Names of the latter
				occurring in the sixteenth– century records of royal entries include, for example, those of grammarian William Lily (in 1522), playwright/printer[producer [ohn Rastell (in 1522), scholars and writers Nicholas Udall and [ohn Leland (in 1533), and
				playwright and court entertainer ]ohn Heywood (in 1553 and 1554). s. Street processions in relation to royalty
				did not always include royalty itself, and could sometimes, at least in the late thirteenth and early fourteenth centuries, involve portable pageants. In 1208 the Fishmongers paraded to Leadenhall on St Magnus Day, to celebrate a military victory by the
				king against the Scots, with a representation of the saint and with </p>
			<pb n="9" />
			<p>
				DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS xxx gilded sturgeons, silver salmon, and
				knights made to look like luces, all on horses. Other companies may also have had pageants. In 1312713 the Fishmongers rode through the city to Westminster with a ship pageant, to escort the queen from Westminster to Eltham after the birth of Prince Edward./
				The city as a whole might also mark special royal events with street celebrations involving music, dance, and often bonfires, normally on the orders
				of the civic government or the Crown.2s In early 1377, when the city sent mummers to entertain Prince Richard
				(shortly to become Richard II), the mummers created a major moving spectacle as they rode through the city and across the Bridge on their way to the
				royal palace at Rennington, in a civic processional equivalent to the occasional fourteenth–century pre–tournament processions made by the nobility through Cheapside.: Mayoral Oath–Takings and Shrieval Presentations The annual inaugurations of the mayor and of the sheriffs were, from early times, significant occasions of civic
				processional display. For most of the period between c 1200 and 1558, the newly chosen sheriffs swore their oath of office at the Guildhall on 28
				September and took office immediately: then, usually on 30 September, they processed to Westminster to be presented there to the king or to the barons of the Exchequer as his representatives. In the early fourteenth century the city successfully
				argued that no shrieval oath to the Crown was necessary until the sheriffs submitted their accounts at the conclusion of their terms: this collection therefore refers throughout to the sheriffs presentation at Westminster, rather than to their
				oath–taking, even though they normally took an oath in any case. This terminology also provides a useful differentiation between the shrieval
				occasion and the oath–taking of the mayor. The newly chosen mayor swore an oath of office at the Guildhall on 28 October, but did not fully become mayor until processing to Westminster, usually on 2 October, to take his oath to the
				monarch or to the Exchequer barons. The processional route, by the early fifteenth century at least, was from the Guildhall along Cheapside, through
				Newgate, and along Fleet Street to Westminster. Occasionally, when neither the monarch nor the barons were
				available at Westminster, the inauguration procession was instead to the Tower of London, for the sheriffs presentation or the mayor&apos;s
				oath–taking there, before the Constable of the Tower as the monarchs representative. Tower–oath years for both the mayor and the sheriffs, 1208–1558, are listed in Appendix 8.5 Although musicians – above all trumpeters– were probably part of
				both the shrieva and the mayoral processions from very early times, we have no records of processional music until, in the fourteenth century, some of the companies surviving accounts and court minutes begin, since the companies provided much of the
				ceremonial for mayoral and shrieval inaugura tions. The first company record of oath–taking music for the mayor is in 1360, and the first record of such music for a sheriff is in 1383. Both records are from the Goldsmiths early combined accounts and
				minutes (which also record mayoral–procession music in 1377 and in 1388). The Grocers also record minstrels for a sheriff in 1386: and by the 1300s
					the records of the Grocers, Mercers, and Merchant Taylors all show one or more payments to minstrels on the
				mayor&apos;s riding to Westminster, the Mercers also recording minstrels </p>
			<pb n="10" />
			<p>
				DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS xxxi three times with the sheriffs.2 In
				the fifteenth century, the records become more extensive Early on, the processions could be by land, on foot or on horseback, or by water: but by
				the late fourteenth century, processions by land, on horseback, appear to have become the norm Then, in 1389, it
				was determined that, as a cost–cutting measure, the sheriffs should hencefortk no longer ride each year to their Westminster presentations but
				should go either by water or by foot on land –a decision that does not appear to have taken consistent effect until 1435. 5 In 1453, after an initial unsuccessful attempt in 1447, the decision was made that the mayor would regularly go to his Westminster
				oath–taking by water Prior to this, in the late fourteenth and early fifteenth centuries, the mayor is definitely recorded as going by water only
				in 1422: an unusual oath–taking year, because the mayoral inauguration was closely followed by the funeral in
				early November of Henry V. At first, from 1453, the mayor and his entourage went on foot to the Thames to take barges up the river: but in 1501,
				mayor [ohn Shaa began the practice of riding on horseback to the river.€ Either by land or by water, the procession (even when by water, still often called a riding) involved the city&apos;s governors – aldermen, other city officers, senior members of
				companies– in their formal liveries, in set processional order, with banners and with minstrels. S By at least
				the late fifteenth century, some kinds of special displays were in use in the procession on land from the Guildhall to the Thames, and on land
				again when the mayoi returned from Westminster, as in 148I the city prohibited any disguising or pageant, at the mayor&apos;s oath–taking, either from the mayor&apos;s house to the water or from the water to the mayor&apos;s house. : We cannot be sure of
				just what these pageants were, given the common use at this time of the word pageant to mean simply an elaborate display (including elaborate banners, wall hangings, embroidered cushions, and the like, as well as images or wood–and canvas
				constructions): but it is difficult to see why something as usual as banners would have been prohibited. The term disguising also can be variously
				interpreted, but suggests costuming or masking at the least. It is unclear how long the 148I prohibition held: but the traditional belief that portable constructed pageants began to be carried (again€) in mayoral processions generally, in 1535 and in
				1540, is not necessarily correct. This belief has been based on a Drapers record in 1540 which cites, as a precedent for a pageant in the 1540 draper mayor&apos;s oath–taking procession, the carrying of a pageant in 1535 at the inauguration of a mercer
				mayor. Both 1535 and 1540, however, were unusual years in which the mayor swore his oath not at Westminster but at the Tower of London: and the
				Drapers in 1540 cite the 1535 precedent as specifically involving a Tower oath (when the oath–taking procession, from the Guildhall to the Tower and back, was for a shorter distance than to Westminster and back, and without a water component). The 1540
				record (actually two records) thus tells us nothing about the usual situation, before or after 1535, in Westminster oath–taking years. Also, given the elasticity of the use of the term pageant, just what the Drapers 1540 pageant was,
				besides being a portable representation of the Assumption, is unclear, although presumably it – and the Mercers 1535 pageant– was something more
				substantial than a banner or in 1540 no precedent would have been thought necessary. The Drapers sixteenth century Midsummer Watch records provide examples of pageant variety, with representations of the Assumption ranging from elaborate banners to a
				wood–and–canvas construction in </p>
			<pb n="11" />
			<pb n="12" />
			<pb n="13" />
			<pb n="14" />
			<pb n="15" />
			<pb n="16" />
			<pb n="17" />
			<pb n="18" />
			<pb n="19" />
			<pb n="20" />
			<pb n="21" />
			<pb n="22" />
			<pb n="23" />
			<pb n="24" />
			<pb n="25" />
			<pb n="26" />
			<pb n="27" />
			<pb n="28" />
			<pb n="29" />
			<pb n="30" />
			<pb n="31" />
			<pb n="32" />
			<pb n="33" />
			<pb n="34" />
			<pb n="35" />
			<pb n="36" />
			<pb n="37" />
			<pb n="38" />
			<pb n="39" />
			<pb n="40" />
			<pb n="41" />
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
