<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>Ecclesiastical_DramaMusicCeremony</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l1' n='N001'/>Drama, Music, and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l2' n='N002'/>Ceremonial Customs
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l3' n='N003'/>St Paul&apos;s Cathedral
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l4' n='N004'/>St Paul&apos;s great age (it was built in 604) and its size, second only to Winchester Cathedral, make
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l5' n='N005'/>recognition of its importance inescapable. As Derek keene points out, however, it is essentially
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l6' n='N006'/>the cathedral&apos;s association with London, the richest city in the land and increasingly the seat
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l7' n='N007'/>of national power, that accounts for its massive presence in the events of English history and
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l8' n='N008'/>in the imaginations of contemporaries as well. Its association with drama and dramatic ceremo*
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l9' n='N009'/>nial traced in this collection was an element in St Paul&apos;s cultural centrality, and that aspect of
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l10' n='N010'/>the cathedral&apos;s life is visible from the twelfth century through the early modern period
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l11' n='N011'/>PAULS SONG.SCHOOL AND CHORISTERS
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l12' n='N012'/>Writing on secular cathedrals Rathleen Edwards says that from early times, in important centres,
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l13' n='N013'/>a school of grammar under the chancellor and a song–school under the precentor were separately
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l14' n='N014'/>established.: More recently Roger Bowers has suggested that in monasteries the earliest almonry
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l15' n='N015'/>schools were established ... simply as grammar schools –of which a sub–group of pupils began
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l16' n='N016'/>to constitute a Lady Chapel choir... long after the original foundation.8 At St Paul&apos;s it seems
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l17' n='N017'/>not to have been until the evolution of the almoner&apos;s office in the late twelfth century that
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l18' n='N018'/>singing boys, their welfare and their maintenance, became part of the almoner&apos;s charitable
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l19' n='N019'/>responsibilities.: The first mention of these almonry boys is found in the statutes of Dean
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l20' n='N020'/>Ralph de Diceto, c 1180–1200: they enjoin humility on the choristers who may compare
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l21' n='N021'/>unfavourably the rich food of feasts, eaten elsewhere, with the humble food they regularly
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l22' n='N022'/>receive from their master in the almonry (see p 14). Intellectual responsibility for the boys is
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l23' n='N023'/>clear in the 13287/D will of almoner William Tolleshunt, which leaves Priscian&apos;s grammar
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l24' n='N024'/>texts, Isidores E૱y₱¢l¢₩€$£, and boy bishop sermons– perhaps his own compositions – ad
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l25' n='N025'/>vsum fructuum pueror¥₱ ... degenciu₱ (to the use (and) enjoyment of the boys dwelling
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l26' n='N026'/>in the almonry (see pp 18–10).: Thus when Sebastian Westcotes 1582 will revealed that his
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l27' n='N027'/>ten choristers slept in five almonry beds it was only the latest demonstration of the long–standing
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l28' n='N028'/>relation between almoner and choristers (see p 153). It is this relationship that will be illustrated
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l29' n='N029'/>here: St Paul&apos;s grammar school will be included in a later REED collection.
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l30' n='N030'/>The earliest evidence for plays by persons associated with St Paul&apos;s comes from an eighteenth–
				<lb facs='#facs_1_r1l31' n='N031'/>century editor. In 1738 Italian actor, playwright, and historian Luigi Riccoboni (c 1676–1753)
			</p>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l2' n='N002'/>xviii
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l3' n='N003'/>published his R£fl£x€¢₭৳ h€৳૱¢৲€q¥£৳ et critiq¥£৳ s¥r les differe₭s theatres de IEu৲op£, which was
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l4' n='N004'/>translated and published in London three years later in 1741. Riccoboni&apos;s source was a book
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l5' n='N005'/>he called The Antiquities of London whose account noted that under Richard II, who reignec
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l6' n='N006'/>in the Tear 1378, the clergy and scholars of Paul&apos;s school petitioned the king to prohibit a
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l7' n='N007'/>Company of unexpert People from presenting the History of the Old Testament, to the
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l8' n='N008'/>great Prejudice of the said Clergy, who have been at great Charge and Expence, in order to
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l9' n='N009'/>represent it publickly at Christmas (see p 10). S
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l10' n='N010'/>Riccoboni&apos;s quotation from the unknown Antiquities mentions the date 1378 but it seems
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l11' n='N011'/>unlikely that this date is to be associated with the plays: it is merely an approximation of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l12' n='N012'/>Richard&apos;s regnal years (1377–00). Hence this lost petition might come from any time in Richard&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l13' n='N013'/>reign. Cathedral Christmas–time plays were often associated with the feast of fools, boy bishops:
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l14' n='N014'/>and general misrule, and it is possible that St Pauls, like many great European cathedrals, present.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l15' n='N015'/>ed an Ordo Prophetarum at Christmas. These prophet plays, incorporating the words of such
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l16' n='N016'/>witnesses as Moses, ]eremiah, Isaiah, and Daniel, were strongly tied to the Old Testament
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l17' n='N017'/>readings of the Advent liturgy. They were staged at the cathedrals of Arles, Salerno, Limoges,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l18' n='N018'/>Tours, Laon, and Rouen, and at the last two, contained roles for boys as well as men. At Laon
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l19' n='N019'/>Daniel was played by an adolescens, and a puer figures in the Balaam episode, while at Rouen
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l20' n='N020'/>Shadrach, Mishach, and Abednego were also boys./ If such a play had been given in London
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l21' n='N021'/>as well, it would constitute the first indication we have of public acting by Paul&apos;s choristers.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l22' n='N022'/>As to the other play in this account it is doubtful that the reference to unexpert People who
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l23' n='N023'/>challenged the cathedral play was intended to describe the famous contemporary performances
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l24' n='N024'/>by the parish clerks of London, presented between summers 1384 and 1410/1I at Skinner&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l25' n='N025'/>Well (see p 20 for an additional appearance). These summer plays, given over several days,
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l26' n='N026'/>depicted Christ&apos;s Passion and the creation of the world.s Although at least the latter of these
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l27' n='N027'/>subjects could be the History of the Old Testament that the Antiquities refers to, the calendar
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l28' n='N028'/>distance makes conflict between Paul&apos;s Christmas plays and the clerks summer ones unlikely.
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l29' n='N029'/>]ohn Redford
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l30' n='N030'/>Plays at Paul&apos;s, if they existed, have left no trace from the end of the fourteenth century until
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l31' n='N031'/>the early sixteenth century, when ]ohn Redford became almoner and master of the choristers
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l32' n='N032'/>in the residential song–school based in the almoner&apos;s house. Probably Redford&apos;s sister Margaret
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l33' n='N033'/>Coxe served as domestic manager for the choristers there. In 1547 brother and sister were
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l34' n='N034'/>living together since ]ohn&apos;s will describes Margaret as now being w€t฿ me and leaves her my
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l35' n='N035'/>best bedstede in my Chambr£ whiche I now occupie and lye vpon and the third fetherbed
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l36' n='N036'/>with thappurtenances whiche she lyeth vpon herself (see p 110). A lease granted her in 1555
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l37' n='N037'/>after Redford&apos;s death (see pp 129–32) identifies her dwelling then as the southern portion of
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l38' n='N038'/>the almoner&apos;s house, a property in the almoner&apos;s gist, as is shown by the identity of its previous
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l39' n='N039'/>tenant, William Hickman, presumably a relative of earlier almoner Thomas Hickman. The
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l40' n='N040'/>Coxe lease specifies that in the property a room shall be reserved next to the almonry to be
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l41' n='N041'/>used as an infirmary for the choristers, and stairs from the room to the well₯house were to be
				<lb facs='#facs_2_r1l42' n='N042'/>newly built. Margaret Coxe&apos;s responsibility for the boys is implied: the relationship is further
			</p>
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l2' n='N002'/>xix
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l3' n='N003'/>affirmed by her will bequest of 3s 4d to each of the choristers and to Rowe, perhaps another
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l4' n='N004'/>member of the almoner&apos;s staff.1
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l5' n='N005'/>The survival of [ohn Redford&apos;s play W€૱ $₭₨ Sc€£₭₯£ has generally been taken to imply its
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l6' n='N006'/>performance by the chapel boys. The play is undated as is the beginning of Redford&apos;s period
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l7' n='N007'/>of service as St Paul&apos;s almoner and master of the choristers. The composition of the play
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l8' n='N008'/>and the inception of the position have both been pinned to 1534, since in that year Thomas
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l9' n='N009'/>Hickman died. Hickman is identified as maister of the queresters in 1527, the next year he
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l10' n='N010'/>is called Almener, and in his 1534 will he describes himself as subdean. This evidence led
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l11' n='N011'/>Trevor Lennam to suggest that Hickman as almoner seemingly relinquished his post to become
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l12' n='N012'/>subdean probably between 1528 and 1530, although he provides no reference and Hickman
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l13' n='N013'/>is not in Hennessy&apos;s list of cathedral subdeans.: If Redford did become almoner sometime
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l14' n='N014'/>after 1528, five or six years earlier than previously thought, the dating of W€૱ $₭₨ Sc€£₭₯£, as
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l15' n='N015'/>also of his two surviving interlude fragments, might fall anywhere between 1528 and his death
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l16' n='N016'/>in 1547.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l17' n='N017'/>The circumstances of the play&apos;s performance however are unknown– though its epilogue
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l18' n='N018'/>shows it was acted before a king, queen, and court. In March 1537/8 ]ohn Heywood, the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l19' n='N019'/>playwright and musician, received a payment of 40s for performing an interlude with his
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l20' n='N020'/>Children before Princess Mary. Scholars have wondered whether the children might have
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l21' n='N021'/>been the boys of Paul&apos;s under Redford&apos;s mastership, since Heywood and Redford&apos;s successor,
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l22' n='N022'/>Sebastian Westcote, together produced royal performances with the choristers in 1551 and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l23' n='N023'/>1550.1 Further the unique surviving manuscript of Redford&apos;s W€૱ $₭₨ Sc€£₭₯£, BL: Additional
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l24' n='N024'/>MS 15233, also contains ten poems written by Heywood. The manuscript has been called
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l25' n='N025'/>the work of a group of friends connected in one way or another with ]ohn Redford&apos;s choii
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l26' n='N026'/>school at St. Paul&apos;s, and A.W. Reed suggested it was the song–book that Sebastian Westcote
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l27' n='N027'/>presented to Cueen Mary at New Tear&apos;s 1557.1s Some of Heywood&apos;s songs in it may have
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l28' n='N028'/>been written for Paul&apos;s plays. For instance the song Be merye, frendes concludes, Bee meery
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l29' n='N029'/>in God, saynt Powle sayth playne.16 Reed thought Heywood&apos;s role with the Paul&apos;s boys
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l30' n='N030'/>was to manage, collaborate, or advise: Streitberger viewed him as a producer of occasional
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l31' n='N031'/>entertainment./ Both believed Heywood exercised this function under Redford as well as
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l32' n='N032'/>more visibly under Westcote.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l33' n='N033'/>If Redford&apos;s mastership of the choristers did begin in the 1520s, that decade also saw the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l34' n='N034'/>performance of at least three Latin plays by the boys of St Paul&apos;s grammar school under theii
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l35' n='N035'/>master [ohn Rightwise.8 Grammar school playing continued throughout the century as did
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l36' n='N036'/>that of the choristers. This is the first point, roughly between 1527 and 1534, at which we
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l37' n='N037'/>can view the coexistence of two performing childrens troupes at Paul&apos;s.
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l38' n='N038'/>Redford would necessarily have been involved too in the choristers employment by the
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l39' n='N039'/>cathedral&apos;s lay guild of the Holy Name of [esus. Founded in 1450 and reorganized in 1507
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l40' n='N040'/>with statutes by Dean Colet, the guild met in the Crowdes (shrouds) or cathedral crypt and
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l41' n='N041'/>employed cathedral staff– choristers and a vicar choral– to sing the ]esus antiphon or salve
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l42' n='N042'/>each evening. Though this activity was entirely liturgical the publicity for the feast and its
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l43' n='N043'/>bonfire was secular: garlanded waits in ]esus liveries carried banners and performed musical
				<lb facs='#facs_3_r1l44' n='N044'/>announcements throughout the city (see Records, c 1506–35). 1
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l2' n='N002'/>xx
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l3' n='N003'/>Sebastian Westcote
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l4' n='N004'/>Though Redford&apos;s work as dramatist is obscure we know much more about what his successor
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l5' n='N005'/>(and his will&apos;s executor), Sebastian Westcote, did in the almoner&apos;s position. The boys extensive
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l6' n='N006'/>court appearances under Westcote will not be discussed here though their record is remarkable.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l7' n='N007'/>They performed for thirty years, from 1551 to 1581, and presented before Elizabeth more
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l8' n='N008'/>frequently than any other troupe, playing as well before the city companies, including the
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l9' n='N009'/>Drapers and the Merchant Taylors.2 The focus here however will be on Westcotes important
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l10' n='N010'/>inception of commercial production, the location of the theatre in which he offered those plays
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l11' n='N011'/>and the thirty years, roughly 1575 to 1606, when Paul&apos;s boys performed not only in their
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l12' n='N012'/>traditional roles as liturgical singers and court entertainers, but as actors in the developing
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l13' n='N013'/>world of London&apos;s commercial theatre.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l14' n='N014'/>In fall or winter 1576 Richard Farrant, master of the Windsor Chapel children and deputy
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l15' n='N015'/>master of the Chapel Royal, began presenting boys plays at Blackfriars, the former Dominican
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l16' n='N016'/>house.2/ It was a significant theatrical moment yet it had been slightly anticipated. Boys
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l17' n='N017'/>theatre for which admission was charged had at this point been offered twice, in spring 1573
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l18' n='N018'/>and 1574 by Richard Mulcaster and his students at the Merchant Taylors school. It had been
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l19' n='N019'/>extremely popular: because the paying crowd had been both numerous and aggressive, company
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l20' n='N020'/>officers and their friends had been unable to get seats, and as a consequence, the Merchant
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l21' n='N021'/>Taylors had resolved to suspend performance in their hall.€: A bit later, perhaps in late 1574 or
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l22' n='N022'/>early 1575, a second set of boys, playing in St Pauls almonry house, began to charge admission.
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l23' n='N023'/>The witnesses were the London court of Aldermen, who noted in December 1575 that Sebastian
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l24' n='N024'/>Westcote had been presenting playes and resorte of the people to great gaine and asked the cit₺
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l25' n='N025'/>registrar to inform the cathedral dean (see Appendix 2, pp 227–8). Both school performances
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l26' n='N026'/>preceded the third children&apos;s company opening at Blackfriars: Westcote seems to have anticipated
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l27' n='N027'/>Farrant but followed Mulcaster
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l28' n='N028'/>The explanation that these performances were offered as rehearsals for court appearances may
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l29' n='N029'/>be slightly dubious: both Mulcaster&apos;s and Westcotes boys (and of course the Chapel Royal) did
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l30' n='N030'/>perform at court but charging a fee to their general audience seems to undercut the rationale
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l31' n='N031'/>of preparation for a royal appearance, and might better be considered to constitute commercial
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l32' n='N032'/>theatre.2 Thus these three private theatres, all the work of choirmaster and schoolmaster
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l33' n='N033'/>entrepreneurs and their children, anticipated by just a little the coming of the public theatres:
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l34' n='N034'/>Newington Butts (1575 or 1576) and the Theatre (1576).
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l35' n='N035'/>Paul&apos;s Boys after Westcote
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l36' n='N036'/>After Westcotes death in April 1582 mentions in three leases of Thomas Bendbowe as almoner
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l37' n='N037'/>(1582 and 1583) provide a brief interregnum. Chambers conjectured a temporary alternation
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l38' n='N038'/>of three boys companies (Chapel children, earl of Oxford&apos;s children, Pauls children) at Blackfriars
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l39' n='N039'/>in 158374.2 If this were so it would have happened under Bendbowe&apos;s mastership. By May
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l40' n='N040'/>1584, however, plays at Blackfriars had stopped since William More, in one of many lawsuits
				<lb facs='#facs_4_r1l41' n='N041'/>about ownership, possession, and rent of Blackfriars, had seized the building and had everyone
			</p>
			<pb n='5'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxi
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l3' n='N003'/>evicted.2 Whether the appointment on 22 May 1584 of Thomas Giles as almoner had anything
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l4' n='N004'/>to do with these circumstances can only be conjectured
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l5' n='N005'/>Onder Giles the boys appeared at court in the seasons 1587–8, 1588–0, and 1580–00,
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l6' n='N006'/>after which there was a hiatus until 1500. Two reasons have been offered for their absence.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l7' n='N007'/>Involvement in the Martin Marprelate controversy, which criticized the governance of the church
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l8' n='N008'/>of England, in the absence of substantial information has seemed a somewhat unsatisfactory
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l9' n='N009'/>explanation. Richard Dutton has recently argued instead that they fell out of fashion and favori€
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l10' n='N010'/>Their master Giles had been noted as ill on 23 April 1508 at the episcopal visitation, when
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l11' n='N011'/>criticism of the boys dress and its cleanliness had been heard, perhaps due to Giles illness (see
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l12' n='N012'/>p 166).2 About two weeks later on II May his successor, Edward Pearce, was asked to assume
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l13' n='N013'/>the position (see pp 168–70). Presumably he was acting master until Giles death, early in
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l14' n='N014'/>]uly 1600 (he was buried 4 [uly 1600).2
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l15' n='N015'/>Pearce formally relinquished his position in the Chapel Royal in August of that year (see
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l16' n='N016'/>p 172). A number of Paul&apos;s plays may have been produced in late 1500 and early 1600 and if
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l17' n='N017'/>these datings are correct it was Pearce who was responsible. He was certainly involved in the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l18' n='N018'/>production of George Chapman&apos;s lost play, The Old ]oiner of Aldgate, though his statements
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l19' n='N019'/>in the 1603 Star Chamber suit attempt to give a different impression (see pp 200–2).2 A
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l20' n='N020'/>succes de scandale, this sexual farce had not only been played by Paul&apos;s boys, but one of the
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l21' n='N021'/>defendants was a parishioner of St Gregory by St Paul&apos;s, another defendant was a bookbinder
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l22' n='N022'/>and stationer in the churchyard, and a former rector of St Gregory had attempted to intervene.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l23' n='N023'/>Pearce was accused of buying the play from Chapman, which he contemptuously denied. After
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l24' n='N024'/>several reversals a final judgment was awarded in November 1604. When on 2 December 1604
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l25' n='N025'/>Pearce assaulted Thomas Woodford, the man who actually bought the play for Paul&apos;s perform.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l26' n='N026'/>ance, it was probably due to his anger at being involved in this complicated, amusing, and
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l27' n='N027'/>shabby affair (see pp229–31). Those satirized belonged to the centrecity world of the cathedral
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l28' n='N028'/>precinct and its environs, and the narrative shows the power of an appeal to a neighbourhood
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l29' n='N029'/>audience, since identification of its barely disguised characters would have been an easy matter
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l30' n='N030'/>for those living nearby.
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l31' n='N031'/>The boys second incarnation lasted from 1500 to summer 1606, when their performance in
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l32' n='N032'/>]uly before king [ames seems to have been their last. A curious postscript survives in a lawsuii
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l33' n='N033'/>of 1610, which revealed that Philip Rosseter, then one of the managers of the children&apos;s company
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l34' n='N034'/>playing at the Whitefriars, had paid Edward Pearce a dead rent of E20 to keep St Paul&apos;s theatre
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l35' n='N035'/>dark. The king&apos;s men, who were playing at Blackfriars and who considered that they benefited
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l36' n='N036'/>also, later contributed half of the sum (see pp 265–6). The payment was probably made in
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l37' n='N037'/>mid–1600, and Hillebrand believed the bribe suggested that Pearce at the time might have been
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l38' n='N038'/>considering re–opening Paul&apos;s theatre. s0
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l39' n='N039'/>Location of the Theatre
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l40' n='N040'/>The site of St Paul&apos;s theatre has been much discussed since contemporary references to it are
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l41' n='N041'/>vague– for instance the 1610 lawsuit that referred to it as neere St Pawles Church (see p 205).
				<lb facs='#facs_5_r1l42' n='N042'/>The earliest of these descriptions comes from a piece of evidence now lost, produced by Bishop
			</p>
			<pb n='6'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxii
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l3' n='N003'/>Richard Bancroft&apos;s visitation of Paul&apos;s in 1508. The visitation included testimony that the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l4' n='N004'/>house of [ohn Gyles was partly formed by St. Paul&apos;s, and was Tately used for a playhouse.
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l5' n='N005'/>This visitation document does not survive and we have only a summary made by [. R Malcolm
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l6' n='N006'/>in his 1803 compilation on the city, L¢₭₨€₭€¥₱ Re₨€v€v¥₱ (p 164). His Tohn Gyles has univer
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l7' n='N007'/>sally been taken as an error for Thomas Giles, almoner and master of the choristers in 1508
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l8' n='N008'/>A lawsuit in 1603 provided a second piece of evidence. Here the theatre was described as a
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l9' n='N009'/>pryvate house of a longe tyme Reepte vsed &amp; accustomede for y$t purpose – that is, for playing
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l10' n='N010'/>(see p 188). A third reference comes from Edmund Howes revision of [ohn Stow&apos;s A₭₭$₮৳
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l11' n='N011'/>produced in the years 1628 to 1631. Howes listed a variety of theatrical structures both purpose
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l12' n='N012'/>built and intended originally for other uses, and among the latter he included S. Paules singing
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l13' n='N013'/>Schoole (see p 212).8 Finally in 1664 the playwright Richard Flecknoe attached a short history
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l14' n='N014'/>of English theatre to his play L¢v£৳ R€₭₩₨¢₱. In Elizabeths reign, he said, the children of St
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l15' n='N015'/>Paul&apos;s acted plays behinde the Convocation–house in P$¥₮৳.252
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l16' n='N016'/>Strenuous efforts have been made to locate a building that would fit all these descriptions
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l17' n='N017'/>but they have been largely unsuccessful. E.k. Chambers thought the boys song–school was
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l18' n='N018'/>perhaps in the church of St Gregory within the cathedral precinct, or some other neighbourhood
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l19' n='N019'/>building. Harold Hillebrand concluded that the theatre was probably in the almoner&apos;s house
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l20' n='N020'/>but did not locate it.2 Almost in passing William A. Armstrong noted correctly that Westcote
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l21' n='N021'/>began in 1575 to stage plays in the Almonry House, a small building behind Convocation
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l22' n='N022'/>House. 25 Lennam, whose judgment was so often right, was misled by the traditional assignment
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l23' n='N023'/>of the almonry house to the north churchyard and hence believed one of the almoner&apos;s various
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l24' n='N024'/>rental properties in that area might be the theatre&apos;s site.S Reavley Gair maintained that the plays
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l25' n='N025'/>were given in a house mentioned in Bishop Bancrofts 1508 visitation as built by a Mr Haydon
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l26' n='N026'/>and located in the northwest corner of the chapter house precinct, and his conclusions have
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l27' n='N027'/>been most generally accepted (though criticized by Michael Shapiro who believed the building
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l28' n='N028'/>was likely to have been a small banqueting hall fitted out as a theatre).
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l29' n='N029'/>It was not until the almost simultaneous publication of research by Herbert Berry in 2000
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l30' n='N030'/>and Roger Bowers in 200I (with more detail provided by Berry in 200l) that general agreement
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l31' n='N031'/>was reached, not only on identification of the almoner&apos;s house as the venue for the theatre, but
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l32' n='N032'/>on the location of that building: standing on the south side of the cathedral, adjacent to the
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l33' n='N033'/>chapter houses western precinct wall.€ This conclusion agrees with the early references: it posits
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l34' n='N034'/>a long north–south building, parallel to the lane running south out of the little south door of
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l35' n='N035'/>Pauls. Details of its location are provided by St Paul&apos;s leases of 1440/1, 1526, 1555, 1582, 1583
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l36' n='N036'/>and 1506 (see pp 25–7, 65, 125–32, 145–52, 156–8, 161–4).2 What may be the earliest
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l37' n='N037'/>reference to the almoner&apos;s residence is found in a 1315 lease to almoner William Tolleshunt
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l38' n='N038'/>of a small piece of land belonging to the rector of St Mary Staining Lane on the south side o*
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l39' n='N039'/>the cathedral.*
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l40' n='N040'/>Berry imagines the playgoer&apos;s route: walking north toward the cathedral along the lane leading
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l41' n='N041'/>from the street called St Paul&apos;s Churchyard, turning right through a door in the almonry near
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l42' n='N042'/>the south wall of St Paul&apos;s, and climbing a flight of stairs to a hall, the boys rehearsal room,
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l43' n='N043'/>and theatre. Estimates of its size are not dissimilar: Bowers conjectures that the hall might
				<lb facs='#facs_6_r1l44' n='N044'/>have been 40 6 x 23, while Berry, less precisely, says it might have been 20 wide and much
			</p>
			<pb n='7'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxiii
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l3' n='N003'/>longer.2/ From two sources we know the plays were given in the late afternoon. William Percy
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l4' n='N004'/>(d. 1648), an aristocratic amateur playwright, provides alternative stage directions in the manu*
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l5' n='N005'/>script of his plays, instructing the master of Paul&apos;s children to omit some songs if the plays
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l6' n='N006'/>should be produced there rather than at court, since the children were not to begin before
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l7' n='N007'/>Foure after Prayers And the gates of Powles shutting at six (see Appendix S, p 201). Later, in
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l8' n='N008'/>1664, Richard Flecknoe says, on Week–dayes after Vespers, both the Children of the Chappel
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l9' n='N009'/>and St. P$¥ls, Acted Playes.22 Bequests in Sebastian Westcotes will to Shepard that kepeth the
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l10' n='N010'/>dore at Playes and to Pole the keper of the gate show that there were two sets of barriers for
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l11' n='N011'/>playgoers to traverse, the gate in question perhaps being the one on the west side of the cathedral
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l12' n='N012'/>precinct leading into Ludgate (see p 156).
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l13' n='N013'/>Poaching
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l14' n='N014'/>Writs of impressment allowing chapel masters to draft boys for their choirs are visible from
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l15' n='N015'/>the opening of the fifteenth century: Hillebrand cites an example from 1420, issued to ]ohn
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l16' n='N016'/>Pyamour, clerk of the Chapel Royal.1 Such permissions, given to royal choirmasters, were both
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l17' n='N017'/>frequent and unremarkable: for instance Richard III in 1484 gave a similar warrant to ]ohn
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l18' n='N018'/>Melyonik of the Chapel Royal, to impress anywhere but at Windsor.1 Perhaps equally con–
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l19' n='N019'/>ventional, since almost equally early, was the practice of stealing the best voices from these
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l20' n='N020'/>children&apos;s choirs. Hillebrand noted a document dated 9 ]uly 1453 in which the dean of Paul&apos;s,
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l21' n='N021'/>Thomas Lisieux, requested assurance that neither the dean of the Chapel Royal nor any other
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l22' n='N022'/>king&apos;s minister or officer should take any chorister or minister from the cathedral. Roger
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l23' n='N023'/>Bowers has provided a variety of early sixteenth–century examples both of this practice and of
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l24' n='N024'/>attempts at its prevention. In 1514 the dean and chapter of Lincoln Cathedral secured royal
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l25' n='N025'/>letters granting their choir exemption from poaching (except by the Chapel Royal) and in
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l26' n='N026'/>1523–4 the choir of St Botolphs, Boston (Lincolnshire), paid 26s 8d to be spared the impress*
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l27' n='N027'/>ment of their singing boys for Cardinal Wolsey&apos;s chapel.৳
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l28' n='N028'/>Thus the permissions to take up boys for St Paul&apos;s choir, received both by Sebastian Westcote
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l29' n='N029'/>and his successor, Thomas Giles, represent conventional practice (see pp 135, 160) –as does
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l30' n='N030'/>the poaching of one of Westcotes boys in 1575, revealed by a note in the acts of the privy
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l31' n='N031'/>council (see p 148). The fullest account of this practice however comes from a Star Chamber
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l32' n='N032'/>suit brought in December 1601. In it Henry Clifton, father of an impressed boy, charged that
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l33' n='N033'/>not only his son but also seven other named boys had been commandeered to be part of the
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l34' n='N034'/>new Blackfriars acting company. Although at least two of the boys had been Paul&apos;s choristers,
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l35' n='N035'/>Clifton charged that all had been impressed for their acting ability and were in noe way able
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l36' n='N036'/>or fitt for singinge (see p 174). The historic practice of stealing boy musicians for distinguished
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l37' n='N037'/>choirs seems thus to underlie the later, similar theft of boy actors.
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l38' n='N038'/>Parishes
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l39' n='N039'/>Parish records in London survive abundantly and reveal a rich variety of drama.s The capital is
				<lb facs='#facs_7_r1l40' n='N040'/>traditionally said to have had 108 parish churches before the Great Fire. That listing, followed
			</p>
			<pb n='8'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxiv
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l3' n='N003'/>here, incorporates those parishes lying in both London and Middlesex: St Andrew Holborn
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l4' n='N004'/>St Botolph without Aldgate, St Botolph without Bishopsgate, St Dunstan in the West, St Giles
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l5' n='N005'/>without Cripplegate, and St Sepulchre (see Appendix 7).2 London&apos;s population in its twenty*
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l6' n='N006'/>five wards has been discussed above (see pp xiii–xiv). An important element in assessing the
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l7' n='N007'/>citys size, the 1540 responses to the Chantries Act, provides figures on parish size as well. At
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l8' n='N008'/>mid–century the majority had 200 to 400 communicants while the outlying parishes were
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l9' n='N009'/>considerably larger.
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l10' n='N010'/>Financial records earlier than 1642– churchwardens accounts and vestry minutes – exist for
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l11' n='N011'/>eighty out of the capital&apos;s 108 churches, roughly three–quarters of London&apos;s parishes.€ Our
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l12' n='N012'/>knowledge of parish drama however is dependent on the earliest of the parish records since with
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l13' n='N013'/>the accession of Elizabeth the traditional, religiously based dramatic practices were no longer
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l14' n='N014'/>part of parish life in London. After 1558 parish boy bishops, hocking, maying, and Palm Sunday
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l15' n='N015'/>drama disappear, and the only witness of parish–based plays are two rentals of parish space:
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l16' n='N016'/>St Xatharine Cree&apos;s churchyard in 1565 and St Botolph without Aldersgate&apos;s former fraternity
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l17' n='N017'/>hall for a decade ending in 1567.
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l18' n='N018'/>It is thus in a smaller, earlier group of records that we must look for traces of ceremony and
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l19' n='N019'/>theatre: in the pre–Elizabethan accounts surviving in twenty–seven parishes –one quarter of
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l20' n='N020'/>London&apos;s total. Supplementary information is found in the Edwardian inventories produced
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l21' n='N021'/>by most parishes when, between 1548 and 1552, they sold their vestments and other posses*
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l22' n='N022'/>sions connected with religious ceremonial.2 Forty–three such inventories survive, from close
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l23' n='N023'/>to half the 108 London parishes, and twenty–nine come from churches where we do not have
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l24' n='N024'/>the more complete record provided by accounts. The conclusion is inescapable: if we had
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l25' n='N025'/>accounts from the parishes where we have only lists of goods, our notion of parish playing
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l26' n='N026'/>would be realistically fuller.
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l27' n='N027'/>A group of thirteen parishes whose records originate before I500 provides the earliest glimpse
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l28' n='N028'/>of parish life. The first record comes from St Mary at Hill around 1422 followed by St Petei
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l29' n='N029'/>Westcheap in 1431. Five parishes have records from the 1450s (All Hallows Barking and St
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l30' n='N030'/>Nicholas Shambles, 1452: St Andrew Hubbard, 1454: All Hallows on London Wall and St
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l31' n='N031'/>Michael Cornhill, 1455), while the records of the remaining six begin at various points in the
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l32' n='N032'/>second half of the century (All Hallows Staining, St Botolph without Aldersgate, St Dunstan
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l33' n='N033'/>in the East, St Martin Orgar, St Stephen Coleman Street, and St Stephen Walbrook).
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l34' n='N034'/>Several quasi–dramatic forms appear in these pre–1500 accounts and continue later, in other
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l35' n='N035'/>records. The boy bishop is found almost from the beginning of the accounts in 1431 and 1432
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l36' n='N036'/>and earlier a child&apos;s mitre is listed in an isolated inventory of around 1400 from St Martin
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l37' n='N037'/>Ludgate. The most substantial evidence of this immensely popular practice however appears
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l38' n='N038'/>not in the parish accounts but in the Edwardian inventories descriptions of small copes and
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l39' n='N039'/>mitres. In addition a dramatized, symbolic liturgy of Palm Sunday involved the rental of wigs
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l40' n='N040'/>and costumes and the construction of platforms for parishioners who played the prophets
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l41' n='N041'/>celebrating Christ&apos;s ]erusalem entry. Hocking (1457) and maying (1458) each occur in six
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l42' n='N042'/>parishes. Display and festivity were provided as well by portable pageants used as sets for both
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l43' n='N043'/>human and artificial figures, by constructed figures of giants, and by parish–owned stores
				<lb facs='#facs_8_r1l44' n='N044'/>of costumes.
			</p>
			<pb n='9'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxv
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l3' n='N003'/>THE LITURGICAL CALENDAR
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l4' n='N004'/>The Boy Bishop
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l5' n='N005'/>The liturgical year&apos;s first dramatic celebration offered a ceremony of inversion centred around
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l6' n='N006'/>the boy bishop, as costumed choirboys took the places of their masters on either St Nicholas
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l7' n='N007'/>Day (6 December) or Holy Innocents Day (28 December). The feast permitted reversal of
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l8' n='N008'/>the familiar clerical hierarchy, licensed some degree of disorder, and encouraged recognition
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l9' n='N009'/>of skill in music and Latinity– perhaps the reason ]ohn Colet encouraged the practice in his
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l10' n='N010'/>statutes for St Paul&apos;s school.S By Colet&apos;s time the ceremony had been established at the cathedra
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l11' n='N011'/>for over 300 years, since it is mentioned in the statutes of Ralph de Diceto, c 1180–1200 (see
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l12' n='N012'/>p 14). Its earliest material witness is the white mitre given to the cathedral&apos;s boy bishop by
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l13' n='N013'/>]ohn Belemeyns, a prebendary, and listed in an inventory of 1245 (see p 15).5 The same
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l14' n='N014'/>inventory also mentions twenty–eight boys copes and mantles, designated for the feasts of
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l15' n='N015'/>fools and Innocents.
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l16' n='N016'/>The boy bishop ceremonies originated in cathedrals and monasteries, their mocking inversions
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l17' n='N017'/>springing out of a close living community of men and boys. Tet these practices are also very
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l18' n='N018'/>widely found in London parishes. Fifty–two parishes, about half of London&apos;s total, possessed
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l19' n='N019'/>the vestments necessary for the boy bishop observance. Often the record is unequivocal, as with
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l20' n='N020'/>the ownership of a mitre, but even if the less clear records are removed (copes for children might
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l21' n='N021'/>indicate only the presence of a boys choir) thirty–seven parishes remain –a third of the total of
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l22' n='N022'/>108 London parishes.2 Considering the losses of documents the number was almost certainly
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l23' n='N023'/>higher and perhaps as many as two₯thirds of London parishioners enjoyed these Christmas₯time
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l24' n='N024'/>revels in their churches and neighbourhoods.
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l25' n='N025'/>The earliest parish record comes from a St Martin Ludgate inventory around 1400, about
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l26' n='N026'/>a century and a half after Belemeyns gift to Paul&apos;s boy bishop and perhaps two centuries after
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l27' n='N027'/>de Diceto&apos;s statutes. It lists two albs, two amices, and a cope for St Nicholas, plus a mitre
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l28' n='N028'/>garnished with l£૱૱res de le৳¥s &amp; Marie de perill (see p 23). In 1431 and 1432 St Peter
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l29' n='N029'/>Westcheap and St Mary at Hill list similar items: two children&apos;s copes and a mitre at the latter,
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l30' n='N030'/>the same at the former, plus a chasuble, tunicle, and three albs for children (see p 24). Copes
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l31' n='N031'/>or mantles were widely used as choir habits on feasts, both by men and boys, and were worn
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l32' n='N032'/>by clergy and laity:૱ At St Martin the two childrens albs probably dressed the boys accompanying
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l33' n='N033'/>the bishop, who wore the cope and the pearl mitre. Taken together St Martin&apos;s possessions,
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l34' n='N034'/>like the cathedral&apos;s inventory, allow us to see a liturgically costumed boy bishop escorted by
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l35' n='N035'/>other costumed children. The most continuous fifteenth–century references to this custom come
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l36' n='N036'/>from St Mary at Hill (1431–2, 1485–6, 1480–00) and St Nicholas Shambles (1468–0,
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l37' n='N037'/>1476–3, c 1400).
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l38' n='N038'/>Red was frequently the colour for these garments, since although St Nicholas was not a martyr,
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l39' n='N039'/>the Holy Innocents were. St Michael Cornhill owned a vestment somtyme for .S. Nycolas
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l40' n='N040'/>byshop for A chyld of red velvet w€t฿ orfews of ye apostles (see p 108). Mitres abound. Indeec
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l41' n='N041'/>it is possible to trace the three types distinguished by liturgists: the precious mitre (St Sepulchre
				<lb facs='#facs_9_r1l42' n='N042'/>had one garnished with silver, pearls, and stones): the golden mitre (St Antholin&apos;s was made
			</p>
			<pb n='10'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxvi
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l3' n='N003'/>of needlework of gold and one of St Peter Westcheap&apos;s three mitres was cloth of silver): and
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l4' n='N004'/>the simple mitre (St Peter Cornhill had one of white silk).
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l5' n='N005'/>The parish–by–parish sale of religious goods between 1548 and 1552 in response to doctrinal
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l6' n='N006'/>changes shows how widespread ownership of this clothing was. Because several parishes have
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l7' n='N007'/>both accounts (which record their purchase) and Edwardian lists (which record their sale), it is
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l8' n='N008'/>occasionally possible to identify the small garments bought and made earlier as those disposed
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l9' n='N009'/>of in mid–century. In 1521–2 the wardens of St Peter Westcheap had purchased material for
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l10' n='N010'/>the bishop&apos;s robe, two yards of red Bristol cloth, plus sarcenet for the hood, and had paid for
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l11' n='N011'/>making the costume, spending in all the considerable amount of I0s 6d for materials and
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l12' n='N012'/>construction (see p 60). It seems likely that when in 1548–0 the parish sold its St Nicholas
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l13' n='N013'/>coat for 20d, that is, less than 2s, it was the same piece described with so much detail in their
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l14' n='N014'/>earlier accounts (see p 112).
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l15' n='N015'/>Provincial parish records do not register such enthusiasm for the boy bishop. In part, at
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l16' n='N016'/>least, London&apos;s wide investment in this custom may be explained by the cathedral&apos;s presence
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l17' n='N017'/>and its recognized status as a touchstone of liturgical practice. It may be too that the high
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l18' n='N018'/>incidence of boy bishops in the capital is connected, either as cause or effect, with London&apos;s
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l19' n='N019'/>development of parish childrens choirs (see Appendix I0). Since eleven parishes register the
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l20' n='N020'/>presence of boy bishops between 1400 and 1500, we might wonder whether the parish boys
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l21' n='N021'/>choirs now visible only from the end of the fifteenth century might have been present earlier.
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l22' n='N022'/>The surprisingly widespread nature of the custom probably lies behind London&apos;s 1538
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l23' n='N023'/>mayoral injunction against it, which places the site of disorder in the parish (see Appendix 3)
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l24' n='N024'/>The order complains of the gret cost£৳ &amp; charg£৳ of many honest p£৲sones in making Bankett£৳
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l25' n='N025'/>to the Clerk£৳ &amp; priest£৳ but also to the great dysquyeting of the said p$৲ysshyon£৲৳. The
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l26' n='N026'/>aldermen are commanded to see that parish staff, curates, parsons, and parish clerks, doo not
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l27' n='N027'/>deck tryme or sett fourth any chyld, nether to be sett in any place w€t₽in the churche nor to
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l28' n='N028'/>goo abowte the p$৲yshe. St Nicholas bishop was a powerful symbol of traditional belief and
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l29' n='N029'/>practices (Machyn calls it ye old ffassyon) and in the royal suppression of these practices that
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l30' n='N030'/>followed the mayor&apos;s command three years later, in 1541, it is possible to see the reformers
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l31' n='N031'/>distaste for this excrescence on the liturgy, its playful foolishness expressing all too well the old
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l32' n='N032'/>religion&apos;s impurities. Such a position may lie behind the civic command as well, yet the mayoral
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l33' n='N033'/>language stresses the customs nuisance quotient, for which the parish clergy are held responsible
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l34' n='N034'/>at a moment when liturgical reform had not yet firmly taken hold.
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l35' n='N035'/>Dueen Mary revived the custom in 1554 about a month before its December observance:
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l36' n='N036'/>on 13 November Bishop Edmund Bonner issued a permission to all priests of his London
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l37' n='N037'/>diocese. Machyn, the only witness, says the permission was rescinded, but that the ceremony
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l38' n='N038'/>was observed in divers Parishes, then, and again in 1556. Nuisance, or even crime, is invoked
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l39' n='N039'/>again in the latter year when the conservative Dr Francis Mallett, master of St katharines
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l40' n='N040'/>Hospital, asked a reforming parishioner, Gertrude Crokhay, why she refused the boy bishop
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l41' n='N041'/>entrance. Crokhay replied, Twas a frayd of them that came with hym to haue had my purse
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l42' n='N042'/>cut by them. For I haue harde of men robbed by S. Nicolas clerks (see p 136). Lest we think
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l43' n='N043'/>this is merely Crokhays Protestantism speaking we should note that three years earlier, in
				<lb facs='#facs_10_r1l44' n='N044'/>1553, Thomas Wilson&apos;s A৲૱£ of R฿£૱¢৲€₯ describes this class: they are no Churchmen, they are
			</p>
			<pb n='11'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxvii
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l3' n='N003'/>maisterlesse men, or rather S. Nicolas Clarkes that lacke liuing. S As in the 1538 civic order two
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l4' n='N004'/>decades before, Crokhay&apos;s reply charges the old ceremonies with the production of disorder.
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l5' n='N005'/>Palm Sunday Prophet:
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l6' n='N006'/>London parochial involvement with this elaborated festival liturgy is extensive, though Palm
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l7' n='N007'/>Sunday prophets were not nearly so popular as were boy bishops.s€ Thirteen London parishes,
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l8' n='N008'/>about half of those having pre–1558 records, embellished their Palm Sunday liturgy with
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l9' n='N009'/>procession and with dramatization of the liturgical texts, in which boys and adult men played
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l10' n='N010'/>(and sang) the Old Testament prophets. In the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries parishes rented
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l11' n='N011'/>costumes, wigs, and props for prophets, and paid to build scaffolds for them to stand on.s The
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l12' n='N012'/>full presentation of what nevertheless remained a liturgical celebration might even include a
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l13' n='N013'/>scenic backdrop: St Margaret, Southwark, possessed a stained, or painted, cloth of [erusalem
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l14' n='N014'/>for use on Palm Sunday. A lost payment for playing the prophet has been cited from 1451
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l15' n='N015'/>the earliest reference (see p 27), while records of Palm Sunday carpentry survive from 1486 to
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l16' n='N016'/>1400 (and perhaps earlier), but the celebration&apos;s heyday came in the early sixteenth century
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l17' n='N017'/>and it continued until Elizabeth&apos;s accession. 6
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l18' n='N018'/>The Sarum liturgy for Palm Sunday was indeed quasi৳mimetic. Before mass and after the
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l19' n='N019'/>blessing of palms the priest, followed by choir and people, made his way outside to the church*
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l20' n='N020'/>yard cross, where the deacon read the gospel account of Christ&apos;s entry into ]erusalem. &amp; This
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l21' n='N021'/>procession of priest and parishioners represented the crowd welcoming Christ to the city. As
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l22' n='N022'/>the concluding words of the gospel were uttered, Blessed is he who comes in the name of the
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l23' n='N023'/>Lord, a second procession, carrying the sacrament and symbolizing Christ and the disciples,
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l24' n='N024'/>emerged from the church and met the first one. At this moment when Christ and the crowd
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l25' n='N025'/>met symbolically, three men standing on scaffolds– the prophets– sang three short texts
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l26' n='N026'/>of welcome.
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l27' n='N027'/>Four parishes rented costumes (called either garments or raiment) for the adult prophets:
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l28' n='N028'/>Sts Dunstan in the East and West, St Mary at Hill, and St Mary Magdalen Milk Street (which
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l29' n='N029'/>mounted a more complex production on Palm Sunday that will be discussed below). St Magnus
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l30' n='N030'/>was wealthy enough to own the costumes it used. Under Edward vi it listed fyve garment£৳
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l31' n='N031'/>for p৲¢phett£৳ w€t฿ fyve collers &amp; V crownet£৳ and v heres thereto belonging./ At St Mary
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l32' n='N032'/>Woolnoth and St Michael le Cuerne the pynnes to dresse profitt£৳ show there were costumed
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l33' n='N033'/>prophets in these parishes as well, although their costumes were likely to have been liturgical
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l34' n='N034'/>vestments, adjusted in this standard way.
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l35' n='N035'/>Three parishes rented wigs (hairs) for prophets: St Mary at Hill, St Peter Westcheap, and
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l36' n='N036'/>St Stephen Walbrook (1522 to 1534). St Stephen got its wigs in 1531 from ]ohn English, one
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l37' n='N037'/>of Henry V11&apos;s players at least since 1494, sometimes the troupes leader, and paid as a member
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l38' n='N038'/>until 1531, the year in which St Stephen rented from him.ss In addition St Margaret Lothbury
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l39' n='N039'/>in 1540 sold iij heres (see p 112).
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l40' n='N040'/>St Andrew Hubbard and St Mary at Hill rented Palm Sunday hangings from the royal
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l41' n='N041'/>wardrobe in the Tower. These hangings were a staple decorative element on public occasions
				<lb facs='#facs_11_r1l42' n='N042'/>and were sometimes rented by parishes for royal entries. That parishes drew on royal stores
			</p>
			<pb n='12'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l1' n='N001'/>5
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l2' n='N002'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l3' n='N003'/>xxviii
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l4' n='N004'/>to augment their theatrical resources is not surprising, but the borrowings could go in the
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l5' n='N005'/>other direction as well, as when the office of the revels borrowed frames from St Sepulchres
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l6' n='N006'/>parish. The movement of liturgy toward drama was intensified by the parish purchase of
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l7' n='N007'/>identifying scrolls, boards, or labels with the prophets names (St Dunstan in the West, St Martin
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l8' n='N008'/>Orgar, St Mary at Hill, St Mary Magdalen Milk Street, and St Stephen Walbrook).
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l9' n='N009'/>The Palm Sunday celebration at St Mary Magdalen Milk Street, a well–off parish with a
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l10' n='N010'/>substantial number of mercer parishioners, was more elaborate than other displays of prophetic
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l11' n='N011'/>witnesS. Its expenditure of Ss in 1535–6 for prophets garments is substantial: more typical
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l12' n='N012'/>would be I2d or 16d. The play&apos;s scope was larger as well because it included not only Christs
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l13' n='N013'/>[erusalem entry (there were payments for the man who led God&apos;s horse) but also the Crucifixion
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l14' n='N014'/>(payments for Longinus, the blind centurion, and for liquid that ran out of the cross).0 What
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l15' n='N015'/>Milk Street offered was a Passion play, one not freestanding but springing out of the liturgy of
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l16' n='N016'/>Palm Sunday and moving forward through the events of Christ&apos;s death.
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l17' n='N017'/>Payment for carpentry precedes the other expenses for wigs, costumes, and props, and Palm
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l18' n='N018'/>Sunday playing may come as early as 1468 if St Michael Cornhill&apos;s two hurdles (supporting
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l19' n='N019'/>cross–bars) for stages for the church wall were really intended to hold Palm Sunday prophets
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l20' n='N020'/>(see p 30). St Andrew Hubbard&apos;s payments for frame and workmanship over the church door
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l21' n='N021'/>(1485–6, 1452–3) are later elucidated by St Mary at Hill&apos;s 1525 payment for a quarter of
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l22' n='N022'/>board for the frame over the north door p$t is for pe p৲¢fett£৳ on palmesonday.
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l23' n='N023'/>Palm Sunday dramatic celebrations, as revealed by parish carpentry, thus may begin in the
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l24' n='N024'/>last quarter of the fifteenth century and they run through spring 1546. Henry VII1 died in
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l25' n='N025'/>]anuary 154677: after a hiatus under Edward, Mary&apos;s reinstitution of traditional liturgical
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l26' n='N026'/>celebrations like processions and holy days, on 20 December 1553 and 4 March 1553/4, was
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l27' n='N027'/>carried out with alacrity.: That spring St Dunstan in the West bought three bills (labels) for
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l28' n='N028'/>prophets and St Mary Woolnoth purchased girdles, needles, thread, and palms, but the celebra*
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l29' n='N029'/>tions disappeared again under Elizabeth
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l30' n='N030'/>In the late fifteenth and early sixteenth centuries this symbolism supported a particular
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l31' n='N031'/>religious point of view, as the issue of the eucharistic real presence became increasingly contro
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l32' n='N032'/>versial. The Palm Sunday ceremonies were strongly associated with traditional belief in the
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l33' n='N033'/>sacrament. In them the displayed host was identified with the historic Christ of Palm Sunday
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l34' n='N034'/>and was greeted, reverenced, and welcomed with music and spectacle. These practices developed,
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l35' n='N035'/>in London at least, when that belief was under attack, and in their musical, dramatized, litur
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l36' n='N036'/>gical display of the sacrament they represent the response of orthodoxy to a theological challenge
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l37' n='N037'/>Other Parish Plays
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l38' n='N038'/>On other occasions besides Palm Sunday the tendency of the liturgy to dramatic realization can
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l39' n='N039'/>be seen. In 1539/40 St Mary Woolnoth rented hairs, garlands, and lamps for five virgins to play
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l40' n='N040'/>on All Hallows Day, and it may be that the parable of the wise and foolish virgins (Mt 13. 1–25)
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l41' n='N041'/>was thought appropriate for celebration on this feast of the saved (see p 96). When Mary was
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l42' n='N042'/>on the throne in 1557 Machyn recorded a Passion play at the Greyfriars, but whether it was
				<lb facs='#facs_12_r1l43' n='N043'/>liturgical or not is unclear, and in the same year St Olave Silver Street (Monkwell Street)
			</p>
			<pb n='13'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxix
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l3' n='N003'/>offered a Stage–Play, of a goodly Matter– which might be either a religious or a secular play
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l4' n='N004'/>(see p 136).
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l5' n='N005'/>PARISH CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l6' n='N006'/>Hocking
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l7' n='N007'/>Six London parishes show receipts for hocking collections: at four of them the practice begar
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l8' n='N008'/>in the fifteenth century. These collections provided both fun and money for the parish on the
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l9' n='N009'/>second Monday and Tuesday after Easter. On alternate days the women and men stopped and
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l10' n='N010'/>bound each other in order to extract playful fines.*
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l11' n='N011'/>Civic sources predate the parish records and show that hocking was being practised in
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l12' n='N012'/>London from the beginning of the fifteenth century. Between 1406 and 1438 the citys Letter
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l13' n='N013'/>Books I and X include fifteen injunctions issued by the mayor and aldermen against hocking
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l14' n='N014'/>in this context a rowdy, public disturbance. The brief, formulaic character of the commands,
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l15' n='N015'/>coming as they do every two or three years and forbidding citizens to force others to join in
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l16' n='N016'/>hocking, speaks of the routine maintenance of order. Strangely the remaining fifteenth–century
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l17' n='N017'/>Letter Book L (through 1457) does not mention this practice (though a reference from 1446
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l18' n='N018'/>forbids hocking during Margaret of Anjou&apos;s arrival in London). Hence it may be that the
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l19' n='N019'/>earliest surviving mentions of hocking under parish auspices in the 1450s signal a change in
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l20' n='N020'/>its function if not its nature: the domestication of disorder and the taming of its character
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l21' n='N021'/>under institutional supervision. As katherine French points out the rise of hocking came at
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l22' n='N022'/>a point when the parish was increasing its influence in late medieval society.76 Although it
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l23' n='N023'/>was preceded by a 1450 letter condemning hocking, sent from Bishop [ohn Carpenter of
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l24' n='N024'/>Worcester to the priests and people of his diocese, and by the 1455 occurrence of hocking at
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l25' n='N025'/>St Margaret, Southwark, the record in 1457 from All Hallows on London Wall (two years after
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l26' n='N026'/>their accounts begin) is certainly one of the earliest instances of parish hocking anywhere.
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l27' n='N027'/>All Hallows on London Wall&apos;s Hocktide receipts run irregularly from 1457–8 to 1528–0.
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l28' n='N028'/>Both men and women collected here in 1457–8 and in 1500–11. But the record also provides
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l29' n='N029'/>instances of wives gathering alone and it gives the names of three women who handed over
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l30' n='N030'/>Hocktide collections. Since all three were the wives of wardens it appears that their husbands
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l31' n='N031'/>positions gave them a degree of official responsibility for gathering. In 1457–8 money was
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l32' n='N032'/>received from Botelers wyf whose husband William was a warden in that year and served
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l33' n='N033'/>both an earlier and a later term of office. The wife of Simon Pratt appears as a collector in
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l34' n='N034'/>1477–8: her husband was a warden then and would be again in 1482–5. ]ohn Webbe served
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l35' n='N035'/>in an undated year between 1512 and 1528, when his wife turned in a substantial sum in hock
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l36' n='N036'/>money. That the responsibility for the parish&apos;s financial well–being was shared by this group
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l37' n='N037'/>of men and women (and that it was not confined only to Hocktide gatherings) is shown
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l38' n='N038'/>by an All Hallows on London Wall account entry for 1480–2 which notes that over 21s
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l39' n='N039'/>were received in Gaderyng of almes toward the chirch werks by the churchwardens and
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l40' n='N040'/>their wives.*
				<lb facs='#facs_13_r1l41' n='N041'/>Hocking at St Nicholas Shambles is illustrated by a single reference from 1464–5, when
			</p>
			<pb n='14'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxx
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l3' n='N003'/>the large sum of 20s 4d was received from a variety of sources including maye money and
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l4' n='N004'/>hoctydemoney (see p 20). All Hallows Stainings exclusively female hocking is recorded in the
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l5' n='N005'/>last decade of the fifteenth century and the first decade of the sixteenth. Receipts in 1508–10
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l6' n='N006'/>show that the wives of this parish collected in the hystrete, that is, in the broad street just north
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l7' n='N007'/>of their church leading to Aldgate (the present Fenchurch Street), and in blankechapulton,
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l8' n='N008'/>a liberty east of the church that in the fifteenth century had developed into one of the havens
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l9' n='N009'/>where debtors, aliens, and foreigners could practise their trades immune from crast supervision.
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l10' n='N010'/>As a reward for their work in 1451–2 the parish underwrote a wives dinner which cost over
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l11' n='N011'/>8s, a women&apos;s festival at which meat, cheese, and bread were bought to provide a drynkyng
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l12' n='N012'/>with harp music for the triumphant collectors (see p 37). St Mary at Hill paid much less for
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l13' n='N013'/>a similar feast in 1406–7, 1467–8, 1458–0, and 1409–1500, spending between Dd and 16d
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l14' n='N014'/>each year
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l15' n='N015'/>Although St Andrew Hubbard&apos;s accounts begin in 1454, the first hocking entry comes only
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l16' n='N016'/>in 1521–2 and the second in 1528–8: the collectors are female or unspecified. Such late and
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l17' n='N017'/>scanty evidence in the accounts leads Clive Burgess to suggest that hocking funds might
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l18' n='N018'/>ordinarily have been entrusted to the care of senior members of the parish other than church.
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l19' n='N019'/>wardens, and to imply that hocking was probably more frequent at St Andrew than these
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l20' n='N020'/>records can reveal.s
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l21' n='N021'/>St Mary at Hill&apos;s accounts provide the fullest picture of the practice, showing a remarkably
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l22' n='N022'/>persistent run of hocking receipts for over thirty years, from 1406–7 to 1527–8, with both
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l23' n='N023'/>male and female collectors. Usually the women&apos;s receipts for Hock Monday are two, three,
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l24' n='N024'/>four, or even five times that of the men&apos;s for Hock Tuesday, as in 1504–5 when the women
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l25' n='N025'/>gathered over 33s, the men over 8s, or in 1511–12 when 20s was the women&apos;s total, versus
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l26' n='N026'/>4s for the men. As at All Hallows on London Wall some women&apos;s names are given: in 1522
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l27' n='N027'/>Goodwife Wall appears when her husband ]ohn Wall was in office, and later the wife of Robert
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l28' n='N028'/>Averey, a warden in 1522–3 and 1523–4, is mentioned. Amounts as large as 18s or 20s were
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l29' n='N029'/>sometimes kept back for a year or two, and summonses to turn in the gains had to be issued,
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l30' n='N030'/>as in February 1520/I when the accounts carry the following memo: It£m that the money that
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l31' n='N031'/>is gadered on hokmonday And hoktweysday for ij yer£৳ p$t is past be called in to pis Acompte
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l32' n='N032'/>(see p 57).
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l33' n='N033'/>These payments show the contribution hocking could make to parish liturgical and ceremo
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l34' n='N034'/>nial life. On 13 February 1521/2 St Mary at Hill agreed that five separate parcels of money,
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l35' n='N035'/>four of them hock collections, would go toward the organs. Three of these parcels were for
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l36' n='N036'/>unspecified amounts, but two were for Ss and for 13S. In 1521/2 the parishioners then paid
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l37' n='N037'/>10s 8d for the organs and their transportation, besides that was gaderid, which suggests that
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l38' n='N038'/>it was largely hocking that provided the new organs.
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l39' n='N039'/>St Mary&apos;s hocking concluded with a careful accounting, dated 28 April 1528, of money
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l40' n='N040'/>collected in that year and the previous one. The total was something over E4. Their dis
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l41' n='N041'/>continuing of this practice –or at least its absence from the records– came at exactly the same
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l42' n='N042'/>time as that of All Hallows on London Wall and St Andrew Hubbard. In all three parishes
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l43' n='N043'/>spring 1528 was the last occurrence of hocking, perhaps because the 1520s were a time of
				<lb facs='#facs_14_r1l44' n='N044'/>unusual economic deprivation which saw in London three visitations of the plague as well.৳
			</p>
			<pb n='15'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l1' n='N001'/>DRAMA, MUSIC, AND CEREMONIAL CUSTOMS
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l2' n='N002'/>xxxi
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l3' n='N003'/>One final example comes from Mary&apos;s reign: at St Botolph without Aldgate in 1554–5 certain
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l4' n='N004'/>women of the parish gathered the large sum of 20s which was spent on a Crosse clothe.
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l5' n='N005'/>Hocking has traditionally been classified as rural or at least regional. Hutton says that it was
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l6' n='N006'/>not much used in the capital, its classic home being a provincial town.8 Evidence for the
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l7' n='N007'/>custom at these six London parishes however establishes hocking as definitely urban as well
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l8' n='N008'/>Though St Botolph without Aldgate was situated at the citys eastern edge and All Hallows on
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l9' n='N009'/>London Wall on its northern wall, the other four parishes are not peripheral ones. St Nicholas
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l10' n='N010'/>Shambles lay just north of St Paul&apos;s Cathedral while St Mary at Hill and St Andrew Hubbard
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l11' n='N011'/>were located in the city centre very close to each other, with All Hallows Staining not far off.s৳
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l12' n='N012'/>Maying
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l13' n='N013'/>]ohn Stow&apos;s wellknown description of London&apos;s maying sets it firmly within the parish and
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l14' n='N014'/>provides it with maypoles, martial displays, and morris dancers in the day, and plays and bon–
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l15' n='N015'/>fires in the evening (see pp 51–2). Stow&apos;s tone is antiquarian like that of the 1584 collections
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l16' n='N016'/>of St Andrew Holborn&apos;s churchwarden, Thomas Bentley, which similarly stress parochial
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l17' n='N017'/>community and conviviality. Maying in the parish accounts appears both early and late but
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l18' n='N018'/>not widely. Based on references from St Andrew Hubbard (1459–61, perhaps 1510–12) and
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l19' n='N019'/>from St Nicholas Shambles (1458, 1463, 1465) it seems mainly a fifteenth–century affair
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l20' n='N020'/>though in 1535–6 St Botolph without Aldersgate received 4s 4d from children who made
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l21' n='N021'/>a May game for the church, and Stows story of the reformers destruction of St Andrew
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l22' n='N022'/>Undershaft&apos;s maypole in 1540 is familiar (see pp 114–15). It is the 1550s however, reflected in
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l23' n='N023'/>Henry Machyn&apos;s diary, that produce a cascade of May references. Anne Lancashire has suggesteo
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l24' n='N024'/>that in this decade following the discontinuance of the Midsummer Watch in the 1540s.
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l25' n='N025'/>elaborate May games may have become Watch substitutes, since they share the same elements:
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l26' n='N026'/>guns, drums, morris dancers, and giants.5 Later in 1500 the parish clerk of St Botolph without
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l27' n='N027'/>Aldgate tells the tragic story of a young man who died of gunpowder burns from a May game
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l28' n='N028'/>not a parishioner but fatally injured within the parish (see p 161).
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l29' n='N029'/>Robin Hood games, often a staple of May celebration, were always associated with a con*
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l30' n='N030'/>servative religious and social position. When around 1535 Sir Richard Morrison urged Henry vII
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l31' n='N031'/>to sponsor anti–papal plays, Morrison suggested these should replace the lewd and ribald plays
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l32' n='N032'/>of Robin Hood found everywhere.5 Conversely when Bishop Stephen Gardiner, about ten years
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l33' n='N033'/>later, told the players of London to stick to plays of Robin Hood and Little ]ohn, he meant
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l34' n='N034'/>they should offer traditional inoffensive amusements as opposed to the reforming plays
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l35' n='N035'/>recommended by Morrison (see p 104). That London parishes hosted Robin Hood plays, or
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l36' n='N036'/>at least festivities, is confirmed by the Edwardian inventory of Holy Trinity the Less, which
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l37' n='N037'/>lists fifteen Robin Hood coats (see p 123).
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l38' n='N038'/>Pageants
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l39' n='N039'/>An important part of parish festivities, though less firmly tied to a particular occasion in the
				<lb facs='#facs_15_r1l40' n='N040'/>liturgical year, were parish pageants. The London records associate them with three occasions
			</p>
			<pb n='16'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l42' n='N042'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l43' n='N043'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_16_r1l44' n='N044'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='17'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l42' n='N042'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l43' n='N043'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l44' n='N044'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_17_r1l45' n='N045'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='18'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l42' n='N042'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_18_r1l43' n='N043'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='19'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_19_r1l40' n='N040'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='20'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_20_r1l39' n='N039'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='21'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l42' n='N042'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l43' n='N043'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_21_r1l44' n='N044'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='22'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l42' n='N042'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l43' n='N043'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l44' n='N044'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_22_r1l45' n='N045'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='23'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l42' n='N042'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l43' n='N043'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l44' n='N044'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l45' n='N045'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l46' n='N046'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l47' n='N047'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r1l48' n='N048'/>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_23_r2l1' n='N001'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='24'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_24_r1l1' n='N001'/>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_24_r2l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_24_r2l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_24_r2l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_24_r2l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_24_r2l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_24_r2l6' n='N006'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='25'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_25_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_25_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_25_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_25_r1l4' n='N004'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='26'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l42' n='N042'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_26_r1l43' n='N043'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='27'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_27_r1l42' n='N042'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='28'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_28_r1l42' n='N042'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='29'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_29_r1l42' n='N042'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='30'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l41' n='N041'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l42' n='N042'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l43' n='N043'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_30_r1l44' n='N044'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='31'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l39' n='N039'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l40' n='N040'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_31_r1l41' n='N041'/>
			</p>
			<pb n='32'/>
			<p>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l1' n='N001'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l2' n='N002'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l3' n='N003'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l4' n='N004'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l5' n='N005'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l6' n='N006'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l7' n='N007'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l8' n='N008'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l9' n='N009'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l10' n='N010'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l11' n='N011'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l12' n='N012'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l13' n='N013'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l14' n='N014'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l15' n='N015'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l16' n='N016'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l17' n='N017'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l18' n='N018'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l19' n='N019'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l20' n='N020'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l21' n='N021'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l22' n='N022'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l23' n='N023'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l24' n='N024'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l25' n='N025'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l26' n='N026'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l27' n='N027'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l28' n='N028'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l29' n='N029'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l30' n='N030'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l31' n='N031'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l32' n='N032'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l33' n='N033'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l34' n='N034'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l35' n='N035'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l36' n='N036'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l37' n='N037'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l38' n='N038'/>
				<lb facs='#facs_32_r1l39' n='N039'/>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
